1 Corinthians 2

1 And so, brothers, when I came to you, announcing to you the testimony of Christ, I did not bring exalted words or lofty wisdom.

2 For I did not judge myself to know anything among you, except Jesus Christ, and him crucified.

3 And I was with you in weakness, and in fear, and with much trembling.

4 And my words and preaching were not the persuasive words of human wisdom, but were a manifestation of the Spirit and of virtue,

5 so that your faith would not be based on the wisdom of men, but on the virtue of God.

6 Now, we do speak wisdom among the perfect, yet truly, this is not the wisdom of this age, nor that of the leaders of this age, which shall be reduced to nothing.

7 Instead, we speak of the wisdom of God in a mystery which has been hidden, which God predestined before this age for our glory,

8 something that none of the leaders of this world have known. For if they had known it, they would never have crucified the Lord of glory.

9 But this is just as it has been written: "The eye has not seen, and the ear has not heard, nor has it entered into the heart of man, what things God has prepared for those who love him."

10 But God has revealed these things to us through his Spirit. For the Spirit searches all things, even the depths of God.

11 And who can know the things that are of a man, except the spirit which is within that man? So also, no one knows the things which are of God, except the Spirit of God.

12 But we have not received the spirit of this world, but the Spirit who is of God, so that we may understand the things that have been given to us by God.

13 And we are also speaking of these things, not in the learned words of human wisdom, but in the doctrine of the Spirit, bringing spiritual things together with spiritual things.

14 But the animal nature of man does not perceive these things that are of the Spirit of God. For it is foolishness to him, and he is not able to understand it, because it must be examined spiritually.

15 But the spiritual nature of man judges all things, and he himself may be judged by no man.

16 For who has known the mind of the Lord, so that he may instruct him? But we have the mind of Christ.

1 Corinthians 3

1 And so, brothers, I was not able to speak to you as if to those who are spiritual, but rather as if to those who are carnal. For you are like infants in Christ.

2 I gave you milk to drink, not solid food. For you were not yet able. And indeed, even now, you are not able; for you are still carnal.

3 And since there is still envy and contention among you, are you not carnal, and are you not walking according to man?

4 For if one says, "Certainly, I am of Paul," while another says, "I am of Apollo," are you not men? But what is Apollo, and what is Paul?

5 We are only the ministers of him in whom you have believed, just as the Lord has granted to each of you.

6 I planted, Apollo watered, but God provided the growth.

7 And so, neither he who plants, nor he who waters, is anything, but only God, who provides the growth.

8 Now he who plants, and he who waters, are one. But each shall receive his proper reward, according to his labors.

9 For we are God's assistants. You are God's cultivation; you are God's construction.

10 According to the grace of God, which has been given to me, I have laid the foundation like a wise architect. But another builds upon it. So then, let each one be careful how he builds upon it.

11 For no one is able to lay any other foundation, in place of that which has been laid, which is Christ Jesus.

12 But if anyone builds upon this foundation, whether gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, or stubble,

13 each one's work shall be made manifest. For the day of the Lord shall declare it, because it will be revealed by fire. And this fire will test each one's work, as to what kind it is.

14 If anyone's work, which he has built upon it, remains, then he will receive a reward.

15 If anyone's work is burned up, he will suffer its loss, but he himself will still be saved, but only as through fire.

16 Do you not know that you are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God lives within you?

17 But if anyone violates the Temple of God, God will destroy him. For the Temple of God is holy, and you are that Temple.

18 Let no one deceive himself. If anyone among you seems to be wise in this age, let him become foolish, so that he may be truly wise.

19 For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God. And so it has been written: "I will catch the wise in their own astuteness."

20 And again: "The Lord knows the thoughts of the wise, that they are vain."

21 And so, let no one glory in men.

22 For all is yours: whether Paul, or Apollo, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or the present, or the future. Yes, all is yours.

23 But you are Christ's, and Christ is God's.

1 Corinthians 4

1 Accordingly, let man consider us to be ministers of Christ and attendants of the mysteries of God.

2 Here and now, it is required of attendants that each one be found to be faithful.

3 But as for me, it is such a small thing to be judged by you, or by the age of mankind. And neither do I judge myself.

4 For I have nothing on my conscience. But I am not justified by this. For the Lord is the One who judges me.

5 And so, do not choose to judge before the time, until the Lord returns. He will illuminate the hidden things of the darkness, and he will make manifest the decisions of hearts. And then each one shall have praise from God.

6 And so, brothers, I have presented these things in myself and in Apollo, for your sakes, so that you may learn, through us, that no one should be inflated against one person and for another, not beyond what has been written.

7 For what distinguishes you from another? And what do you have that you have not received? But if you have received it, why do you glory, as if you had not received it?

8 So, now you have been filled, and now you have been made wealthy, as if to reign without us? But I wish that you would reign, so that we, too, might reign with you!

9 For I think that God has presented us as the last Apostles, as those destined for death. For we have been made into a spectacle for the world, and for Angels, and for men.

10 So we are fools because of Christ, but you are discerning in Christ? We are weak, but you are strong? You are noble, but we are ignoble?

11 Even to this very hour, we hunger and thirst, and we are naked and repeatedly beaten, and we are unsteady.

12 And we labor, working with our own hands. We are slandered, and so we bless. We suffer and endure persecution.

13 We are cursed, and so we pray. We have become like the refuse of this world, like the reside of everything, even until now.

14 I am not writing these things in order to confound you, but in order to admonish you, as my dearest sons.

15 For you might have ten thousand instructors in Christ, but not so many fathers. For in Christ Jesus, through the Gospel, I have begotten you.

16 Therefore, I beg you, be imitators of me, just as I am of Christ.

17 For this reason, I have sent you Timothy, who is my dearest son, and who is faithful in the Lord. He will remind you of my ways, which are in Christ Jesus, just as I teach everywhere, in every church.

18 Certain persons have become inflated in thinking that I would not return to you.

19 But I will return to you soon, if the Lord is willing. And I will consider, not the words of those who are inflated, but the virtue.

20 For the kingdom of God is not in words, but in virtue.

21 What would you prefer? Should I return to you with a rod, or with charity and a spirit of meekness?

1 Corinthians 5

1 Above all else, it is being said that there is fornication among you, even fornication of a such kind that is not among the Gentiles, so that someone would have the wife of his father.

2 And yet you are inflated, and you have not instead been grieved, so that he who has done this thing would be taken away from your midst.

3 Certainly, though absent in body, I am present in spirit. Thus, I have already judged, as if I were present, him who has done this.

4 In the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, you have been gathered together with my spirit, in the power of our Lord Jesus,

5 to hand over such a one as this to Satan, for the destruction of the flesh, so that the spirit may be saved in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.

6 It is not good for you to glory. Do you not know that a little leaven corrupts the entire mass?

7 Purge the old leaven, so that you may become the new bread, for you are unleavened. For Christ, our Passover, has now been immolated.

8 And so, let us feast, not with the old leaven, not with the leaven of malice and wickedness, but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth.

9 As I have written to you in an epistle: "Do not associate with fornicators,"

10 certainly not with the fornicators of this world, nor with the greedy, nor with robbers, nor with the servants of idolatry. Otherwise, you ought to depart from this world.

11 But now I have written to you: do not associate with anyone who is called a brother and yet is a fornicator, or greedy, or a servant of idolatry, or a slanderer, or inebriated, or a robber. With such a one as this, do not even take food.

12 For what have I to do with judging those who are outside? But do not even you yourselves judge those who are inside?

13 For those who are outside, God will judge. But send this evil person away from yourselves.

1 Corinthians 6

1 How is it that anyone of you, having a dispute against another, would dare to be judged before the iniquitous, and not before the saints?

2 Or do you not know that the saints from this age shall judge it? And if the world is to be judged by you, are you unworthy, then, to judge even the smallest matters?

3 Do you not know that we shall judge angels? How much more the things of this age?

4 Therefore, if you have matters to judge concerning this age, why not appoint those who are most contemptible in the Church to judge these things!

5 But I am speaking so as to shame you. Is there no one among you wise enough, so that he might be able to judge between his brothers?

6 Instead, brother contends against brother in court, and this before the unfaithful!

7 Now there is certainly an offense among you, beyond everything else, when you have court cases against one another. Should you not accept injury instead? Should you not endure being cheated instead?

8 But you are doing the injuring and the cheating, and this toward brothers!

9 Do you not know that the iniquitous will not possess the kingdom of God? Do not choose to wander astray. For neither fornicators, nor servants of idolatry, nor adulterers,

10 nor the effeminate, nor males who sleep with males, nor thieves, nor the avaricious, nor the inebriated, nor slanderers, nor the rapacious shall possess the kingdom of God.

11 And some of you were like this. But you have been absolved, but you have been sanctified, but you have been justified: all in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ and in the Spirit of our God.

12 All is lawful to me, but not all is expedient. All is lawful to me, but I will not be driven back by the authority of anyone.

13 Food is for the stomach, and the stomach is for food. But God shall destroy both the stomach and food. And the body is not for fornication, but rather for the Lord; and the Lord is for the body.

14 Truly, God has raised up the Lord, and he will raise us up by his power.

15 Do you not know that your bodies are a part of Christ? So then, should I take a part of Christ and make it a part of a harlot? Let it not be so!

16 And do you not know that whoever is joined to a harlot becomes one body? "For the two," he said, "shall be as one flesh."

17 But whoever is joined to the Lord is one spirit.

18 Flee from fornication. Every sin whatsoever that a man commits is outside of the body, but whoever fornicates, sins against his own body.

19 Or do you not know that your bodies are the Temple of the Holy Spirit, who is in you, whom you have from God, and that you are not your own?

20 For you have been bought at a great price. Glorify and carry God in your body.

1 Corinthians 7

1 Now concerning the things about which you wrote to me: It is good for a man not to touch a woman.

2 But, because of fornication, let each man have his own wife, and let each woman have her own husband.

3 A husband should fulfill his obligation to his wife, and a wife should also act similarly toward her husband.

4 It is not the wife, but the husband, who has power over her body. But, similarly also, it is not the husband, but the wife, who has power over his body.

5 So, do not fail in your obligations to one another, except perhaps by consent, for a limited time, so that you may empty yourselves for prayer. And then, return together again, lest Satan tempt you by means of your abstinence.

6 But I am saying this, neither as an indulgence, nor as a commandment.

7 For I would prefer it if you were all like myself. But each person has his proper gift from God: one in this way, yet another in that way.

8 But I say to the unmarried and to widows: It is good for them, if they would remain as they are, just as I also am.

9 But if they cannot restrain themselves, they should marry. For it is better to marry, than to be burned.

10 But to those who have been joined in matrimony, it is not I who commands you, but the Lord: a wife is not to separate from her husband.

11 But if she has separated from him, she must remain unmarried, or be reconciled to her husband. And a husband should not divorce his wife.

12 Concerning the rest, I am speaking, not the Lord. If any brother has an unbelieving wife, and she consents to live with him, he should not divorce her.

13 And if any woman has an unbelieving husband, and he consents to live with her, she should not divorce her husband.

14 For the unbelieving husband has been sanctified through the believing wife, and the unbelieving wife has been sanctified through the believing husband. Otherwise, your children would be unclean, whereas instead they are holy.

15 But if the unbeliever departs, let him depart. For a brother or sister cannot be made subject to servitude in this way. For God has called us to peace.

16 And how do you know, wife, whether you will save your husband? Or how do you know, husband, whether you will save your wife?

17 However, let each one walk just as the Lord has distributed to him, each one just as God has called him. And thus do I teach in all the churches.

18 Has any circumcised man been called? Let him not cover his circumcision. Has any uncircumcised man been called? Let him not be circumcised.

19 Circumcision is nothing, and uncircumcision is nothing; there is only the observance of the commandments of God.

20 Let each and every one remain in the same calling to which he was called.

21 Are you a servant who has been called? Do not be concerned about it. But if you ever have the ability to be free, make use of it.

22 For any servant who has been called in the Lord is free in the Lord. Similarly, any free person who has been called is a servant in Christ.

23 You have been bought with a price. Do not be willing to become the servants of men.

24 Brothers, let each one, in whatever state he was called, remain in that state with God.

25 Now, concerning virgins, I have no commandment from the Lord. But I give counsel, as one who has obtained the mercy of the Lord, so as to be faithful.

26 Therefore, I consider this to be good, because of the present necessity: that it is good for a man to be such as I am.

27 Are you bound to a wife? Do not seek to be freed. Are you free of a wife? Do not seek a wife.

28 But if you take a wife, you have not sinned. And if a virgin has married, she has not sinned. Even so, such as these will have the tribulation of the flesh. But I would spare you from this.

29 And so, this is what I say, brothers: The time is short. What remains of it is such that: those who have wives should be as if they had none;

30 and those who weep, as though they were not weeping; and those who rejoice, as if they were not rejoicing; and those who buy, as if they possessed nothing;

31 and those who use the things of this world, as if they were not using them. For the figure of this world is passing away.

32 But I would prefer you to be without worry. Whoever is without a wife is worried about the things of the Lord, as to how he may please God.

33 But whoever is with a wife is worried about the things of the world, as to how he may please his wife. And so, he is divided.

34 And the unmarried woman and the virgin think about the things that are of the Lord, so that she may be holy in body and in spirit. But she who is married thinks about the things that are of the world, as to how she may please her husband.

35 Furthermore, I am saying this for your own benefit, not in order to cast a snare over you, but toward whatever is honest and whatever may provide you with the ability to be without hindrance, so as to worship the Lord.

36 But if any man considers himself to seem dishonorable, concerning a virgin who is of adult age, and so it ought to be, he may do as he wills. If he marries her, he does not sin.

37 But if he has decided firmly in his heart, and he does not have any obligation, but only the power of his free will, and if he has judged this in his heart, to let her remain a virgin, he does well.

38 And so, he who joins with his virgin in matrimony does well, and he who does not join with her does better.

39 A woman is bound under the law for as long as her husband lives. But if her husband has died, she is free. She may marry whomever she wishes, but only in the Lord.

40 But she will be more blessed, if she remains in this state, in accord with my counsel. And I think that I, too, have the Spirit of God.

1 Corinthians 8

1 Now concerning those things that are sacrificed to idols: we know that we all have knowledge. Knowledge puffs up, but charity builds up.

2 But if anyone considers himself to know anything, he does not yet know in the way that he ought to know.

3 For if anyone loves God, he is known by him.

4 But as to the foods that are immolated to idols, we know that an idol in the world is nothing, and that no one is God, except One.

5 For although there are things that are called gods, whether in heaven or on earth, (if one even considers there to be many gods and many lords)

6 yet we know that there is only one God, the Father, from whom all things are, and in whom we are, and one Lord Jesus Christ, through whom all things are, and by whom we are.

7 But knowledge is not in everyone. For some persons, even now, with consent to an idol, eat what has been sacrificed to an idol. And their conscience, being infirm, becomes polluted.

8 Yet food does not commend us to God. For if we eat, we will not have more, and if we do not eat, we will not have less.

9 But be careful not to let your liberty become a cause of sin to those who are weak.

10 For if anyone sees someone with knowledge sitting down to eat in idolatry, will not his own conscience, being infirm, be emboldened to eat what has been sacrificed to idols?

11 And should an infirm brother perish by your knowledge, even though Christ died for him?

12 So when you sin in this way against the brothers, and you harm their weakened conscience, then you sin against Christ.

13 Because of this, if food leads my brother to sin, I will never eat meat, lest I lead my brother to sin.

1 Corinthians 9

1 Am I not free? Am I not an Apostle? Have I not seen Christ Jesus our Lord? Are you not my work in the Lord?

2 And if I am not an Apostle to others, yet still I am to you. For you are the seal of my Apostleship in the Lord.

3 My defense with those who question me is this:

4 Do we not have the authority to eat and to drink?

5 Do we not have the authority to travel around with a woman who is a sister, just as do the other Apostles, and the brothers of the Lord, and Cephas?

6 Or is it only myself and Barnabas who do not have the authority to act in this way?

7 Who has ever served as a soldier and paid his own stipend? Who plants a vineyard and does not eat from its produce? Who pastures a flock and does not drink from the milk of the flock?

8 Am I saying these things according to man? Or does the law not also say these things?

9 For it is written in the law of Moses: "You shall not bind the mouth of an ox, while it is treading out the grain." Is God here concerned with the oxen?

10 Or is he saying this, indeed, for our sake? These things were written specifically for us, because he who plows, ought to plow in hope, and he who threshes, too, in hope of receiving the produce.

11 If we have sown spiritual things in you, is it important if we harvest from your worldly things?

12 If others are sharers in this authority over you, why are we not more entitled? And yet we have not used this authority. Instead, we bear all things, lest we give any hindrance to the Gospel of Christ.

13 Do you not know that those who work in the holy place eat the things that are for the holy place, and that those who serve at the altar also share with the altar?

14 So, too, has the Lord ordained that those who announce the Gospel should live by the Gospel.

15 Yet I have used none of these things. And I have not written so that these things may be done for me. For it is better for me to die, rather than to let anyone empty out my glory.

16 For if I preach the Gospel, it is not glory for me. For an obligation has been laid upon me. And woe to me, if I do not preach the Gospel.

17 For if I do this willingly, I have a reward. But if I do this reluctantly, a dispensation is granted to me.

18 And what, then, would be my reward? So, when preaching the Gospel, I should give the Gospel without taking, so that I may not misuse my authority in the Gospel.

19 For when I was a free man to all, I made myself the servant of all, so that I might gain all the more.

20 And so, to the Jews, I became like a Jew, so that I might gain the Jews.

21 To those who are under the law, I became as if I were under the law, (though I was not under the law) so that I might gain those who were under the law. To those who were without the law, I became as if I were without the law, (though I was not without the law of God, being in the law of Christ) so that I might gain those who were without the law.

22 To the weak, I became weak, so that I might gain the weak. To all, I became all, so that I might save all.

23 And I do everything for the sake of the Gospel, so that I may become its partner.

24 Do you not know that, of those who run in a race, all of them, certainly, are runners, but only one achieves the prize. Similarly, you must run, so that you may achieve.

25 And one who competes in a contest abstains from all things. And they do this, of course, so that they may achieve a corruptible crown. But we do this, so that we may achieve what is incorruptible.

26 And so I run, but not with uncertainty. And so I fight, but not by flailing in the air.

27 Instead, I chastise my body, so as to redirect it into servitude. Otherwise, I might preach to others, but become myself an outcast.

1 Corinthians 10

1 For I do not want you to be ignorant, brothers, that our fathers were all under the cloud, and they all went across the sea.

2 And in Moses, they all were baptized, in the cloud and in the sea.

3 And they all ate of the same spiritual food.

4 And they all drank of the same spiritual drink. And so, they all were drinking of the spiritual rock seeking to obtain them; and that rock was Christ.

5 But with most of them, God was not well-pleased. For they were struck down in the desert.

6 Now these things were done as an example for us, so that we might not desire evil things, just as they desired.

7 And so, do not take part in idolatry, as some of them did, just as it was written: "The people sat down to eat and to drink, and then they rose up to amuse themselves."

8 And let us not commit fornication, as some of them fornicated, and so twenty-three thousand fell on one day.

9 And let us not tempt Christ, as some of them tempted, and so they perished by serpents.

10 And you should not murmur, as some of them murmured, and so they perished by the destroyer.

11 Now all of these things happened to them as an example, and so they have been written for our correction, because the final age has fallen upon us.

12 And so, whosoever considers himself to be standing, let him be careful not to fall.

13 Temptation should not take hold of you, except what is human. For God is faithful, and he will not permit you to be tempted beyond your ability. Instead, he will effect his Providence, even during temptation, so that you may be able to bear it.

14 Because of this, most beloved of mine, flee from the worship of idols.

15 Since I am speaking to those who are prudent, judge what I say for yourselves.

16 The cup of benediction that we bless, is it not a communion in the Blood of Christ? And the bread that we break, is it not a participation in the Body of the Lord?

17 Through the one bread, we, though many, are one body: all of us who are partakers of the one bread.

18 Consider Israel, according to the flesh. Are not those who eat from the sacrifices partakers of the altar?

19 What is next? Should I say that what is immolated to idols is anything? Or that the idol is anything?

20 But the things that the Gentiles immolate, they immolate to demons, and not to God. And I do not want you to become partakers with demons.

21 You cannot drink the cup of the Lord, and the cup of demons. You cannot be partakers of the table of the Lord, and partakers of the table of demons.

22 Or should we provoke the Lord to jealousy? Are we stronger than he is? All is lawful to me, but not all is expedient.

23 All is lawful to me, but not all is edifying.

24 Let no one seek for himself, but for others.

25 Whatever is sold in the market, you may eat, without asking questions for the sake of conscience.

26 "The earth and all its fullness belong to the Lord."

27 If you are invited by any unbelievers, and you are willing to go, you may eat whatever is set before you, without asking questions for the sake of conscience.

28 But if anyone says, "This has been sacrificed to idols," do not eat it, for the sake of the one who told you, and for the sake of conscience.

29 But I am referring to the conscience of the other person, not to yours. For why should my liberty be judged by the conscience of another?

30 If I partake with thanksgiving, why should I be slandered over that for which I give thanks?

31 Therefore, whether you eat or drink, or whatever else you may do, do everything for the glory of God.

32 Be without offense toward the Jews, and toward the Gentiles, and toward the Church of God,

33 just as I also, in all things, please everyone, not seeking what is best for myself, but what is best for many others, so that they may be saved.

1 Corinthians 11

1 Be imitators of me, as I also am of Christ.

2 Now I praise you, brothers, because you are mindful of me in everything, in such a way as to hold to my precepts as I have handed them down to you.

3 So I want you to know that the head of every man is Christ. But the head of woman is man. Yet truly, the head of Christ is God.

4 Every man praying or prophesying with his head covered disgraces his head.

5 But every woman praying or prophesying with her head not covered disgraces her head. For it is the same as if her head were shaven.

6 So if a woman is not veiled, let her hair be cut off. Truly then, if it is a disgrace for a woman to have her hair cut off, or to have her head shaven, then she should cover her head.

7 Certainly, a man ought not to cover his head, for he is the image and glory of God. But woman is the glory of man.

8 For man is not of woman, but woman is of man.

9 And indeed, man was not created for woman, but woman was created for man.

10 Therefore, a woman ought to have a sign of authority on her head, because of the Angels.

11 Yet truly, man would not exist without woman, nor would woman exist without man, in the Lord.

12 For just as woman came into existence from man, so also does man exist through woman. But all things are from God.

13 Judge for yourselves. Is it proper for a woman to pray to God unveiled?

14 Does not even nature herself teach you that, indeed, if a man grows his hair long, it is a disgrace for him?

15 Yet truly, if a woman grows her hair long, it is a glory for her, because her hair has been given to her as a covering.

16 But if anyone has a mind to be contentious, we have no such custom, nor does the Church of God.

17 Now I caution you, without praising, about this: that you assemble together, and not for better, but for worse.

18 First of all, indeed, I hear that when you assemble together in the church, there are schisms among you. And I believe this, in part.

19 For there must also be heresies, so that those who have been tested may be made manifest among you.

20 And so, when you assemble together as one, it is no longer in order to eat the Lord's supper.

21 For each one first takes his own supper to eat. And as a result, one person is hungry, while another is inebriated.

22 Do you not have houses, in which to eat and drink? Or do you have such contempt for the Church of God that you would confound those who do not have such contempt? What should I say to you? Should I praise you? I am not praising you in this.

23 For I have received from the Lord what I have also delivered to you: that the Lord Jesus, on the same night that he was handed over, took bread,

24 and giving thanks, he broke it, and said: "Take and eat. This is my body, which shall be given up for you. Do this in remembrance of me."

25 Similarly also, the cup, after he had eaten supper, saying: "This cup is the new covenant in my blood. Do this, as often as you drink it, in remembrance of me."

26 For whenever you eat this bread and drink this cup, you proclaim the death of the Lord, until he returns.

27 And so, whoever eats this bread, or drinks from the cup of the Lord, unworthily, shall be liable of the body and blood of the Lord.

28 But let a man examine himself, and, in this way, let him eat from that bread, and drink from that cup.

29 For whoever eats and drinks unworthily, eats and drinks a sentence against himself, not discerning it to be the body of the Lord.

30 As a result, many are weak and sick among you, and many have fallen asleep.

31 But if we ourselves were discerning, then certainly we would not be judged.

32 Yet when we are judged, we are being corrected by the Lord, so that we might not be condemned along with this world.

33 And so, my brothers, when you assemble together to eat, be attentive to one another.

34 If anyone is hungry, let him eat at home, so that you may not assemble together unto judgment. As for the rest, I will set it in order when I arrive.

1 Corinthians 12

1 Now concerning spiritual things, I do not want you to be ignorant, brothers.

2 You know that when you were Gentiles, you approached mute idols, doing what you were led to do.

3 Because of this, I would have you know that no one speaking in the Spirit of God utters a curse against Jesus. And no one is able to say that Jesus is Lord, except in the Holy Spirit.

4 Truly, there are diverse graces, but the same Spirit.

5 And there are diverse ministries, but the same Lord.

6 And there are diverse works, but the same God, who works everything in everyone.

7 However, the manifestation of the Spirit is given to each one toward what is beneficial.

8 Certainly, to one, through the Spirit, is given words of wisdom; but to another, according to the same Spirit, words of knowledge;

9 to another, in the same Spirit, faith; to another, in the one Spirit, the gift of healing;

10 to another, miraculous works; to another, prophecy; to another, the discernment of spirits; to another, different kinds of languages; to another, the interpretation of words.

11 But one and the same Spirit works all these things, distributing to each one according to his will.

12 For just as the body is one, and yet has many parts, so all the parts of the body, though they are many, are only one body. So also is Christ.

13 And indeed, in one Spirit, we were all baptized into one body, whether Jews or Gentiles, whether servant or free. And we all drank in the one Spirit.

14 For the body, too, is not one part, but many.

15 If the foot were to say, "Because I am not the hand, I am not of the body," would it then not be of the body?

16 And if the ear were to say, "Because I am not the eye, I am not of the body," would it then not be of the body?

17 If the whole body were the eye, how would it hear? If the whole were hearing, how would it smell?

18 But instead, God has placed the parts, each one of them, in the body, just as it has pleased him.

19 So if they were all one part, how would it be a body?

20 But instead, there are many parts, indeed, yet one body.

21 And the eye cannot say to the hand, "I have no need for your works." And again, the head cannot say to the feet, "You are of no use to me."

22 In fact, so much more necessary are those parts of the body which seem to be weaker.

23 And though we consider certain parts of the body to be less noble, we surround these with more abundant dignity, and so, those parts which are less presentable end up with more abundant respect.

24 However, our presentable parts have no such need, since God has tempered the body together, distributing the more abundant honor to that which has the need,

25 so that there might be no schism in the body, but instead the parts themselves might take care of one another.

26 And so, if one part suffers anything, all the parts suffer with it. Or, if one part finds glory, all the parts rejoice with it.

27 Now you are the body of Christ, and parts like any part.

28 And indeed, God has established a certain order in the Church: first Apostles, second Prophets, third Teachers, next miracle-workers, and then the grace of healing, of helping others, of governing, of different kinds of languages, and of the interpretation of words.

29 Are all Apostles? Are all Prophets? Are all Teachers?

30 Are all workers of miracles? Do all have the grace of healing? Do all speak in tongues? Do all interpret?

31 But be zealous for the better charisms. And I reveal to you a yet more excellent way.

1 Corinthians 13

1 If I were to speak in the language of men, or of Angels, yet not have charity, I would be like a clanging bell or a crashing cymbal.

2 And if I have prophecy, and learn every mystery, and obtain all knowledge, and possess all faith, so that I could move mountains, yet not have charity, then I am nothing.

3 And if I distribute all my goods in order to feed the poor, and if I hand over my body to be burned, yet not have charity, it offers me nothing.

4 Charity is patient, is kind. Charity does not envy, does not act wrongly, is not inflated.

5 Charity is not ambitious, does not seek for itself, is not provoked to anger, devises no evil.

6 Charity does not rejoice over iniquity, but rejoices in truth.

7 Charity suffers all, believes all, hopes all, endures all.

8 Charity is never torn away, even if prophecies pass away, or languages cease, or knowledge is destroyed.

9 For we know only in part, and we prophesy only in part.

10 But when the perfect arrives, the imperfect passes away.

11 When I was a child, I spoke like a child, I understood like a child, I thought like a child. But when I became a man, I put aside the things of a child.

12 Now we see through a glass darkly. But then we shall see face to face. Now I know in part, but then I shall know, even as I am known.

13 But for now, these three continue: faith, hope, and charity. And the greatest of these is charity.

1 Corinthians 14

1 Pursue charity. Be zealous for spiritual things, but only so that you may prophesy.

2 For whoever speaks in tongues, speaks not to men, but to God. For no one understands. Yet by the Spirit, he speaks mysteries.

3 But whoever prophesies speaks to men for edification and exhortation and consolation.

4 Whoever speaks in tongues edifies himself. But whoever prophesies edifies the Church.

5 Now I want you all to speak in tongues, but more so to prophesy. For he who prophesies is greater than he who speaks in tongues, unless perhaps he interprets, so that the Church may receive edification.

6 But now, brothers, if I were to come to you speaking in tongues, how would it benefit you, unless instead I speak to you in revelation, or in knowledge, or in prophecy, or in doctrine?

7 Even those things that are without a soul can make sounds, whether it is a wind or a stringed instrument. But unless they present a distinction within the sounds, how will it be known which is from the pipe and which is from the string?

8 For example, if the trumpet made an uncertain sound, who would prepare himself for battle?

9 So it is with you also, for unless you utter with the tongue in plain speech, how will it be known what is said? For then you would be speaking into the air.

10 Consider that there are so many different kinds of languages in this world, and yet none is without a voice.

11 Therefore, if I do not understand the nature of the voice, then I shall be like a foreigner to the one with whom I am speaking; and he who is speaking will be like a foreigner to me.

12 So it is with you also. And since you are zealous for what is spiritual, seek the edification of the Church, so that you may abound.

13 For this reason, too, whoever speaks in tongues, let him pray for the interpretation.

14 So, if I pray in tongues, my spirit prays, but my mind is without fruit.

15 What is next? I should pray with the spirit, and also pray with the mind. I should sing psalms with the spirit, and also recite psalms with the mind.

16 Otherwise, if you have blessed only with the spirit, how can someone, in a state of ignorance, add an "Amen" to your blessing? For he does not know what you are saying.

17 In this case, certainly, you give thanks well, but the other person is not edified.

18 I thank my God that I speak in tongues for all of you.

19 But in the Church, I prefer to speak five words from my mind, so that I may instruct others also, rather than ten thousand words in tongues.

20 Brothers, do not choose to have the minds of children. Instead, be free of malice like infants, but be mature in your minds.

21 It is written in the law: "I will speak to this people with other tongues and other lips, and even so, they will not heed me, says the Lord."

22 And so, tongues are a sign, not for believers, but for unbelievers; and prophecies are not for unbelievers, but for believers.

23 If then, the entire Church were to gather together as one, and if all were to speak in tongues, and then ignorant or unbelieving persons were to enter, would they not say that you were insane?

24 But if everyone prophesies, and one who is ignorant or unbelieving enters, he may be convinced by it all, because he understands it all.

25 The secrets of his heart are then made manifest. And so, falling to his face, he would adore God, proclaiming that God is truly among you.

26 What is next, brothers? When you gather together, each one of you may have a psalm, or a doctrine, or a revelation, or a language, or an interpretation, but let everything be done for edification.

27 If anyone is speaking in tongues, let there be only two, or at most three, and then in turn, and let someone interpret.

28 But if there is no one to interpret, he should remain silent in the church, then he may speak when he is alone with God.

29 And let the prophets speak, two or three, and let the others discern.

30 But then, if something is revealed to another who is sitting, let the first one become silent.

31 For you are all able to prophesy one at a time, so that all may learn and all may be encouraged.

32 For the spirits of the prophets are subject to the prophets.

33 And God is not of dissension, but of peace, just as I also teach in all the churches of the saints.

34 Women should be silent in the churches. For it is not permitted for them to speak; but instead, they should be subordinate, as the law also says.

35 And if they want to learn anything, let them ask their husbands at home. For it is disgraceful for a woman to speak in church.

36 So now, did the Word of God proceed from you? Or was it sent to you alone?

37 If anyone seems to be a prophet or a spiritual person, he should understand these things which I am writing to you, that these things are the commandments of the Lord.

38 If anyone does not recognize these things, he should not be recognized.

39 And so, brothers, be zealous to prophesy, and do not prohibit speaking in tongues.

40 But let everything be done respectfully and according to proper order.

1 Corinthians 15

1 And so I make known to you, brothers, the Gospel that I preached to you, which you also received, and on which you stand.

2 By the Gospel, too, you are being saved, if you hold to the understanding that I preached to you, lest you believe in vain.

3 For I handed on to you, first of all, what I also received: that Christ died for our sins, according to the Scriptures;

4 and that he was buried; and that he rose again on the third day, according to the Scriptures;

5 and that he was seen by Cephas, and after that by the eleven.

6 Next he was seen by more than five hundred brothers at one time, many of whom remain, even to the present time, although some have fallen asleep.

7 Next, he was seen by James, then by all the Apostles.

8 And last of all, he was seen also by me, as if I were someone born at the wrong time.

9 For I am the least of the Apostles. I am not worthy to be called an Apostle, because I persecuted the Church of God.

10 But, by the grace of God, I am what I am. And his grace in me has not been empty, since I have labored more abundantly than all of them. Yet it is not I, but the grace of God within me.

11 For whether it is I or they: so we preach, and so you have believed.

12 Now if Christ is preached, that he rose again from the dead, how is it that some among you say that there is no resurrection of the dead?

13 For if there is no resurrection of the dead, then Christ has not risen.

14 And if Christ has not risen, then our preaching is useless, and your faith is also useless.

15 Then, too, we would be found to be false witnesses of God, because we would have given testimony against God, saying that he had raised up Christ, when he had not raised him up, if, indeed, the dead do not rise again.

16 For if the dead do not rise again, then neither has Christ risen again.

17 But if Christ has not risen, then your faith is vain; for you would still be in your sins.

18 Then, too, those who have fallen asleep in Christ would have perished.

19 If we have hope in Christ for this life only, then we are more miserable than all men.

20 But now Christ has risen again from the dead, as the first-fruits of those who sleep.

21 For certainly, death came through a man. And so, the resurrection of the dead came through a man

22 And just as in Adam all die, so also in Christ all will be brought to life,

23 but each one in his proper order: Christ, as the first-fruits, and next, those who are of Christ, who have believed in his advent.

24 Afterwards is the end, when he will have handed over the kingdom to God the Father, when he will have emptied all principality, and authority, and power.

25 For it is necessary for him to reign, until he has set all his enemies under his feet.

26 Lastly, the enemy called death shall be destroyed. For he has subjected all things under his feet. And although he says,

27 "All things have been subjected to him," without doubt he does not include the One who has subjected all things to him.

28 And when all things will have been subjected to him, then even the Son himself will be subjected to the One who subjected all things to him, so that God may be all in all.

29 Otherwise, what will those who are being baptized for the dead do, if the dead do not rise again at all? Why then are they being baptized for them?

30 Why also do we endure trials every hour?

31 Daily I die, by means of your boasting, brothers: you whom I have in Christ Jesus our Lord.

32 If, according to man, I fought with the beasts at Ephesus, how would that benefit me, if the dead do not rise again? "Let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we shall die."

33 Do not be led astray. Evil communication corrupts good morals.

34 Be vigilant, you just ones, and do not be willing to sin. For certain persons have an ignorance of God. I say this to you with respect.

35 But someone may say, "How do the dead rise again?" or, "What type of body do they return with?"

36 How foolish! What you sow cannot be brought back to life, unless it first dies.

37 And what you sow is not the body that will be in the future, but a bare grain, such as of wheat, or of some other grain.

38 For God gives it a body according to his will, and according to each seed's proper body.

39 Not all flesh is the same flesh. But one is indeed of men, another truly is of beasts, another is of birds, and another is of fish.

40 Also, there are heavenly bodies and earthly bodies. But while the one, certainly, has the glory of heaven, the other has the glory of earth.

41 One has the brightness of the sun, another the brightness of the moon, and another the brightness of the stars. For even star differs from star in brightness.

42 So it is also with the resurrection of the dead. What is sown in corruption shall rise to incorruption.

43 What is sown in dishonor shall rise to glory. What is sown in weakness shall rise to power.

44 What is sown with an animal body shall rise with a spiritual body. If there is an animal body, there is also a spiritual one.

45 Just as it was written that the first man, Adam, was made with a living soul, so shall the last Adam be made with a spirit brought back to life.

46 So what is, at first, not spiritual, but animal, next becomes spiritual.

47 The first man, being earthly, was of the earth; the second man, being heavenly, will be of heaven.

48 Such things as are like the earth are earthly; and such things as are like the heavens are heavenly.

49 And so, just as we have carried the image of what is earthly, let us also carry the image of what is heavenly.

50 Now I say this, brothers, because flesh and blood is not able to possess the kingdom of God; neither will what is corrupt possess what is incorrupt.

51 Behold, I tell you a mystery. Certainly, we shall all rise again, but we shall not all be transformed:

52 in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trumpet. For the trumpet will sound, and the dead will rise up, incorruptible. And we shall be transformed.

53 Thus, it is necessary for this corruptibility to be clothed with incorruptibility, and for this mortality to be clothed with immortality.

54 And when this mortality has been clothed with immortality, then the word that was written shall occur: "Death is swallowed up in victory."

55 "O death, where is your victory? O death, where is your sting?"

56 Now the sting of death is sin, and the power of sin is the law.

57 But thanks be to God, who has given us victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.

58 And so, my beloved brothers, be steadfast and unmovable, abounding always in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not useless in the Lord.

1 Corinthians 16

1 Now concerning the collections which are made for the saints: just as I have arranged for the churches of Galatia, so should it also be done with you.

2 On the first day of the week, the Sabbath, let each one of you take from himself, setting aside what will be well-pleasing to him, so that when I arrive, the collections will not have to be made then.

3 And when I am present, whomever you shall approve through letters, these I shall send to bear your gifts to Jerusalem.

4 And if it is fitting for me to go too, they shall go with me.

5 Now I will visit you after I have passed through Macedonia. For I will pass through Macedonia.

6 And perhaps I will stay with you, and even spend the winter, so that you may lead me on my way, whenever I depart.

7 For I am not willing to see you now only in passing, since I hope that I may remain with you for some length of time, if the Lord permits.

8 But I must remain at Ephesus, even until Pentecost.

9 For a door, great and unavoidable, has opened to me, as well as many adversaries.

10 Now if Timothy arrives, see to it that he may be among you without fear. For he is doing the work of the Lord, just as I also do.

11 Therefore, let no one despise him. Instead, lead him on his way in peace, so that he may come to me. For I am awaiting him with the brothers.

12 But concerning our brother, Apollo, I am letting you know that I pleaded with him greatly to go to you with the brothers, and clearly it was not his will to go at this time. But he will arrive when there is a space of time for him.

13 Be vigilant. Stand with faith. Act manfully and be strengthened.

14 Let all that is yours be immersed in charity.

15 And I beg you, brothers: You know the house of Stephanus, and of Fortunatus, and of Achaicus, that they are the first-fruits of Achaia, and that they have dedicated themselves to the ministry of the saints.

16 So you should be subject also to persons such as this, as well as to all who are cooperating and working with them.

17 Now I rejoice in the presence of Stephanus and Fortunatus and Achaicus, because what was lacking in you, they have supplied.

18 For they have refreshed my spirit and yours. Therefore, recognize persons such as this.

19 The churches of Asia greet you. Aquila and Priscilla greet you greatly in the Lord, with the church of their household, where I also am a guest.

20 All the brothers greet you. Greet one another with a holy kiss.

21 This is a greeting from my own hand, Paul.

22 If anyone does not love our Lord Jesus Christ, let him be anathema! Maran Atha.

23 May the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all.

24 My charity is with all of you in Christ Jesus. Amen.

2 Corinthians 1

1 Paul, an Apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, and Timothy, a brother, to the church of God which is at Corinth, with all the saints who are in all of Achaia:

2 Grace and peace to you from God our Father and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

3 Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of mercies and the God of all consolation.

4 He consoles us in all our tribulation, so that we too may be able to console those who are in any kind of distress, through the exhortation by which we also are being exhorted by God.

5 For just as the Passion of Christ abounds in us, so also, through Christ, does our consolation abound.

6 So, if we are in tribulation, it is for your exhortation and salvation, or if we are in consolation, it is for your consolation, or if we are exhorted, it is for your exhortation and salvation, which results in the patience endurance of the same passion which we also endure.

7 So may our hope for you be made firm, knowing that, just as you are participants in the suffering, so also shall you be participants in the consolation.

8 For we do not want you to be ignorant, brothers, about our tribulation, which happened to us in Asia. For we were weighed down beyond measure, beyond our strength, so that we became weary, even of life itself.

9 But we had within ourselves the response to death, so that we would not have faith in ourselves, but in God, who raises the dead.

10 He has rescued us, and he is rescuing us, from great peril. In him, we hope that he will continue to rescue us.

11 And you are assisting, with your prayers for us, so that from many persons, by that which is a gift in us, thanks may be given through many persons, because of us.

12 For our glory is this: the testimony of our conscience, which is found in simplicity of heart and in sincerity toward God. And it is not with worldly wisdom, but in the grace of God, that we have conversed with this world, and more abundantly toward you.

13 For we write nothing else to you other than what you have read and understood. And I hope that you will continue to understand, even unto the end.

14 And just as you have acknowledged us in our role, that we are your glory, so also you are ours, unto the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.

15 And with this confidence, I wanted to come to you sooner, so that you might have a second grace,

16 and through you to pass into Macedonia, and to return to you again from Macedonia, and so be led by you on my way to Judea.

17 Then, although I had intended this, did I act lightly? Or in the things that I consider, do I consider according to the flesh, so that there would be, with me, both Yes and No?

18 But God is faithful, so our word, which was set before you, was not, in him, both Yes and No.

19 For the Son of God, Jesus Christ, who was preached among you through us, through myself and Sylvanus and Timothy, was not Yes, and No; but was simply Yes in him.

20 For whatever promises are of God are, in him, Yes. For this reason, too, through him: Amen to God for our glory.

21 Now the One who confirms us with you in Christ, and who has anointed us, is God.

22 And he has sealed us, and he has placed the pledge of the Spirit in our hearts.

23 But I call God as a witness to my soul, that I was lenient with you, in that I did not return to Corinth:

24 not because we have dominion over your faith, but because we are assistants of your joy. For by faith you stand.

2 Corinthians 2

1 But I determined this within myself, not to return again to you in sorrow.

2 For if I make you sorrowful, then who is it that can make me glad, except the one who is made sorrowful by me?

3 And so, I wrote this same thing to you, so that I might not, when I arrive, add sorrow to sorrow for those with whom I ought to rejoice, having confidence in you in all things, so that my joy may be entirely yours.

4 For with much tribulation and anguish of heart, I wrote to you with many tears: not so that you would be sorrowful, but so that you might know the charity that I have more abundantly toward you.

5 But if anyone has brought sorrow, he has not sorrowed me. Yet, for my part, this is so that I might not burden all of you.

6 Let this rebuke be sufficient for someone like this, for it has been brought by many.

7 So then, to the contrary, you should be more forgiving and consoling, lest perhaps someone like this may be overwhelmed with excessive sorrow.

8 Because of this, I beg you to confirm your charity toward him.

9 It was for this reason, also, that I wrote, so that I might know, by testing you, whether you would be obedient in all things.

10 But anyone whom you have forgiven of anything, I also forgive. And then, too, anyone I have forgiven, if I have forgiven anything, it was done in the person of Christ for your sakes,

11 so that we would not be circumvented by Satan. For we are not ignorant of his intentions.

12 And when I had arrived at Troas, because of the Gospel of Christ, and a door had opened to me in the Lord,

13 I had no rest within my spirit, because I was not able to find Titus, my brother. So, saying goodbye to them, I set out for Macedonia.

14 But thanks be to God, who always brings triumph to us in Christ Jesus, and who manifests the fragrance of his knowledge through us in every place.

15 For we are the sweet fragrance of Christ for God, both with those who are being saved and with those who are perishing.

16 To the one, certainly, the fragrance is of death unto death. But to the other, the fragrance is of life unto life. And concerning these things, who is so suitable?

17 For we are not like many others, adulterating the Word of God. But instead, we speak with sincerity: from God, before God, and in Christ.

2 Corinthians 3

1 Must we begin again to commend ourselves? Or are we in need (as some are) of epistles of commendation for you, or from you?

2 You are our Epistle, written in our hearts, which is known and read by all men.

3 It has been made manifest that you are the Epistle of Christ, ministered by us, and written down, not with ink, but with the Spirit of the living God, and not on tablets of stone, but on the fleshly tablets of the heart.

4 And we have such faith, through Christ, toward God.

5 It is not that we are adequate to think anything of ourselves, as if anything was from us. But our adequacy is from God.

6 And he has made us suitable ministers of the New Testament, not in the letter, but in the Spirit. For the letter kills, but the Spirit gives life.

7 But if the ministration of death, engraved with letters upon stones, was in glory, (so much so that the sons of Israel were not able to gaze intently upon the face of Moses, because of the glory of his countenance) even though this ministration was ineffective,

8 how could the ministration of the Spirit not be in greater glory?

9 For if the ministration of condemnation is with glory, so much more is the ministration of justice abundant in glory.

10 And neither was it glorified by means of an excellent glory, though it was made illustrious in its own way.

11 For if even what was temporary has its glory, then what is lasting has an even greater glory.

12 Therefore, having such a hope, we act with much confidence,

13 and not as Moses did, in placing a veil over his face, so that the sons of Israel would not gaze intently at his face. This was ineffective,

14 for their minds were obtuse. And, even until this present day, the very same veil, in the readings from the Old Testament, remains not taken away (though, in Christ, it is taken away).

15 But even until today, when Moses is read, a veil is still set over their hearts.

16 But when they will have been converted to the Lord, then the veil shall be taken away.

17 Now the Spirit is Lord. And wherever the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty.

18 Yet truly, all of us, as we gaze upon the unveiled glory of the face of the Lord, are transfigured into the same image, from one glory to another. And this is done by the Spirit of the Lord.

2 Corinthians 4

1 Therefore, since we have this ministry, and in as much as we have obtained mercy for ourselves, we are not inadequate.

2 For we renounce dishonorable and hidden acts, not walking by craftiness, nor by adulterating the Word of God. Instead, by the manifestation of truth, we commend ourselves to the conscience of each man before God.

3 But if our Gospel is in some way hidden, it is hidden to those who are perishing.

4 As for them, the god of this age has blinded the minds of unbelievers, so that the light of the Gospel of the glory of Christ, who is the image of God, would not shine in them.

5 For we are not preaching about ourselves, but about Jesus Christ our Lord. We are merely your servants through Jesus.

6 For God, who told the light to shine out of darkness, has shined a light into our hearts, to illuminate the knowledge of the splendor of God, in the person of Christ Jesus.

7 But we hold this treasure in earthen vessels, so that what is sublime may be of the power of God, and not of us.

8 In all things, we endure tribulation, yet we are not in anguish. We are constrained, yet we are not destitute.

9 We suffer persecution, yet we have not been abandoned. We are thrown down, yet we do not perish.

10 We ever carry around the mortification of Jesus in our bodies, so that the life of Jesus may also be manifested in our bodies.

11 For we who live are ever handed over unto death for the sake of Jesus, so that the life of Jesus may also be manifested in our mortal flesh.

12 Therefore, death is at work in us, and life is at work in you.

13 But we have the same Spirit of faith. And just as it is written, "I believed, and for that reason I spoke," so we also believe, and for that reason, we also speak.

14 For we know that the One who raised up Jesus will raise us up also with Jesus and will place us with you.

15 Thus, all is for you, so that grace, abounding through many in thanksgiving, may abound to the glory of God.

16 For this reason, we are not insufficient. But it is as though our outer man is corrupted, while our inner man is renewed from day to day.

17 For though our tribulation is, at the present time, brief and light, it accomplishes in us the weight of a sublime eternal glory, beyond measure.

18 And we are contemplating, not the things that are seen, but the things that are unseen. For the things that are seen are temporal, whereas the things that are not seen are eternal.

2 Corinthians 5

1 For we know that, when our earthly house of this habitation is dissolved, we have a building of God, a house not made with hands, eternal in heaven.

2 And for this reason also, we groan, desiring to be clothed from above with our habitation from heaven.

3 If we are so clothed, then we will not be found to be naked.

4 Then too, we who are in this tabernacle groan under the burden, because we do not want to be stripped, but rather to be clothed from above, so that what is mortal may be absorbed by life.

5 Now the One who accomplishes this very thing in us is God, who has given us the pledge of the Spirit.

6 Therefore, we are ever confident, knowing that, while we are in the body, we are on a pilgrimage in the Lord.

7 For we walk by means of faith, and not by sight.

8 So we are confident, and we have the good will to be on a pilgrimage in the body, so as to be present to the Lord.

9 And thus we struggle, whether absent or present, to please him.

10 For it is necessary for us to be manifested before the judgment seat of Christ, so that each one may receive the proper things of the body, according to his behavior, whether it was good or evil.

11 Therefore, having knowledge of the fear of the Lord, we appeal to men, but we are made manifest before God. Yet I hope, too, that we may be made manifest in your consciences.

12 We are not commending ourselves again to you, but rather we are presenting you with an opportunity to glory because of us, when you deal with those who glory in face, and not in heart.

13 For if we are excessive in mind, it is for God; but if we are sober, it is for you.

14 For the charity of Christ urges us on, in consideration of this: that if one died for all, then all have died.

15 And Christ died for all, so that even those who live might not now live for themselves, but for him who died for them and who rose again.

16 And so, from now on, we know no one according to the flesh. And though we have known Christ according to the flesh, yet now we know him in this way no longer.

17 So if anyone is a new creature in Christ, what is old has passed away. Behold, all things have been made new.

18 But all is of God, who has reconciled us to himself through Christ, and who has given us the ministry of reconciliation.

19 For certainly God was in Christ, reconciling the world to himself, not charging them with their sins. And he has placed in us the Word of reconciliation.

20 Therefore, we are ambassadors for Christ, so that God is exhorting through us. We beseech you for Christ: be reconciled to God.

21 For God made him who did not know sin to be sin for us, so that we might become the justice of God in him.

2 Corinthians 6

1 But, as a help to you, we exhort you not to receive the grace of God in vain.

2 For he says: "In a favorable time, I heeded you; and on the day of salvation, I helped you." Behold, now is the favorable time; behold, now is the day of salvation.

3 May we never give offense to anyone, so that our ministry may not be disparaged.

4 But in all things, let us exhibit ourselves as ministers of God with great patience: through tribulation, difficulties, and distress;

5 despite wounds, imprisonment, and rebellion; with hard work, vigilance, and fasting;

6 by chastity, knowledge, and longsuffering; in pleasantness, in the Holy Spirit, and in unfeigned charity;

7 with the Word of truth, with the power of God, and with the armor of justice to the right and to the left;

8 through honor and dishonor, despite good reports and bad, whether seen as deceivers or truth-tellers, whether ignored or acknowledged;

9 as if dying and yet truly alive; as if chastised and yet not subdued;

10 as if sorrowful and yet always rejoicing; as if needy and yet enriching many; as if having nothing and possessing everything.

11 Our mouth is open to you, O Corinthians; our heart is enlarged.

12 You are not narrowed by us, but it is by your own inner selves that you are narrowed.

13 But since we have the same recompense, (I am speaking as if to my own sons), you, too, should be enlarged.

14 Do not choose to bear the yoke with unbelievers. For how can justice be a participant with iniquity? Or how can the fellowship of light be a participant with darkness?

15 And how can Christ join together with Belial? Or what part do the faithful have with the unfaithful?

16 And what consensus does the temple of God have with idols? For you are the temple of the living God, just as God says: "I will dwell with them, and I will walk among them. And I will be their God, and they shall be my people.

17 Because of this, you must depart from their midst and be separate, says the Lord. And do not touch what is unclean.

18 Then I will accept you. And I will be a Father to you, and you shall be sons and daughters to me, says the Lord Almighty."

2 Corinthians 7

1 Therefore, having these promises, most beloved, let us cleanse ourselves from all defilement of the flesh and of the spirit, perfecting sanctification in the fear of God.

2 Consider us. We have injured no one; we have corrupted no one; we have defrauded no one.

3 I am not saying this to your condemnation. For we have told you before that you are in our hearts: to die together and to live together.

4 Great is my confidence in you. Great is my glorying over you. I have been filled with consolation. I have a superabundant joy throughout all our tribulation.

5 Then, too, when we had arrived in Macedonia, our flesh had no rest. Instead, we suffered every tribulation: exterior conflicts, interior fears.

6 But God, who consoles the humble, consoled us by the arrival of Titus,

7 and not only by his arrival, but also by the consolation with which he was consoled among you. For he brought to us your desire, your weeping, your zeal for me, so that I rejoiced all the more.

8 For though I made you sorrowful by my epistle, I do not repent. And if I did repent, but only for a time, having realized that the same epistle made you sorrowful,

9 now I am glad: not because you were sorrowful, but because you were sorrowful unto repentance. For you became sorrowful for God, so that you might not suffer any harm from us.

10 For the sorrow that is according to God accomplishes a repentance which is steadfast unto salvation. But the sorrow that is of the world accomplishes death.

11 So consider this same idea, being sorrowful according to God, and what great solicitude it accomplishes in you: including protection, and indignation, and fear, and desire, and zeal, and vindication. In all things, you have shown yourselves to be uncorrupted by this sorrow.

12 And so, though I wrote to you, it was not because of him who caused the injury, nor because of him who suffered from it, but so as to manifest our solicitude, which we have for you before God.

13 Therefore, we have been consoled. But in our consolation, we have rejoiced even more abundantly over the joy of Titus, because his spirit was refreshed by all of you.

14 And if I have gloried in anything to him about you, I have not been put to shame. But, just as we have spoken all things to you in truth, so also our glorying before Titus has been the truth.

15 And his feelings are now more abundant toward you, since he remembers the obedience of you all, and how you received him with fear and trembling.

16 I rejoice that in all things I have confidence in you.

2 Corinthians 8

1 And so we are making known to you, brothers, the grace of God that has been given in the churches of Macedonia.

2 For within a great experience of tribulation, they have had an abundance of joy, and their profound poverty has only increased the richness of their simplicity.

3 And I bear witness to them, that they were willing to accept what was in accord with their ability, and even what was beyond their ability.

4 For they were begging us, with great exhortation, for the grace and the communication of the ministry that is with the saints.

5 And this is beyond what we had hoped, since they gave themselves, first of all to the Lord, and then also to us, through the will of God,

6 so much so that we petitioned Titus, that in the same manner as he had begun, he would also complete in you this same grace.

7 But, just as in all things you abound in faith and in word and in knowledge and in all solicitude, and even more so in your charity toward us, so also may you abound in this grace.

8 I am speaking, not commanding. But through the solicitude of others, I approve of the good character of your charity.

9 For you know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, that though he was rich, he became poor for your sakes, so that through his poverty, you might become rich.

10 And about this, I give my counsel. For this is useful to those of you who, only a year earlier, had just begun to act, or even to be willing to act.

11 So, truly now, accomplish this in deed, so that, in the same manner as your willing mind is prompted, you may also act, out of that which you have.

12 For when the will is prompted, it receives according to what that person has, not according to what that person does not have.

13 And it is not that others should be relieved, while you are troubled, but that there should be an equality.

14 In this present time, let your abundance supply their need, so that their abundance may also supply your need, in order that there may be an equality, just as it was written:

15 "He with more did not have too much; and he with less did not have too little."

16 But thanks be to God, who has granted to the heart of Titus, this same solicitude for you.

17 For certainly, he accepted the exhortation. But since he was more solicitous, he went to you of his own free will.

18 And we have even sent with him a brother whose praise accompanies the Gospel throughout all the churches.

19 And not only that, but he was also chosen by the churches to be a companion for our sojourn in this grace, which is ministered by us with our determined will, to the glory of the Lord.

20 So let us avoid this, lest anyone disparage us over the abundance that is ministered by us.

21 For we provide for what is good, not only in the sight of God, but also in the sight of men.

22 And we have also sent with them our brother, whom we have proven to be frequently solicitous in many matters. But now there is a greater solicitousness, which is greatly entrusted to you;

23 and whether it concerns Titus, who is a companion to me and a helper to you, or whether it concerns our brothers, the Apostles of the churches, it is to the glory of Christ.

24 Therefore, in the sight of the churches, show them the proof of your charity and of our glorying about you.

2 Corinthians 9

1 Now, concerning the ministry that is done toward the saints, it is not necessary for me to write to you.

2 For I know your willing mind. I glory about you, concerning this, to the Macedonians. For Achaia has also been prepared, for the past year. And your example has inspired very many others.

3 Now I have sent the brothers, so that what we glory about concerning you might be not be empty in this matter, in order that (as I have explained) you may be prepared.

4 Otherwise, if the Macedonians arrive with me and find you unprepared, we (not to mention you) would be ashamed in this matter.

5 Therefore, I considered it necessary to ask the brothers to go to you in advance and to prepare this blessing as promised, and in this way, you may be ready as a blessing, not as an excess.

6 But I say this: Whoever sows sparingly will also reap sparingly. And whoever sows with blessings shall also reap from blessings:

7 each one giving, just as he has determined in his heart, neither out of sadness, nor out of obligation. For God loves a cheerful giver.

8 And God is able to make every grace abound in you, so that, always having what you need in all things, you may abound unto every good work,

9 just as it was written: "He has distributed widely, he has given to the poor; his justice remains from age to age."

10 And he who ministers seed to the sower will offer you bread to eat, and will multiply your seed, and will increase the growth of the fruits of your justice.

11 So then, having been enriched in all things, you may abound in all simplicity, which works thanksgiving to God through us.

12 For the ministration of this office not only supplies whatever the saints need, but also abounds through many thanksgivings in the Lord.

13 And so, through the evidence of this ministry, you glorify God by the obedience of your confession in the Gospel of Christ, and by the simplicity of your communion with them and with everyone,

14 and they offer prayers for you, being solicitous about you, because of the excellent grace of God within you.

15 Thanks be to God for his ineffable gift.

2 Corinthians 10

1 But I myself, Paul, am begging you, through the meekness and modesty of Christ. I am certainly, by appearances, lowly among you, yet I have confidence in you, even while I am absent.

2 So I am petitioning you, lest I be bold, when present, with that bold confidence that I am considered to have by certain ones who judge us as if we were walking according to the flesh.

3 For though we walk in the flesh, we do not battle according to the flesh.

4 For the weapons of our battles are not carnal, yet still they are powerful with God, unto the destruction of fortifications: tearing down every counsel

5 and height that extols itself contrary to the wisdom of God, and leading every intellect into the captivity of obedience to Christ,

6 and standing ready to repudiate every disobedience, when your own obedience has been fulfilled.

7 Consider the things that are in accord with appearances. If anyone trusts that by these things he belongs to Christ, let him reconsider this within himself. For just as he belongs to Christ, so also do we.

8 And if I were even to glory somewhat more about our authority, which the Lord has given to us for your edification, and not for your destruction, I should not be ashamed.

9 But let it not be said that I am scaring you by means of epistles.

10 For they say: "His epistles, indeed, are weighty and strong. But his bodily presence is weak, and his speech is contemptible."

11 Let someone like this realize that whatever we are in word through epistles, while absent: we are much the same in deed, while present.

12 For we would not dare to interpose or compare ourselves with certain ones who commend themselves. But we measure ourselves by ourselves, and we compare ourselves with ourselves.

13 Thus, we will not glory beyond our measure, but rather according to the measure of the limit which God has measured out to us, a measure which extends even to you.

14 For we are not overextending ourselves, as if we are not able to reach as far as you are able. For we have gone even as far as you have in the Gospel of Christ.

15 We are not glorying immeasurably over the labors of others. Instead, we hold on to the hope of your growing faith, so as to be magnified in you, according to our own limits, but in abundance,

16 and even so as to evangelize in those places that are beyond you, not in order to glory in the measure of others, but rather in those things which have already been prepared.

17 But whoever glories, let him glory in the Lord.

18 For it is not he who commends himself who is approved, but rather he whom God commends.

2 Corinthians 11

1 I wish that you would endure a small amount of my foolishness, so as to bear with me.

2 For I am jealous toward you, with the jealousy of God. And I have espoused you to one husband, offering you as a chaste virgin to Christ.

3 But I am afraid lest, as the serpent led astray Eve by his cleverness, so your minds might be corrupted and might fall away from the simplicity which is in Christ.

4 For if anyone arrives preaching another Christ, one whom we have not preached; or if you receive another Spirit, one whom you have not received; or another Gospel, one which you have not been given: you might permit him to guide you.

5 For I consider that I have done nothing less than the great Apostles.

6 For although I may be unskilled in speech, yet I am not so in knowledge. But, in all things, we have been made manifest to you.

7 Or did I commit a sin by humbling myself so that you would be exalted? For I preached the Gospel of God to you freely.

8 I have taken from other churches, receiving a stipend from them to the benefit of your ministry.

9 And when I was with you and in need, I was burdensome to no one. For the brothers who came from Macedonia supplied whatever was lacking to me. And in all things, I have kept myself, and I will keep myself, from being burdensome to you.

10 The truth of Christ is in me, and so this glorying shall not be broken away from me in the regions of Achaia.

11 Why so? Is it because I do not love you? God knows I do.

12 But what I am doing, I will continue to do, so that I may take away an opportunity from those who desire an opportunity by which they may glory, so as to be considered to be like us.

13 For false apostles, such as these deceitful workers, are presenting themselves as if they were Apostles of Christ.

14 And no wonder, for even Satan presents himself as if he were an Angel of light.

15 Therefore, it is no great thing if his ministers present themselves as if they were ministers of justice, for their end shall be according to their works.

16 I say again. And let no one consider me to be foolish. Or, at least, accept me as if I were foolish, so that I also may glory a small amount.

17 What I am saying is not said according to God, but as if in foolishness, in this matter of glorying.

18 Since so many glory according to the flesh, I will glory also.

19 For you freely accept the foolish, though you yourselves claim to be wise.

20 For you permit it when someone guides you into servitude, even if he devours you, even if he takes from you, even if he is extolled, even if he strikes you repeatedly on the face.

21 I speak according to disgrace, as if we had been weak in this regard. In this matter, (I speak in foolishness) if anyone dares, I dare also.

22 They are Hebrews; so am I. They are Israelites; so am I. They are the offspring of Abraham; so am I.

23 They are the ministers of Christ (I speak as if I were less wise); more so am I: with many more labors, with numerous imprisonments, with wounds beyond measure, with frequent mortifications.

24 On five occasions, I received forty stripes, less one, from the Jews.

25 Three times, I was beaten with rods. One time, I was stoned. Three times, I was shipwrecked. For a night and a day, I was in the depths of the sea.

26 I have made frequent journeys, through dangerous waters, in danger of robbers, in danger from my own nation, in danger from the Gentiles, in danger in the city, in danger in the wilderness, in danger in the sea, in danger from false brothers,

27 with hardships and difficulties, with much vigilance, in hunger and thirst, with frequent fasts, in cold and nakedness,

28 and, in addition to these things, which are external: there is my daily earnestness and solicitude for all the churches.

29 Who is weak, and I am not weak? Who is scandalized, and I am not being burned?

30 If it is necessary to glory, I will glory of the things that concern my weaknesses.

31 The God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who is blessed forever, knows that I am not lying.

32 At Damascus, the governor of the nation under Aretas the king, watched over the city of the Damascenes, so as to apprehend me.

33 And, through a window, I was let down along the wall in a basket; and so I escaped his hands.

2 Corinthians 12

1 If it is necessary (though certainly not expedient) to glory, then I will next tell of visions and revelations from the Lord.

2 I know a man in Christ, who, more than fourteen years ago (whether in the body, I do not know, or out of the body, I do not know: God knows), was enraptured to the third heaven.

3 And I know a certain man (whether in the body, or out of the body, I do not know: God knows),

4 who was enraptured into Paradise. And he heard words of mystery, which it is not permitted for man to speak.

5 On behalf of someone like this, I will glory. But on behalf of myself, I will not glory about anything, except my infirmities.

6 For even though I am willing to glory, I will not be foolish. But I will speak the truth. Yet I will do so sparingly, lest anyone may consider me to be anything more than what he sees in me, or anything more than what he hears from me.

7 And lest the greatness of the revelations should extol me, there was given to me a prodding in my flesh: an angel of Satan, who struck me repeatedly.

8 Because of this, three times I petitioned the Lord that it might be taken away from me.

9 And he said to me: "My grace is sufficient for you. For virtue is perfected in weakness." And so, willingly shall I glory in my weaknesses, so that the virtue of Christ may live within me.

10 Because of this, I am pleased in my infirmity: in reproaches, in difficulties, in persecutions, in distresses, for the sake of Christ. For when I am weak, then I am powerful.

11 I have become foolish; you have compelled me. For I ought to have been commended by you. For I have been nothing less than those who claim to be above the measure of Apostles, even though I am nothing.

12 And the seal of my Apostleship has been set over you, with all patience, with signs and wonders and miracles.

13 For what is there that you have had which is less than the other churches, except that I myself did not burden you? Forgive me this injury.

14 Behold, this is the third time I have prepared to come to you, and yet I will not be a burden to you. For I am seeking not the things that are yours, but you yourselves. And neither should the children store up for the parents, but the parents for the children.

15 And so, very willingly, I will spend and exhaust myself for the sake of your souls, loving you more, while being loved less.

16 And so be it. I have not burdened you, but instead, being astute, I obtained you by guile.

17 And yet, did I defraud you by means of any of those whom I sent to you?

18 I asked for Titus, and I sent a brother with him. Did Titus defraud you? Did we not walk with the same spirit? Did we not walk in the same steps?

19 Have you ever thought that we should explain ourselves to you? We speak in the sight of God, in Christ. But all things, most beloved, are for your edification.

20 Yet I fear, lest perhaps, when I have arrived, I might not find you such as I would want, and I might be found by you, such as you would not want. For perhaps there may be among you: contention, envy, animosity, dissension, detraction, whispering, self-exaltation, and rebellion.

21 If so, then, when I have arrived, God may again humble me among you. And so, I mourn for the many who sinned beforehand, and did not repent, over the lust and fornication and homosexuality, which they have committed.

2 Corinthians 13

1 Behold, this is the third time that I am coming to you. By the mouth of two or three witnesses, every word shall stand.

2 I have preached when present, and I will preach now while absent, to those who sinned before, and to all the others, because, when I arrive again, I will not be lenient with you.

3 Do you seek evidence that it is Christ who speaks in me, who is not weak with you, but is powerful with you?

4 For although he was crucified in weakness, yet he lives by the power of God. And yes, we are weak in him. But we shall live with him by the power of God among you.

5 Test yourselves as to whether you are in the faith. Examine yourselves. Or do you yourselves not know whether Christ Jesus is in you? But perhaps you are reprobates.

6 But I hope you know that we ourselves are not reprobates.

7 Now we pray to God that you shall do nothing evil, not so that we may seem to be approved, but so that you may do what is good, even if we seem like reprobates.

8 For we cannot do anything against the truth, but only for the truth.

9 For we rejoice that we are weak, while you are strong. This is also what we pray for: your perfection.

10 Therefore, I write these things while absent, so that, when present, I may not have to act more harshly, according to the authority which the Lord has given to me, for edification and not for destruction.

11 As to the rest, brothers, rejoice, be perfect, be encouraged, have the same mind, have peace. And so the God of peace and love will be with you.

12 Greet one another with a holy kiss. All the saints greet you.

13 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, and the charity of God, and the communion of the Holy Spirit be with you all. Amen.

Galatians 1

1 Paul, an Apostle, not from men and not through man, but through Jesus Christ, and God the Father, who raised him from the dead,

2 and all the brothers who are with me: to the churches of Galatia.

3 Grace and peace to you from God the Father, and from our Lord Jesus Christ,

4 who gave himself on behalf of our sins, so that he might deliver us from this present wicked age, according to the will of God our Father.

5 To him is glory forever and ever. Amen.

6 I wonder that you have been so quickly transferred, from him who called you into the grace of Christ, over to another gospel.

7 For there is no other, except that there are some persons who disturb you and who want to overturn the Gospel of Christ.

8 But if anyone, even we ourselves or an Angel from Heaven, were to preach to you a gospel other than the one that we have preached to you, let him be anathema.

9 Just as we have said before, so now I say again: If anyone has preached a gospel to you, other than that which you have received, let him be anathema.

10 For am I now persuading men, or God? Or, am I seeking to please men? If I still were pleasing men, then I would not be a servant of Christ.

11 For I would have you understand, brothers, that the Gospel which has been preached by me is not according to man.

12 And I did not receive it from man, nor did I learn it, except through the revelation of Jesus Christ.

13 For you have heard of my former behavior within Judaism: that, beyond measure, I persecuted the Church of God and fought against Her.

14 And I advanced in Judaism beyond many of my equals among my own kind, having proven to be more abundant in zeal toward the traditions of my fathers.

15 But, when it pleased him who, from my mother's womb, had set me apart, and who has called me by his grace,

16 to reveal his Son within me, so that I might evangelize him among the Gentiles, I did not next seek the consent of flesh and blood.

17 Neither did I go to Jerusalem, to those who were Apostles before me. Instead, I went into Arabia, and next I returned to Damascus.

18 And then, after three years, I went to Jerusalem to see Peter; and I stayed with him for fifteen days.

19 But I saw none of the other Apostles, except James, the brother of the Lord.

20 Now what I am writing to you: behold, before God, I am not lying.

21 Next, I went into the regions of Syria and Cilicia.

22 But I was unknown by face to the churches of Judea, which were in Christ.

23 For they had only heard that: "He, who formerly persecuted us, now evangelizes the faith which he once fought."

24 And they glorified God in me.

Galatians 2

1 Next, after fourteen years, I went up again to Jerusalem, taking with me Barnabas and Titus.

2 And I went up according to revelation, and I debated with them about the Gospel that I am preaching among the Gentiles, but away from those who were pretending to be something, lest perhaps I might run, or have run, in vain.

3 But even Titus, who was with me, though he was a Gentile, was not compelled to be circumcised,

4 but only because of false brothers, who were brought in unknowingly. They entered secretly to spy on our liberty, which we have in Christ Jesus, so that they might reduce us to servitude.

5 We did not yield to them in subjection, even for an hour, in order that the truth of the Gospel would remain with you,

6 and away from those who were pretending to be something. (Whatever they might have been once, it means nothing to me. God does not accept the reputation of a man.) And those who were claiming to be something had nothing to offer me.

7 But it was to the contrary, since they had seen that the Gospel to the uncircumcised was entrusted to me, just as the Gospel to the circumcised was entrusted to Peter.

8 For he who was working the Apostleship to the circumcised in Peter, was also working in me among the Gentiles.

9 And so, when they had acknowledged the grace that was given to me, James and Cephas and John, who seemed like pillars, gave to me and to Barnabas the right hand of fellowship, so that we would go to the Gentiles, while they went to the circumcised,

10 asking only that we should be mindful of the poor, which was the very thing that I also was solicitous to do.

11 But when Cephas had arrived at Antioch, I stood against him to his face, because he was blameworthy.

12 For before certain ones arrived from James, he ate with the Gentiles. But when they had arrived, he drew apart and separated himself, fearing those who were of the circumcision.

13 And the other Jews consented to his pretense, so that even Barnabas was led by them into that falseness.

14 But when I had seen that they were not walking correctly, by the truth of the Gospel, I said to Cephas in front of everyone: "If you, while you are a Jew, are living like the Gentiles and not the Jews, how is it that you compel the Gentiles to keep the customs of the Jews?"

15 By nature, we are Jews, and not of the Gentiles, sinners.

16 And we know that man is not justified by the works of the law, but only by the faith of Jesus Christ. And so we believe in Christ Jesus, in order that we may be justified by the faith of Christ, and not by the works of the law. For no flesh will be justified by the works of the law.

17 But if, while seeking to be justified in Christ, we ourselves are also found to be sinners, would then Christ be the minister of sin? Let it not be so!

18 For if I rebuild the things that I have destroyed, I establish myself as a prevaricator.

19 For through the law, I have become dead to the law, so that I may live for God. I have been nailed to the cross with Christ.

20 I live; yet now, it is not I, but truly Christ, who lives in me. And though I live now in the flesh, I live in the faith of the Son of God, who loved me and who delivered himself for me.

21 I do not reject the grace of God. For if justice is through the law, then Christ died in vain.

Galatians 3

1 O senseless Galatians, who has so fascinated you that you would not obey the truth, even though Jesus Christ has been presented before your eyes, crucified among you?

2 I wish to know only this from you: Did you receive the Spirit by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith?

3 Are you so foolish that, though you began with the Spirit, you would now end with the flesh?

4 Have you been suffering so much without a reason? If so, then it is in vain.

5 Therefore, does he who distributes the Spirit to you, and who works miracles among you, act by the works of the law, or by the hearing of the faith?

6 It is just as it was written: "Abraham believed God, and it was reputed to him unto justice."

7 Therefore, know that those who are of faith, these are the sons of Abraham.

8 Thus Scripture, foreseeing that God would justify the Gentiles by faith, foretold to Abraham: "All nations shall be blessed in you."

9 And so, those who are of faith shall be blessed with faithful Abraham.

10 For as many as are of the works of the law are under a curse. For it has been written: "Cursed is everyone who does not continue in all the things that have been written in the book of the Law, so as to do them."

11 And, since in the law no one is justified with God, this is manifest: "For the just man lives by faith."

12 But the law is not of faith; instead, "he who does these things shall live by them."

13 Christ has redeemed us from the curse of the law, since he became a curse for us. For it is written: "Cursed is anyone who hangs from a tree."

14 This was so that the blessing of Abraham might reach the Gentiles through Christ Jesus, in order that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith.

15 Brothers (I speak according to man), if a man's testament has been confirmed, no one would reject it or add to it.

16 The promises were made to Abraham and to his offspring. He did not say, "and to descendents," as if to many, but instead, as if to one, he said, "and to your offspring," who is Christ.

17 But I say this: the testament confirmed by God, which, after four hundred and thirty years became the Law, does not nullify, so as to make the promise empty.

18 For if the inheritance is of the law, then it is no longer of the promise. But God bestowed it to Abraham through the promise.

19 Why, then, was there a law? It was established because of transgressions, until the offspring would arrive, to whom he made the promise, ordained by Angels through the hand of a mediator.

20 Now a mediator is not of one, yet God is one.

21 So then, was the law contrary to the promises of God? Let it not be so! For if a law had been given, which was able to give life, truly justice would be of the law.

22 But Scripture has enclosed everything under sin, so that the promise, by the faith of Jesus Christ, might be given to those who believe.

23 But before the faith arrived, we were preserved by being enclosed under the law, unto that faith which was to be revealed.

24 And so the law was our guardian in Christ, in order that we might be justified by faith.

25 But now that faith has arrived, we are no longer under a guardian.

26 For you are all sons of God, through the faith which is in Christ Jesus.

27 For as many of you as have been baptized in Christ have become clothed with Christ.

28 There is neither Jew nor Greek; there is neither servant nor free; there is neither male nor female. For you are all one in Christ Jesus.

29 And if you are Christ's, then are you the offspring of Abraham, heirs according to the promise.

Galatians 4

1 But I say that, during the time an heir is a child, he is no different from a servant, even though he is the owner of everything.

2 For he is under tutors and caretakers, until the time which was predetermined by the father.

3 So also we, when we were children, were subservient to the influences of the world.

4 But when the fullness of time arrived, God sent his Son, formed from a woman, formed under the law,

5 so that he might redeem those who were under the law, in order that we might receive the adoption of sons.

6 Therefore, because you are sons, God has sent the Spirit of his Son into your hearts, crying out: "Abba, Father."

7 And so now he is not a servant, but a son. But if he is a son, then he is also an heir, through God.

8 But then, certainly, while ignorant of God, you served those who, by nature, are not gods.

9 But now, since you have known God, or rather, since you have been known by God: how can you turn away again, to weak and destitute influences, which you desire to serve anew?

10 You serve the days, and months, and times, and years.

11 I am afraid for you, lest perhaps I may have labored in vain among you.

12 Brothers, I beg you. Be as I am. For I, too, am like you. You have not injured me at all.

13 But you know that, in the weakness of the flesh, I have preached the Gospel to you for a long time, and that your trials are in my flesh.

14 You did not despise or reject me. But instead, you accepted me like an Angel of God, even like Christ Jesus.

15 Therefore, where is your happiness? For I offer to you testimony that, if it could be done, you would have plucked out your own eyes and would have given them to me.

16 So then, have I become your enemy by telling you the truth?

17 They are not imitating you well. And they are willing to exclude you, so that you might imitate them.

18 But be imitators of what is good, always in a good way, and not only when I am present with you.

19 My little sons, I am giving birth to you again, until Christ is formed in you.

20 And I would willingly be present with you, even now. But I would alter my voice: for I am ashamed of you.

21 Tell me, you who desire to be under the law, have you not read the law?

22 For it is written that Abraham had two sons: one by a servant woman, and one by a free woman.

23 And he who was of the servant was born according to the flesh. But he who was of the free woman was born by the promise.

24 These things are said through an allegory. For these represent the two testaments. Certainly the one, on Mount Sinai, gives birth unto servitude, which is Hagar.

25 For Sinai is a mountain in Arabia, which is related to the Jerusalem of the present time, and it serves with her sons.

26 But that Jerusalem which is above is free; the same is our mother.

27 For it was written: "Rejoice, O barren one, though you do not conceive. Burst forth and cry out, though you do not give birth. For many are the children of the desolate, even more than of her who has a husband."

28 Now we, brothers, like Isaac, are sons of the promise.

29 But just as then, he who was born according to the flesh persecuted him who was born according to the Spirit, so also it is now.

30 And what does Scripture say? "Cast out the woman servant and her son. For the son of a servant women shall not be an heir with the son of a free woman."

31 And so, brothers, we are not the sons of the servant woman, but rather of the free woman. And this is the freedom with which Christ has set us free.

Galatians 5

1 Stand firm, and do not be willing to be again held by the yoke of servitude.

2 Behold, I, Paul, say to you, that if you have been circumcised, Christ will be of no benefit to you.

3 For I again testify, about every man circumcising himself, that he is obligated to act according to the entire law.

4 You are being emptied of Christ, you who are being justified by the law. You have fallen from grace.

5 For in spirit, by faith, we await the hope of justice.

6 For in Christ Jesus, neither circumcision nor uncircumcision prevails over anything, but only faith which works through charity.

7 You have run well. So what has impeded you, that you would not obey the truth?

8 This kind of influence is not from him who is calling you.

9 A little leaven corrupts the whole mass.

10 I have confidence in you, in the Lord, that you will accept nothing of the kind. However, he who disturbs you shall bear the judgment, whomever he may be.

11 And as for me, brothers, if I still preach circumcision, why am I still suffering persecution? For then the scandal of the Cross would be made empty.

12 And I wish that those who disturb you would be torn away.

13 For you, brothers, have been called to liberty. Only you must not make liberty into an occasion for the flesh, but instead, serve one another through the charity of the Spirit.

14 For the entire law is fulfilled by one word: "You shall love your neighbor as yourself."

15 But if you bite and devour one another, be careful that you are not consumed by one another!

16 So then, I say: Walk in the spirit, and you will not fulfill the desires of the flesh.

17 For the flesh desires against the spirit, and the spirit against the flesh. And since these are against one another, you may not do whatever you want.

18 But if you are led by the Spirit, you are not under the law.

19 Now the works of the flesh are manifest; they are: fornication, lust, homosexuality, self-indulgence,

20 the serving of idols, drug use, hostility, contentiousness, jealousy, wrath, quarrels, dissensions, divisions,

21 envy, murder, inebriation, carousing, and similar things. About these things, I continue to preach to you, as I have preached to you: that those who act in this way shall not obtain the kingdom of God.

22 But the fruit of the Spirit is charity, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, forbearance,

23 meekness, faith, modesty, abstinence, chastity. There is no law against such things.

24 For those who are Christ's have crucified their flesh, along with its vices and desires.

25 If we live by the Spirit, we should also walk by the Spirit.

26 Let us not become desirous of empty glory, provoking one another, envying one another.

Galatians 6

1 And, brothers, if a man has been overtaken by any offense, you who are spiritual should instruct someone like this with a spirit of leniency, considering that you yourselves might also be tempted.

2 Carry one another's burdens, and so shall you fulfill the law of Christ.

3 For if anyone considers himself to be something, though he may be nothing, he deceives himself.

4 So let each one prove his own work. And in this way, he shall have glory in himself only, and not in another.

5 For each one shall carry his own burden.

6 And let him who is being taught the Word discuss it with him who is teaching it to him, in every good way.

7 Do not choose to wander astray. God is not to be ridiculed.

8 For whatever a man will have sown, that also shall he reap. For whoever sows in his flesh, from the flesh he shall also reap corruption. But whoever sows in the Spirit, from the Spirit he shall reap eternal life.

9 And so, let us not be deficient in doing good. For in due time, we shall reap without fail.

10 Therefore, while we have time, we should do good works toward everyone, and most of all toward those who are of the household of the faith.

11 Consider what kind of letters I have written to you with my own hand.

12 For as many of you as they desire to please in the flesh, they compel to be circumcised, but only so that they might not suffer the persecution of the cross of Christ.

13 And yet, neither do they themselves, who are circumcised, keep the law. Instead, they want you to be circumcised, so that they may glory in your flesh.

14 But far be it from me to glory, except in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom the world is crucified to me, and I to the world.

15 For in Christ Jesus, neither circumcision nor uncircumcision prevails in any way, but instead there is a new creature.

16 And whoever follows this rule: may peace and mercy be upon them, and upon the Israel of God.

17 Concerning other matters, let no one trouble me. For I carry the stigmata of the Lord Jesus in my body.

18 May the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit, brothers. Amen.

Ephesians 1

1 Paul, an Apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God, to all the saints who are at Ephesus and to the faithful in Christ Jesus.

2 Grace and peace to you from God the Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

3 Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has blessed us with every spiritual blessing in the heavens, in Christ,

4 just as he chose us in him before the foundation of the world, so that we would be holy and immaculate in his sight, in charity.

5 He has predestined us to adoption as sons, through Jesus Christ, in himself, according to the purpose of his will,

6 for the praise of the glory of his grace, with which he has gifted us in his beloved Son.

7 In him, we have redemption through his blood: the remission of sins in accord with the riches of his grace,

8 which is superabundant in us, with all wisdom and prudence.

9 So does he make known to us the mystery of his will, which he has set forth in Christ, in a manner well-pleasing to him,

10 in the dispensation of the fullness of time, so as to renew in Christ everything that exists through him in heaven and on earth.

11 In him, we too are called to our portion, having been predestined in accord with the plan of the One who accomplishes all things by the counsel of his will.

12 So may we be, to the praise of his glory, we who have hoped beforehand in Christ.

13 In him, you also, after you heard and believed the Word of truth, which is the Gospel of your salvation, were sealed with the Holy Spirit of the Promise.

14 He is the pledge of our inheritance, unto the acquisition of redemption, to the praise of his glory.

15 Because of this, and hearing of your faith that is in the Lord Jesus, and of your love toward all the saints,

16 I have not ceased giving thanks for you, calling you to mind in my prayers,

17 so that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give a spirit of wisdom and of revelation to you, in knowledge of him.

18 May the eyes of your heart be illuminated, so that you may know what is the hope of his calling, and the wealth of the glory of his inheritance with the saints,

19 and the preeminent magnitude of his virtue toward us, toward we who believe in accord with the work of his powerful virtue,

20 which he wrought in Christ, raising him from the dead and establishing him at his right hand in the heavens,

21 above every principality and power and virtue and dominion, and above every name that is given, not only in this age, but even in the future age.

22 And he has subjected all things under his feet, and he has made him the head over the entire Church,

23 which is his body and which is the fullness of him who accomplishes everything in everyone.

Ephesians 2

1 And you were once dead in your sins and offenses,

2 in which you walked in times past, according to the age of this world, according to the prince of the power of this sky, the spirit who now works in the sons of distrust.

3 And we too were all conversant in these things, in times past, by the desires of our flesh, acting according to the will of the flesh and according to our own thoughts. And so we were, by nature, sons of wrath, even like the others.

4 Yet still, God, who is rich in mercy, for the sake of his exceedingly great charity with which he loved us,

5 even when we were dead in our sins, has enlivened us together in Christ, by whose grace you have been saved.

6 And he has raised us up together, and he has caused us to sit down together in the heavens, in Christ Jesus,

7 so that he may display, in the ages soon to arrive, the abundant wealth of his grace, by his goodness toward us in Christ Jesus.

8 For by grace, you have been saved through faith. And this is not of yourselves, for it is a gift of God.

9 And this is not of works, so that no one may glory.

10 For we are his handiwork, created in Christ Jesus for the good works which God has prepared and in which we should walk.

11 Because of this, be mindful that, in times past, you were Gentiles in the flesh, and that you were called uncircumcised by those who are called circumcised in the flesh, something done by man,

12 and that you were, in that time, without Christ, being foreign to the way of life of Israel, being visitors to the testament, having no hope of the promise, and being without God in this world.

13 But now, in Christ Jesus, you, who were in times past far away, have been brought near by the blood of Christ.

14 For he is our peace. He made the two into one, by dissolving the intermediate wall of separation, of opposition, by his flesh,

15 emptying the law of commandments by decree, so that he might join these two, in himself, into one new man, making peace

16 and reconciling both to God, in one body, through the cross, destroying this opposition in himself.

17 And upon arriving, he evangelized peace to you who were far away, and peace to those who were near.

18 For by him, we both have access, in the one Spirit, to the Father.

19 Now, therefore, you are no longer visitors and new arrivals. Instead, you are citizens among the saints in the household of God,

20 having been built upon the foundation of the Apostles and of the Prophets, with Jesus Christ himself as the preeminent cornerstone.

21 In him, all that has been built is framed together, rising up into a holy temple in the Lord.

22 In him, you also have been built together into a habitation of God in the Spirit.

Ephesians 3

1 By reason of this grace, I, Paul, am a prisoner of Jesus Christ, for the sake of you Gentiles.

2 Now certainly, you have heard of the dispensation of the grace of God, which has been given to me among you:

3 that, by means of revelation, the mystery was made known to me, just as I have written above in a few words.

4 Yet, by reading this closely, you might be able to understand my prudence in the mystery of Christ.

5 In other generations, this was unknown to the sons of men, even as it has now been revealed to his holy Apostles and Prophets in the Spirit,

6 so that the Gentiles would be co-heirs, and of the same body, and partners together, by his promise in Christ Jesus, through the Gospel.

7 Of this Gospel, I have been made a minister, according to the gift of the grace of God, which has been given to me by means of the operation of his virtue.

8 Although I am the least of all the saints, I have been given this grace: to evangelize among the Gentiles the unsearchable riches of Christ,

9 and to enlighten everyone concerning the dispensation of the mystery, hidden before the ages in God who created all things,

10 so that the manifold wisdom of God may become well-known to the principalities and powers in the heavens, through the Church,

11 according to that timeless purpose, which he has formed in Christ Jesus our Lord.

12 In him we trust, and so we approach with confidence, through his faith.

13 Because of this, I ask you not to be weakened by my tribulations on your behalf; for this is your glory.

14 By reason of this grace, I bend my knees to the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,

15 from whom all paternity in heaven and on earth takes its name.

16 And I ask him to grant to you to be strengthened in virtue by his Spirit, in accord with the wealth of his glory, in the inner man,

17 so that Christ may live in your hearts through a faith rooted in, and founded on, charity.

18 So may you be able to embrace, with all the saints, what is the width and length and height and depth

19 of the charity of Christ, and even be able to know that which surpasses all knowledge, so that you may be filled with all the fullness of God.

20 Now to him who is able to do all things, more abundantly than we could ever ask or understand, by means of the virtue which is at work in us:

21 to him be glory, in the Church and in Christ Jesus, throughout every generation, forever and ever. Amen.

Ephesians 4

1 And so, as a prisoner in the Lord, I beg you to walk in a manner worthy of the vocation to which you have been called:

2 with all humility and meekness, with patience, supporting one another in charity.

3 Be anxious to preserve the unity of the Spirit within the bonds of peace.

4 One body and one Spirit: to this you have been called by the one hope of your calling:

5 one Lord, one faith, one baptism,

6 one God and Father of all, who is over all, and through all, and in us all.

7 Yet to each one of us there has been given grace according to the measure allotted by Christ.

8 Because of this, he says: "Ascending on high, he took captivity itself captive; he gave gifts to men."

9 Now that he has ascended, what is left except for him also to descended, first to the lower parts of the earth?

10 He who descended is the same one who also ascended above all the heavens, so that he might fulfill everything.

11 And the same one granted that some would be Apostles, and some Prophets, yet truly others evangelists, and others pastors and teachers,

12 for the sake of the perfection of the saints, by the work of the ministry, in the edification of the body of Christ,

13 until we all meet in the unity of faith and in the knowledge of the Son of God, as a perfect man, in the measure of the age of the fullness of Christ.

14 So may we then no longer be little children, disturbed and carried about by every wind of doctrine, by the wickedness of men, and by the craftiness which deceives unto error.

15 Instead, acting according to truth in charity, we should increase in everything, in him who is the head, Christ himself.

16 For in him, the whole body is joined closely together, by every underlying joint, through the function allotted to each part, bringing improvement to the body, toward its edification in charity.

17 And so, I say this, and I testify in the Lord: that from now on you should walk, not as the Gentiles also walk, in the vanity of their mind,

18 having their intellect obscured, being alienated from the life of God, through the ignorance that is within them, because of the blindness of their hearts.

19 Such as these, despairing, have given themselves over to sexual immorality, carrying out every impurity with rapacity.

20 But this is not what you have learned in Christ.

21 For certainly, you have listened to him, and you have been instructed in him, according to the truth that is in Jesus:

22 to set aside your earlier behavior, the former man, who was corrupted, by means of desire, unto error,

23 and so be renewed in the spirit of your mind,

24 and so put on the new man, who, in accord with God, is created in justice and in the holiness of truth.

25 Because of this, setting aside lying, speak the truth, each one with his neighbor. For we are all part of one another.

26 "Be angry, but do not be willing to sin." Do not let the sun set over your anger.

27 Provide no place for the devil.

28 Whoever was stealing, let him now not steal, but rather let him labor, working with his hands, doing what is good, so that he may have something to distribute to those who suffer need.

29 Let no evil words proceed from your mouth, but only what is good, toward the edification of faith, so as to bestow grace upon those who listen.

30 And do not be willing to grieve the Holy Spirit of God, in whom you have been sealed, unto the day of redemption.

31 Let all bitterness and anger and indignation and outcry and blasphemy be taken away from you, along with all malice.

32 And be kind and merciful to one another, forgiving one another, just as God has forgiven you in Christ.

Ephesians 5

1 Therefore, as most beloved sons, be imitators of God.

2 And walk in love, just as Christ also loved us and delivered himself for us, as an oblation and a sacrifice to God, with a fragrance of sweetness.

3 But let not any kind of fornication, or impurity, or rapacity so much as be named among you, just as is worthy of the saints,

4 nor any indecent, or foolish, or abusive talk, for this is without purpose; but instead, give thanks.

5 For know and understand this: no one who is a fornicator, or lustful, or rapacious (for these are a kind of service to idols) holds an inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and of God.

6 Let no one seduce you with empty words. For because of these things, the wrath of God was sent upon the sons of unbelief.

7 Therefore, do not choose to become participants with them.

8 For you were darkness, in times past, but now you are light, in the Lord. So then, walk as sons of the light.

9 For the fruit of the light is in all goodness and justice and truth,

10 affirming what is well-pleasing to God.

11 And so, have no fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but instead, refute them.

12 For the things that are done by them in secret are shameful, even to mention.

13 But all things that are disputed are made manifest by the light. For all that is made manifest is light.

14 Because of this, it is said: "You who are sleeping: awaken, and rise up from the dead, and so shall the Christ enlighten you."

15 And so, brothers, see to it that you walk cautiously, not like the foolish,

16 but like the wise: atoning for this age, because this is an evil time.

17 For this reason, do not choose to be imprudent. Instead, understand what is the will of God.

18 And do not choose to be inebriated by wine, for this is self-indulgence. Instead, be filled with the Holy Spirit,

19 speaking among yourselves in psalms and hymns and spiritual canticles, singing and reciting psalms to the Lord in your hearts,

20 giving thanks always for everything, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, to God the Father.

21 Be subject to one another in the fear of Christ.

22 Wives should be submissive to their husbands, as to the Lord.

23 For the husband is the head of the wife, just as Christ is the head of the Church. He is the Savior of his body.

24 Therefore, just as the Church is subject to Christ, so also should wives be subject to their husbands in all things.

25 Husbands, love your wives, just as Christ also loved the Church and handed himself over for her,

26 so that he might sanctify her, washing her clean by water and the Word of life,

27 so that he might offer her to himself as a glorious Church, not having any spot or wrinkle or any such thing, so that she would be holy and immaculate.

28 So, too, husbands should love their wives as their own bodies. He who loves his wife loves himself.

29 For no man has ever hated his own flesh, but instead he nourishes and cherishes it, as Christ also does to the Church.

30 For we are a part of his body, of his flesh and of his bones.

31 "For this reason, a man shall leave behind his father and mother, and he shall cling to his wife; and the two shall be as one flesh."

32 This is a great Sacrament. And I am speaking in Christ and in the Church.

33 Yet truly, each and every one of you should love his wife as himself. And a wife should fear her husband.

Ephesians 6

1 Children, obey your parents in the Lord, for this is just.

2 Honor your father and your mother. This is the first commandment with a promise:

3 so that it may be well with you, and so that you may have a long life upon the earth.

4 And you, fathers, do not provoke your children to anger, but educate them with the discipline and correction of the Lord.

5 Servants, be obedient to your lords according to the flesh, with fear and trembling, in the simplicity of your heart, as to Christ.

6 Do not serve only when seen, as if to please men, but act as servants of Christ, doing the will of God from the heart.

7 Serve with good will, as to the Lord, and not to men.

8 For you know that whatever good each one will do, the same will he receive from the Lord, whether he is servant or free.

9 And you, lords, act similarly toward them, setting aside threats, knowing that the Lord of both you and them is in heaven. For with him there is no favoritism toward anyone.

10 Concerning the rest, brothers, be strengthened in the Lord, by the power of his virtue.

11 Be clothed in the armor of God, so that you may be able to stand against the treachery of the devil.

12 For our struggle is not against flesh and blood, but against principalities and powers, against the directors of this world of darkness, against the spirits of wickedness in high places.

13 Because of this, take up the armor of God, so that you may be able to withstand the evil day and remain perfect in all things.

14 Therefore, stand firm, having been girded about your waist with truth, and having been clothed with the breastplate of justice,

15 and having feet which have been shod by the preparation of the Gospel of peace.

16 In all things, take up the shield of faith, with which you may be able to extinguish all the fiery darts of the most wicked one.

17 And take up the helmet of salvation and the sword of the Spirit (which is the Word of God).

18 Through every kind of prayer and supplication, pray at all times in spirit, and so be vigilant with every kind of earnest supplication, for all the saints,

19 and also for me, so that words may be given to me, as I open my mouth with faith to make known the mystery of the Gospel,

20 in such a manner that I may dare to speak exactly as I ought to speak. For I act as an ambassador in chains for the Gospel.

21 Now, so that you also may know the things that concern me and what I am doing, Tychicus, a most beloved brother and a faithful minister in the Lord, will make known everything to you.

22 I have sent him to you for this very reason, so that you may know the things that concern us, and so that he may console your hearts.

23 Peace to the brothers, and charity with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

24 May grace be with all those who love our Lord Jesus Christ, unto incorruption. Amen.

Philippians 1

1 Paul and Timothy, servants of Jesus Christ, to all the saints in Christ Jesus who are at Philippi, with the bishops and deacons.

2 Grace and peace to you, from God our Father and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

3 I give thanks to my God, with every remembrance of you,

4 always, in all my prayers, making supplication for all of you with joy,

5 because of your communion in the Gospel of Christ, from the first day even until now.

6 I am confident of this very thing: that he who has begun this good work in you will perfect it, unto the day of Christ Jesus.

7 So then, it is right for me to feel this way about all of you, because I hold you in my heart, and because, in my chains and in the defense and confirmation of the Gospel, you all are partakers of my joy.

8 For God is my witness how, within the heart of Jesus Christ, I long for all of you.

9 And this I pray: that your charity may abound more and more, with knowledge and with all understanding,

10 so that you may be confirmed in what is better, in order that you may be sincere and without offense on the day of Christ:

11 filled with the fruit of justice, through Jesus Christ, in the glory and praise of God.

12 Now, brothers, I want you to know that the things concerning me happened for the advancement of the Gospel,

13 in such a way that my chains have become manifest in Christ in every place of judgment and in all other such places.

14 And many from among the brothers in the Lord, becoming confident through my chains, are now much bolder in speaking the Word of God without fear.

15 Certainly, some do so even because of envy and contention; and others, too, do so because of a good will to preach Christ.

16 Some act out of charity, knowing that I have been appointed for the defense of the Gospel.

17 But others, out of contention, announce Christ insincerely, claiming that their difficulties lift them up to my chains.

18 But what does it matter? As long as, by every means, whether under pretext or in truthfulness, Christ is announced. And about this, I rejoice, and moreover, I will continue to rejoice.

19 For I know that this will bring me to salvation, through your prayers and under the ministration of the Spirit of Jesus Christ,

20 by means of my own expectation and hope. For in nothing shall I be confounded. Instead, with all confidence, now just as always, Christ shall be magnified in my body, whether by life or by death.

21 For to me, to live is Christ, and to die is gain.

22 And while I live in the flesh, for me, there is the fruit of works. But I do not know which I would choose.

23 For I am constrained between the two: having a desire to be dissolved and to be with Christ, which is the far better thing,

24 but then to remain in the flesh is necessary for your sake.

25 And having this confidence, I know that I shall remain and that I shall continue to remain with all of you, for your advancement and for your joy in the faith,

26 so that your rejoicing may abound in Christ Jesus for me, through my return to you again.

27 Only let your behavior be worthy of the Gospel of Christ, so that, whether I return and see you, or whether, being absent, I hear about you, still you may stand firm with one spirit, with one mind, laboring together for the faith of the Gospel.

28 And in nothing be terrified by the adversaries. For what is to them is an occasion of perdition, is to you an occasion of salvation, and this is from God.

29 For this has been given to you on behalf of Christ, not only so that you may believe in him, but even so that you may suffer with him,

30 engaging in the same struggle, of a kind which you also have seen in me, and which you now have heard from me.

Philippians 2

1 Therefore, if there is any consolation in Christ, any solace of charity, any fellowship of the Spirit, any feelings of commiseration:

2 complete my joy by having the same understanding, holding to the same charity, being of one mind, with the same sentiment.

3 Let nothing be done by contention, nor in vain glory. Instead, in humility, let each of you esteem others to be better than himself.

4 Let each of you not consider anything to be your own, but rather to belong to others.

5 For this understanding in you was also in Christ Jesus:

6 who, though he was in the form of God, did not consider equality with God something to be seized.

7 Instead, he emptied himself, taking the form of a servant, being made in the likeness of men, and accepting the state of a man.

8 He humbled himself, becoming obedient even unto death, even the death of the Cross.

9 Because of this, God has also exalted him and has given him a name which is above every name,

10 so that, at the name of Jesus, every knee would bend, of those in heaven, of those on earth, and of those in hell,

11 and so that every tongue would confess that the Lord Jesus Christ is in the glory of God the Father.

12 And so, my most beloved, just as you have always obeyed, not only in my presence, but even more so now in my absence: work toward your salvation with fear and trembling.

13 For it is God who works in you, both so as to choose, and so as to act, in accord with his good will.

14 And do everything without murmuring or hesitation.

15 So may you be without blame, simple sons of God, without reproof, in the midst of a depraved and perverse nation, among whom you shine like lights in the world,

16 holding to the Word of Life, until my glory in the day of Christ. For I have not run in vain, nor have I labored in vain.

17 Moreover, if I am to be immolated because of the sacrifice and service of your faith, I rejoice and give thanks with all of you.

18 And over this same thing, you also should rejoice and give thanks, together with me.

19 Now I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy to you soon, in order that I may be encouraged, when I know the things concerning you.

20 For I have no one else with such an agreeable mind, who, with sincere affection, is solicitous for you.

21 For they all seek the things that are of themselves, not the things that are of Jesus Christ.

22 So know this evidence of him: that like a son with a father, so has he served with me in the Gospel.

23 Therefore, I hope to send him to you immediately, as soon as I see what will happen concerning me.

24 But I trust in the Lord that I myself will also return to you soon.

25 Now I have considered it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother, and co-worker, and fellow soldier, and an attendant to my needs, but your Apostle.

26 For certainly, he has desired all of you, and he was saddened because you had heard that he was sick.

27 For he was sick, even unto death, but God took pity on him, and not only on him, but truly on myself also, so that I would not have sorrow upon sorrow.

28 Therefore, I sent him more readily, in order that, by seeing him again, you may rejoice, and I may be without sorrow.

29 And so, receive him with every joy in the Lord, and treat all those like him with honor.

30 For he was brought close even to death, for the sake of the work of Christ, handing over his own life, so that he might fulfill what was lacking from you concerning my service.

Philippians 3

1 Concerning other things, my brothers, rejoice in the Lord. It is certainly not tiresome for me to write the same things to you, but for you, it is not necessary.

2 Beware of dogs; beware of those who work evil; beware of those who are divisive.

3 For we are the circumcised, we who serve God in the Spirit and who glory in Christ Jesus, having no confidence in the flesh.

4 Nevertheless, I might have confidence also in the flesh, for if anyone else seems to have confidence in the flesh, more so do I.

5 For I was circumcised on the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, from the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew among Hebrews. According to the law, I was a Pharisee;

6 according to zeal, I persecuted the Church of God; according to the justice that is in the law, I lived without blame.

7 But the things which had been to my gain, the same have I considered a loss, for the sake of Christ.

8 Yet truly, I consider everything to be a loss, because of the preeminent knowledge of Jesus Christ, my Lord, for whose sake I have suffered the loss of everything, considering it all to be like dung, so that I may gain Christ,

9 and so that you may be found in him, not having my justice, which is of the law, but that which is of the faith of Christ Jesus, the justice within faith, which is of God.

10 So shall I know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his Passion, having been fashioned according to his death,

11 if, by some means, I might attain to the resurrection which is from the dead.

12 It is not as though I have already received this, or were already perfect. But rather I pursue, so that by some means I might attain, that in which I have already been attained by Christ Jesus.

13 Brothers, I do not consider that I have already attained this. Instead, I do one thing: forgetting those things that are behind, and extending myself toward those things that are ahead,

14 I pursue the destination, the prize of the heavenly calling of God in Christ Jesus.

15 Therefore, as many of us as are being perfected, let us agree about this. And if in anything you disagree, God will reveal this to you also.

16 Yet truly, whatever point we reach, let us be of the same mind, and let us remain in the same rule.

17 Be imitators of me, brothers, and observe those who are walking similarly, just as you have seen by our example.

18 For many persons, about whom I have often told you (and now tell you, weeping,) are walking as enemies of the cross of Christ.

19 Their end is destruction; their god is their belly; and their glory is in their shame: for they are immersed in earthly things.

20 But our way of life is in heaven. And from heaven, too, we await the Savior, our Lord Jesus Christ,

21 who will transform the body of our lowliness, according to the form of the body of his glory, by means of that power by which he is even able to subject all things to himself.

Philippians 4

1 And so, my most beloved and most desired brothers, my joy and my crown: stand firm in this way, in the Lord, most beloved.

2 I ask Euodia, and I beg Syntyche, to have the same understanding in the Lord.

3 And I also ask you, as my genuine companion, to assist those women who have labored with me in the Gospel, with Clement and the rest of my assistants, whose names are in the Book of Life.

4 Rejoice in the Lord always. Again, I say, rejoice.

5 Let your modesty be known to all men. The Lord is near.

6 Be anxious about nothing. But in all things, with prayer and supplication, with acts of thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God.

7 And so shall the peace of God, which exceeds all understanding, guard your hearts and minds in Christ Jesus.

8 Concerning the rest, brothers, whatever is true, whatever is chaste, whatever is just, whatever is holy, whatever is worthy to be loved, whatever is of good repute, if there is any virtue, if there is any praiseworthy discipline: meditate on these.

9 All the things that you have learned and accepted and heard and seen in me, do these. And so shall the God of peace be with you.

10 Now I rejoice in the Lord exceedingly, because finally, after some time, your feelings for me have flourished again, just as you formerly felt. For you had been preoccupied.

11 I am not saying this as if out of need. For I have learned that, in whatever state I am, it is sufficient.

12 I know how to be humbled, and I know how to abound. I am prepared for anything, anywhere: either to be full or to be hungry, either to have abundance or to endure scarcity.

13 Everything is possible in him who has strengthened me.

14 Yet truly, you have done well by sharing in my tribulation.

15 But you also know, O Philippians, that at the beginning of the Gospel, when I set out from Macedonia, not a single church shared with me in the plan of giving and receiving, except you alone.

16 For you even sent to Thessalonica, once, and then a second time, for what was useful to me.

17 It is not that I am seeking a gift. Instead, I seek the fruit that abounds to your benefit.

18 But I have everything in abundance. I have been filled up, having received from Epaphroditus the things that you sent; this is an odor of sweetness, an acceptable sacrifice, pleasing to God.

19 And may my God fulfill all your desires, according to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus.

20 And to God our Father be glory forever and ever. Amen.

21 Greet every saint in Christ Jesus.

22 The brothers who are with me greet you. All the saints greet you, but especially those who are of Caesar's household.

23 May the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.

Colossians 1

1 Paul, an Apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, and Timothy, a brother,

2 to the saints and faithful brothers in Christ Jesus who are at Colossae.

3 Grace and peace to you, from God our Father and from the Lord Jesus Christ. We give thanks to God, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, praying for you always.

4 For we have heard of your faith in Christ Jesus, and of the love that you have toward all the saints,

5 because of the hope that has been stored up for you in heaven, which you have heard through the Word of Truth in the Gospel.

6 This has reached you, just as it is present in the whole world, where it grows and bears fruit, as it has also done in you, since the day when you first heard and knew the grace of God in truth,

7 just as you learned it from Epaphras, our most beloved fellow servant, who is for you a faithful minister of Christ Jesus.

8 And he has also manifested to us your love in the Spirit.

9 Then, too, from the day when we first heard it, we have not ceased praying for you and requesting that you be filled with the knowledge of his will, with all wisdom and spiritual understanding,

10 so that you may walk in a manner worthy of God, being pleasing in all things, being fruitful in every good work, and increasing in the knowledge of God,

11 being strengthened in every virtue, in accord with the power of his glory, with all patience and longsuffering, with joy,

12 giving thanks to God the Father, who has made us worthy to have a share in the portion of the saints, in the light.

13 For he has rescued us from the power of darkness, and he has transferred us into the kingdom of the Son of his love,

14 in whom we have redemption through his blood, the remission of sins.

15 He is the image of the invisible God, the first-born of every creature.

16 For in him was created everything in heaven and on earth, visible and invisible, whether thrones, or dominations, or principalities, or powers. All things were created through him and in him.

17 And he is before all, and in him all things continue.

18 And he is the head of his body, the Church. He is the beginning, the first-born from the dead, so that in all things he may hold primacy.

19 For the Father is well-pleased that all fullness reside in him,

20 and that, through him, all things be reconciled to himself, making peace through the blood of his cross, for the things that are on earth, as well as the things that are in heaven.

21 And you, though you had been, in times past, understood to be foreigners and enemies, with works of evil,

22 yet now he has reconciled you, by his body of flesh, through death, so as to offer you, holy and immaculate and blameless, before him.

23 So then, continue in the faith: well-founded and steadfast and immovable, by the hope of the Gospel that you have heard, which has been preached throughout all creation under heaven, the Gospel of which I, Paul, have become a minister.

24 For now I rejoice in my passion on your behalf, and I complete in my flesh the things that are lacking in the Passion of Christ, for the sake of his body, which is the Church.

25 For I have become a minister of the Church, according to the dispensation of God that has been given to me among you, so that I may fulfill the Word of God,

26 the mystery which had remained hidden to past ages and generations, but which now is manifested to his saints.

27 To them, God willed to made known the riches of the glory of this mystery among the Gentiles, which is Christ and the hope of his glory within you.

28 We are announcing him, correcting every man and teaching every man, with all wisdom, so that we may offer every man perfect in Christ Jesus.

29 In him, too, I labor, striving according to his action within me, which he works in virtue.

Colossians 2

1 For I want you to know the kind of solicitude that I have for you, and for those who are at Laodicea, as well as for those who have not seen my face in the flesh.

2 May their hearts be consoled and instructed in charity, with all the riches of a plenitude of understanding, with knowledge of the mystery of God the Father and of Christ Jesus.

3 For in him are hidden all treasures of wisdom and knowledge.

4 Now I say this, so that no one may deceive you with grandiose words.

5 For though I may be absent in body, yet I am with you in spirit. And I rejoice as I gaze upon your order and its foundation, which is in Christ, your faith.

6 Therefore, just as you have received the Lord Jesus Christ, walk in him.

7 Be rooted and continually built up in Christ. And be confirmed in the faith, just as you have also learned it, increasing in him with acts of thanksgiving.

8 See to it that no one deceives you through philosophy and empty falsehoods, as found in the traditions of men, in accord with the influences of the world, and not in accord with Christ.

9 For in him, all the fullness of the Divine Nature dwells bodily.

10 And in him, you have been filled; for he is the head of all principality and power.

11 In him also, you have been circumcised with a circumcision not made by hand, not by the despoiling of the body of flesh, but by the circumcision of Christ.

12 You have been buried with him in baptism. In him also, you have risen again through faith, by the work of God, who raised him up from the dead.

13 And when you were dead in your transgressions and in the uncircumcision of your flesh, he enlivened you, together with him, forgiving you of all transgressions,

14 and wiping away the handwriting of the decree which was against us, which was contrary to us. And he has taken this away from your midst, affixing it to the Cross.

15 And so, despoiling principalities and powers, he has led them away confidently and openly, triumphing over them in himself.

16 Therefore, let no one judge you as concerns food or drink, or a particular feast day, or feast days of new moons, or of Sabbaths.

17 For these are a shadow of the future, but the body is of Christ.

18 Let no one seduce you, preferring base things and a religion of Angels, walking according to what he has not seen, being vainly inflated by the sensations of his flesh,

19 and not holding up the head, with which the whole body, by its underlying joints and ligaments, is joined together and grows with an increase that is of God.

20 So then, if you have died with Christ to the influences of this world, why do you still make decisions as if you were living in the world?

21 Do not touch, do not taste, do not handle these things,

22 which all lead to destruction by their very use, in accord with the precepts and doctrines of men.

23 Such ideas have at least an intention to attain to wisdom, but through superstition and debasement, not sparing the body, and they are without any honor in satiating the flesh.

Colossians 3

1 Therefore, if you have risen together with Christ, seek the things that are above, where Christ is seated at the right hand of God.

2 Consider the things that are above, not the things that are upon the earth.

3 For you have died, and so your life is hidden with Christ in God.

4 When Christ, your life, appears, then you also will appear with him in glory.

5 Therefore, mortify your body, while it is upon the earth. For because of fornication, impurity, lust, evil desires, and avarice, which are a kind of service to idols,

6 the wrath of God has overwhelmed the sons of unbelief.

7 You, too, walked in these things, in times past, when you were living among them.

8 But now you must set aside all these things: anger, indignation, malice, blasphemy, and indecent speech from your mouth.

9 Do not lie to one another. Strip yourselves of the old man, with his deeds,

10 and clothe yourself with the new man, who has been renewed by knowledge, in accord with the image of the One who created him,

11 where there is neither Gentile nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, Barbarian nor Scythian, servant nor free. Instead, Christ is everything, in everyone.

12 Therefore, clothe yourselves like the elect of God: holy and beloved, with hearts of mercy, kindness, humility, modesty, and patience.

13 Support one another, and, if anyone has a complaint against another, forgive one another. For just as the Lord has forgiven you, so also must you do.

14 And above all these things have charity, which is the bond of perfection.

15 And let the peace of Christ lift up your hearts. For in this peace, you have been called, as one body. And be thankful.

16 Let the word of Christ live in you in abundance, with all wisdom, teaching and correcting one another, with psalms, hymns, and spiritual canticles, singing to God with the grace in your hearts.

17 Let everything whatsoever that you do, whether in word or in deed, be done all in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, giving thanks to God the Father through him.

18 Wives, be submissive to your husbands, as is proper in the Lord.

19 Husbands, love your wives, and do not be bitter toward them.

20 Children, obey your parents in all things. For this is well-pleasing to the Lord.

21 Fathers, do not provoke your children to indignation, lest they lose heart.

22 Servants, obey, in all things, your lords according to the flesh, not serving only when seen, as if to please men, but serving in simplicity of heart, fearing God.

23 Whatever you do, do it from the heart, as for the Lord, and not for men.

24 For you know that you will receive from the Lord the repayment of an inheritance. Serve Christ the Lord.

25 For whoever causes injury shall be repaid for what he has wrongfully done. And there no favoritism with God.

Colossians 4

1 You masters, supply your servants with what is just and equitable, knowing that you, too, have a Master in heaven.

2 Pursue prayer. Be watchful in prayer with acts of thanksgiving.

3 Pray together, for us also, so that God may open a door of speech to us, so as to speak the mystery of Christ, (because of which, even now, I am in chains)

4 so that I may manifest it in the manner that I ought to speak.

5 Walk in wisdom toward those who are outside, redeeming this age.

6 Let your speech be ever graceful, seasoned with salt, so that you may know how you ought to respond to each person.

7 As for the things that concern me, Tychicus, a most beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow servant in the Lord, will make everything known to you.

8 I have sent him to you for this very purpose, so that he may know the things that concern you, and may console your hearts,

9 with Onesimus, a most beloved and faithful brother, who is from among you. They shall make known to you everything that is happening here.

10 Aristarchus, my fellow prisoner, greets you, as does Mark, the near cousin of Barnabas, about whom you have received instructions, (if he comes to you, receive him)

11 and Jesus, who is called Justus, and those who are of the circumcision. These alone are my assistants, unto the kingdom of God; they have been a consolation to me.

12 Epaphras greets you, who is from among you, a servant of Christ Jesus, ever solicitous for you in prayer, so that you may stand, perfect and complete, in the entire will of God.

13 For I offer testimony to him, that he has labored greatly for you, and for those who are at Laodicea, and for those at Hierapolis.

14 Luke, a most beloved physician, greets you, as does Demas.

15 Greet the brothers who are at Laodicea, and Nymphas, and those who are at his house, a church.

16 And when this epistle has been read among you, cause it to be read also in the church of the Laodiceans, and you should read that which is from the Laodiceans.

17 And tell Archippus: "See to the ministry that you have received in the Lord, in order to fulfill it."

18 The greeting of Paul by my own hand. Remember my chains. May grace be with you. Amen.

1 Thessalonians 1

1 Paul and Sylvanus and Timothy, to the church of the Thessalonians, in God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

2 Grace and peace to you. We give thanks to God always for all of you, keeping the memory of you in our prayers without ceasing,

3 remembering your work of faith, and hardship, and charity, and enduring hope, in our Lord Jesus Christ, before God our Father.

4 For we know, brothers, beloved of God, of your election.

5 For our Gospel has not been among you in word alone, but also in virtue, and in the Holy Spirit, and with a great fullness, in the same manner as you know we have acted among you for your sake.

6 And so, you became imitators of us and of the Lord, accepting the Word in the midst of great tribulation, but with the joy of the Holy Spirit.

7 So have you become a pattern for all who believe in Macedonia and in Achaia.

8 For from you, the Word of the Lord was spread, not only in Macedonia and in Achaia, but also in every place. Your faith, which is toward God, has advanced so much so that we do not need to speak to you about anything.

9 For others are reporting among us of the kind of acceptance we had among you, and how you were converted from idols to God, to the service of the living and true God,

10 and to the expectation of his Son from heaven (whom he raised up from the dead), Jesus, who has rescued us from the approaching wrath.

1 Thessalonians 2

1 For you yourselves know, brothers, that our acceptance among you was not empty.

2 Instead, having previously suffered and been treated shamefully, as you know, at Philippi, we had confidence in our God, so as to speak the Gospel of God to you with much solicitude.

3 For our exhortation was not in error, nor from impurity, nor with deception.

4 But, just as we have been tested by God, so that the Gospel would be entrusted to us, so also did we speak, not so as to please men, but rather to please God, who tests our hearts.

5 And neither did we, at any time, become flattering in speech, as you know, nor did we seek an opportunity for avarice, as God is witness.

6 Nor did we seek the glory of men, neither from you, nor from others.

7 And although we could have been a burden to you, as Apostles of Christ, instead we became like little ones in your midst, like a nurse cherishing her children.

8 So desirous were we for you that we were willing to hand over to you, not only the Gospel of God, but even our own souls. For you have become most beloved to us.

9 For you remember, brothers, our hardship and weariness. We preached the Gospel of God among you, working night and day, so that we would not be burdensome to any of you.

10 You are witnesses, as is God, of how holy and just and blameless we were with you who have believed.

11 And you know the manner, with each one of you, like a father with his sons,

12 in which we were pleading with you and consoling you, bearing witness, so that you would walk in a manner worthy of God, who has called you into his kingdom and glory.

13 For this reason also, we give thanks to God without ceasing: because, when you had accepted from us the Word of the hearing of God, you accepted it not as the word of men, but (as it truly is) as the Word of God, who is working in you who have believed.

14 For you, brothers, have become imitators of the churches of God which are at Judea, in Christ Jesus. For you, too, have suffered the same things from your fellow countrymen as they have suffered from the Jews,

15 who also killed both the Lord Jesus, and the Prophets, and who have persecuted us. But they do not please God, and so they are adversaries to all men.

16 They prohibit us to speak to the Gentiles, so that they may be saved, and thus do they continually add to their own sins. But the wrath of God will overtake them in the very end.

17 And we, brothers, having been deprived of you for a short time, in sight, but not in heart, have hurried all the more to see your face, with a great desire.

18 For we wanted to come to you, (indeed, I, Paul, attempted to do so once, and then again,) but Satan impeded us.

19 For what is our hope, and our joy, and our crown of glory? Is it not you, before our Lord Jesus Christ at his return?

20 For you are our glory and our joy.

1 Thessalonians 3

1 Because of this, willing to wait no longer, it was pleasing to us to remain at Athens, alone.

2 And we sent Timothy, our brother and a minister of God in the Gospel of Christ, to confirm you and to exhort you, on behalf of your faith,

3 so that no one would be disturbed during these tribulations. For you yourselves know that we have been appointed to this.

4 For even while we were with you, we predicted to you that we would suffer tribulations, even as it has happened, and as you know.

5 For this reason also, I was not willing to wait any longer, and I sent to find out about your faith, lest perhaps he who tempts may have tempted you, and our labor might have been in vain.

6 But then, when Timothy arrived to us from you, he reported to us your faith and charity, and that you keep a good remembrance of us always, desiring to see us, just as we likewise desire to see you.

7 As a result, we were consoled in you, brothers, in the midst of all our difficulties and tribulations, through your faith.

8 For we now live so that you may stand firm in the Lord.

9 For what thanks would we be able to repay to God because of you, for all the joy with which we rejoice over you before our God?

10 For night and day, ever more abundantly, we are praying that we may see your face, and that we may complete those things that are lacking in your faith.

11 But may God our Father himself, and our Lord Jesus Christ, direct our way to you.

12 And may the Lord multiply you, and make you abound in your charity toward one another and toward all, just as we also do toward you,

13 in order to confirm your hearts without blame, in sanctity, before God our Father, unto the return of our Lord Jesus Christ, with all his saints. Amen.

1 Thessalonians 4

1 Therefore, concerning other things, brothers, we ask and beg you, in the Lord Jesus, that, just as you have received from us the way in which you ought to walk and to please God, so also may you walk, in order that you may abound all the more.

2 For you know what precepts I have given to you through the Lord Jesus.

3 For this is the will of God, your sanctification: that you should abstain from fornication,

4 that each one of you should know how to possess his vessel in sanctification and honor,

5 not in passions of lust, like the Gentiles who do not know God,

6 and that no one should overwhelm or circumvent his brother in business. For the Lord is the vindicator of all these things, just as we have preached and testified to you.

7 For God has not called us to impurity, but to sanctification.

8 And so, whoever despises these teachings, does not despise man, but God, who has even provided his Holy Spirit within us.

9 But concerning the charity of brotherhood, we have no need to write to you. For you yourselves have learned from God that you should love one another.

10 For indeed, you act in this way with all the brothers in all of Macedonia. But we petition you, brothers, so that you may abound all the more,

11 to choose work that allows you to be tranquil, and to carry out your business and to do your work with your own hands, just as we have instructed you,

12 and to walk honestly with those who are outside, and to desire nothing belonging to another.

13 And we do not want you to be ignorant, brothers, concerning those who are sleeping, so as not to be sorrowful, like these others who do not have hope.

14 For if we believe that Jesus has died and risen again, so also will God bring back with Jesus those who sleep in him.

15 For we say this to you, in the Word of the Lord: that we who are alive, who remain until the return of the Lord, will not precede those who have fallen asleep.

16 For the Lord himself, with a command and with the voice of an Archangel and with a trumpet of God, shall descend from heaven. And the dead, who are in Christ, shall rise up first.

17 Next, we who are alive, who are remaining, shall be taken up quickly together with them into the clouds to meet Christ in the air. And in this way, we shall be with the Lord always.

18 Therefore, console one another with these words.

1 Thessalonians 5

1 But concerning dates and times, brothers, you do not need us to write to you.

2 For you yourselves thoroughly understand that the day of the Lord shall arrive much like a thief in the night.

3 For when they will say, "Peace and security!" then destruction will suddenly overwhelm them, like the labor pains of a woman with child, and they will not escape.

4 But you, brothers, are not in darkness, so that you would be overtaken by that day as by a thief.

5 For all of you are sons of light and sons of daytime; we are not of nighttime, nor of darkness.

6 Therefore, let us not sleep, as the rest do. Instead, we should be vigilant and sober.

7 For those who sleep, sleep in the night; and those who are inebriated, are inebriated in the night.

8 But we, who are of the daylight, should be sober, being clothed with the breastplate of faith and of charity and having, as a helmet, the hope of salvation.

9 For God has not appointed us for wrath, but for the acquisition of salvation through our Lord Jesus Christ,

10 who died for us, so that, whether we watch, or whether we sleep, we may live in union with him.

11 Because of this, console one another and build up one another, just as you are doing.

12 And we ask you, brothers, to recognize those who labor among you, and who preside over you in the Lord, and who admonish you,

13 so that you may consider them with an abundance of charity, for the sake of their work. Be at peace with them.

14 And we ask you, brothers: correct the disruptive, console the weak-minded, support the sick, be patient with everyone.

15 See to it that no one repays evil for evil to anyone. Instead, always pursue whatever is good, with one another and with all.

16 Rejoice always.

17 Pray without ceasing.

18 Give thanks in everything. For this is the will of God in Christ Jesus for all of you.

19 Do not choose to extinguish the Spirit.

20 Do not spurn prophecies.

21 But test all things. Hold on to whatever is good.

22 Abstain from every kind of evil.

23 And may the God of peace himself sanctify you through all things, so that your whole spirit and soul and body may be preserved without blame unto the return of our Lord Jesus Christ.

24 He who has called you is faithful. He shall act even now.

25 Brothers, pray for us.

26 Greet all the brothers with a holy kiss.

27 I bind you, through the Lord, that this epistle is to be read to all the holy brothers.

28 May the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you. Amen.

2 Thessalonians 2

1 But we ask you, brothers, concerning the advent of our Lord Jesus Christ and of our gathering to him,

2 that you not be readily disturbed or terrified in your minds, by any spirit, or word, or epistle, supposedly sent from us, claiming that the day of the Lord is close by.

3 Let no one deceive you in any way. For this cannot be, unless the apostasy will have arrived first, and the man of sin will have been revealed, the son of perdition,

4 who is an adversary to, and who is lifted up above, all that is called God or that is worshipped, so much so that he sits in the temple of God, presenting himself as if he were God.

5 Do you not recall that, when I was still with you, I told you these things?

6 And now you know what it is that holds him back, so that he may be revealed in his own time.

7 For the mystery of iniquity is already at work. And only one now holds back, and will continue to hold back, until he is taken from our midst.

8 And then that iniquitous one shall be revealed, the one whom the Lord Jesus shall bring to ruin with the spirit of his mouth, and shall destroy at the brightness of his return:

9 him whose advent is accompanied by the works of Satan, with every kind of power and signs and false miracles,

10 and with every seduction of iniquity, toward those who are perishing because they have not accepted the love of truth, so that they may be saved. For this reason, God will send to them works of deception, so that they may believe in lies,

11 in order that all those who have not believed in the truth, but who have consented to iniquity, may be judged.

12 Yet we must always give thanks to God for you, brothers, beloved of God, because God has chosen you as first-fruits for salvation, by the sanctification of the Spirit and by faith in the truth.

13 He has also called you into truth through our Gospel, unto the acquisition of the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ.

14 And so, brothers, stand firm, and hold to the traditions that you have learned, whether by word or by our epistle.

15 So may our Lord Jesus Christ himself, and God our Father, who has loved us and who has given us an everlasting consolation and good hope in grace,

16 exhort your hearts and confirm you in every good word and deed.

2 Thessalonians 3

1 Concerning other things, brothers, pray for us, so that the Word of God may advance and be glorified, just as it is among you,

2 and so that we may be freed from pertinacious and evil men. For not everyone is faithful.

3 But God is faithful. He will strengthen you, and he will guard you from evil.

4 And we have confidence about you in the Lord, that you are doing, and will continue to do, just as we have instructed.

5 And may the Lord direct your hearts, in the charity of God and with the patience of Christ.

6 But we strongly caution you, brothers, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, to draw yourselves away from every brother who is walking in disorder and not according to the tradition that they received from us.

7 For you yourselves know the manner in which you ought to imitate us. For we were not disorderly among you.

8 Nor did we eat bread from anyone for free, but rather, we worked night and day, in hardship and weariness, so as not to be burdensome to you.

9 It was not as if we had no authority, but this was so that we might present ourselves as an example to you, in order to imitate us.

10 Then, too, while we were with you, we insisted on this to you: that if anyone was not willing to work, neither should he eat.

11 For we have heard that there are some among you who act disruptively, not working at all, but eagerly meddling.

12 Now we charge those who act in this way, and we beg them in the Lord Jesus Christ, that they work in silence and eat their own bread.

13 And you, brothers, do not grow weak in doing good.

14 But if anyone does not obey our word by this epistle, take note of him and do not keep company with him, so that he may be ashamed.

15 But do not be willing to consider him as an enemy; instead, correct him as a brother.

16 Then may the Lord of peace himself give you an everlasting peace, in every place. May the Lord be with all of you.

17 The greeting of Paul with my own hand, which is the seal in every epistle. So do I write.

18 May the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.

1 Timothy 1

1 Paul, an Apostle of Jesus Christ by the authority of God our Savior and Christ Jesus our hope,

2 to Timothy, beloved son in the faith. Grace, mercy, and peace, from God the Father and from Christ Jesus our Lord.

3 Now I asked you to remain at Ephesus, while I went into Macedonia, so that you would speak strongly against certain ones who have been teaching a different way,

4 against those who have been paying attention to fables and endless genealogies. These things present questions as if they were greater than the edification that is of God, which is in faith.

5 Now the goal of instruction is charity from a pure heart, and a good conscience, and an unfeigned faith.

6 Certain persons, wandering away from these things, have been turned aside to empty babbling,

7 desiring to be teachers of the law, but understanding neither the things that they themselves are saying, nor what they are affirming about these things.

8 But we know that the law is good, if one makes use of it properly.

9 Knowing this, that the law was not set in place for the just, but for the unjust and the insubordinate, for the impious and sinners, for the wicked and the defiled, for those who commit patricide, matricide, or homicide,

10 for fornicators, for males who sleep with males, for kidnappers, for liars, for perjurers, and whatever else is contrary to sound doctrine,

11 which is in accord with the Gospel of the glory of the blessed God, the Gospel which has been entrusted to me.

12 I give thanks to him who has strengthened me, Christ Jesus our Lord, because he has considered me faithful, placing me in the ministry,

13 though previously I was a blasphemer, and a persecutor, and contemptuous. But then I obtained the mercy of God. For I had been acting ignorantly, in unbelief.

14 And so the grace of our Lord has abounded greatly, with the faith and love that is in Christ Jesus.

15 It is a faithful saying, and worthy of acceptance by everyone, that Christ Jesus came into this world to bring salvation to sinners, among whom I am first.

16 But it was for this reason that I obtained mercy, so that in me as first, Christ Jesus would display all patience, for the instruction of those who would believe in him unto eternal life.

17 So then, to the King of ages, to the immortal, invisible, solitary God, be honor and glory forever and ever. Amen.

18 This precept I commend to you, my son Timothy, in accord with the prophets who preceded you: that you serve among them like a soldier in a good war,

19 holding to faith and good conscience, against those who, by rejecting these things, have made a shipwreck of the faith.

20 Among these are Hymenaeus and Alexander, whom I have handed over to Satan, so that they may learn not to blaspheme.

1 Timothy 2

1 And so I beg you, first of all, to make supplications, prayers, petitions, and thanksgivings for all men,

2 for kings, and for all who are in high places, so that we may lead a quiet and tranquil life in all piety and chastity.

3 For this is good and acceptable in the sight of God our Savior,

4 who wants all men to be saved and to arrive at an acknowledgment of the truth.

5 For there is one God, and one mediator of God and of men, the man Christ Jesus,

6 who gave himself as a redemption for all, as a testimony in its proper time.

7 Of this testimony, I have been appointed a preacher and an Apostle, (I speak the truth, I do not lie) as a teacher of the Gentiles, in faith and in truth.

8 Therefore, I want men to pray in every place, lifting up pure hands, without anger or dissension.

9 Similarly also, women should be dressed fittingly, adorning themselves with compunction and restraint, and not with plaited hair, nor gold, nor pearls, nor costly attire,

10 but in a manner proper for women who are professing piety by means of good works.

11 Let a woman learn in silence with all subjection.

12 For I do not permit a woman to teach, nor to be in authority over a man, but to be in silence.

13 For Adam was formed first, then Eve.

14 And Adam was not seduced, but the woman, having been seduced, was in transgression.

15 Yet she will be saved by bearing children, if she has continued in faith and love, and in sanctification accompanied by self-restraint.

1 Timothy 3

1 It is a faithful saying: if a man desires the episcopate, he desires a good work.

2 Therefore, it is necessary for a bishop to be beyond reproach, the husband of one wife, sober, prudent, gracious, chaste, hospitable, a teacher,

3 not a drunkard, not combative but restrained, not quarrelsome, not covetous;

4 but a man who leads his own house well, having children who are subordinate with all chastity.

5 For if a man does not know how to lead his own house, how will he take care of the Church of God?

6 He must not be a new convert, lest, being elated by pride, he may fall under the sentence of the devil.

7 And it is necessary for him also to have good testimony from those who are outside, so that he may not fall into disrepute and the snare of the devil.

8 Similarly, deacons must be chaste, not double-tongued, not given to much wine, not pursuing tainted profit,

9 holding to the mystery of the faith with a pure conscience.

10 And these things should be proven first, and then they may minister, being without offense.

11 Similarly, the women must be chaste, not slanderers, sober, faithful in all things.

12 Deacons should be the husband of one wife, men who lead their own children and their own houses well.

13 For those who have ministered well will acquire for themselves a good position, and much confidence in the faith which is in Christ Jesus.

14 I am writing these things to you, with the hope that I will come to you soon.

15 But, if I am delayed, you should know the manner in which it is necessary to conduct yourself in the house of God, which is the Church of the living God, the pillar and the foundation of truth.

16 And it is clearly great, this mystery of piety, which was manifested in the flesh, which was justified in the Spirit, which has appeared to Angels, which has been preached to the Gentiles, which is believed in the world, which has been taken up in glory.

1 Timothy 4

1 Now the Spirit has clearly said that, in the end times, some persons will depart from the faith, paying attention to spirits of error and the doctrines of devils,

2 speaking lies in hypocrisy, and having their consciences seared,

3 prohibiting marriage, abstaining from foods, which God has created to be accepted with thanksgiving by the faithful and by those who have understood the truth.

4 For every creature of God is good, and nothing is to be rejected which is received with thanksgiving;

5 for it has been sanctified by the Word of God and by prayer.

6 By proposing these things to the brothers, you will be a good minister of Christ Jesus, nourished by words of faith, and by the good doctrine that you have secured.

7 But avoid the silly fables of old women. And exercise yourself so as to advance in piety.

8 For the exercise of the body is somewhat useful. But piety is useful in all things, holding the promise of life, in the present and in the future.

9 This is a faithful saying and worthy of full acceptance.

10 For this reason we labor and are maligned: because we hope in the living God, who is the Savior of all men, most especially of the faithful.

11 Instruct and teach these things.

12 Let no one despise your youth, but be an example among the faithful in word, in behavior, in charity, in faith, in chastity.

13 Until I arrive, attend to reading, to exhortation, and to doctrine.

14 Do not be willing to neglect the grace that is within you, which was given to you through prophecy, with the imposition of the hands of the priesthood.

15 Meditate on these things, so that your progress may be manifest to all.

16 Pay attention to yourself and to doctrine. Pursue these things. For in doing so, you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.

1 Timothy 5

1 You should not rebuke an old man, but rather plead with him, as if he were your father; with young men, like brothers;

2 with old women, like mothers; with young women, in all chastity, like sisters.

3 Honor those widows who are true widows.

4 But if any widow has children or grandchildren, let her first learn to manage her own household, and to fulfill, in turn, her own obligation to her parents; for this is acceptable before God.

5 But she who is truly a widow and is destitute, let her hope in God, and let her be urgent in supplications and prayers, night and day.

6 For she who is living in pleasures is dead, while living.

7 And give instruction in this, so that they may be beyond reproach.

8 But if anyone has no concern for his own, and especially for those of his own household, he has denied the faith, and he is worse than an unbeliever.

9 Let a widow be chosen who is no less than sixty years of age, who was the wife of one husband,

10 who has testimony of her good works: whether she has educated children, or has provided hospitality, or has washed the feet of the saints, or has ministered to those suffering tribulation, or has pursued any kind of good work.

11 But avoid the younger widows. For once they have flourished in Christ, they will want to marry,

12 resulting in damnation, because they have disregarded the primacy of faith.

13 And being at the same time also idle, they learn to go from house to house, being not only idle, but also talkative and curious, speaking of things which do not concern them.

14 Therefore, I want the younger women to marry, to procreate children, to be mothers of families, to provide no ready opportunity for the adversary to speak evil.

15 For certain ones have already been turned back to Satan.

16 If any among the faithful have widows, let him minister to them and not burden the Church, so that there may be enough for those who are true widows.

17 Let priests who lead well be held worthy of twice the honor, especially those who labor in the Word and in doctrine.

18 For Scripture says: "You shall not muzzle an ox as it is treading out the grain," and, "The worker is worthy of his pay."

19 Do not be willing to accept an accusation against a priest, except under two or three witnesses.

20 Reprove sinners in the sight of everyone, so that the others may have fear.

21 I testify before God and Christ Jesus and the elect Angels, that you should observe these things without prejudgment, doing nothing which shows favoritism to either side.

22 You should not be quick to impose hands on anyone, nor should you take part in the sins of outsiders. Keep yourself chaste.

23 Do not continue to drink only water, but make use of a little wine, for the sake of your stomach and your frequent infirmities.

24 The sins of some men have been made manifest, preceding them to judgment, but those of others are manifested later.

25 Similarly, too, good deeds have been made manifest, but even when they are not, they cannot remain hidden.

1 Timothy 6

1 Whoever are servants under the yoke, let them consider their masters to be worthy of every honor, lest the name and doctrine of the Lord be blasphemed.

2 But those who have believing masters, let them not despise them because they are brothers, but rather serve them all the more because they are believing and beloved, participants of the same service. Teach and exhort these things.

3 If anyone teaches otherwise, and does not consent to the sound words of our Lord Jesus Christ, and to that doctrine which is in accord with piety,

4 then he is arrogant, knowing nothing, yet languishing amid the questions and quarrels of words. From these arise envy, contention, blasphemy, evil suspicions:

5 the conflicts of men who have been corrupted in mind and deprived of truth, who consider profit to be piety.

6 But piety with sufficiency is great gain.

7 For we brought nothing into this world, and there is no doubt that we can take nothing away.

8 But, having nourishment and some kind of covering, we should be content with these.

9 For those who want to become rich fall into temptation and into the snare of the devil and into many useless and harmful desires, which submerge men in destruction and in perdition.

10 For desire is the root of all evils. Some persons, hungering in this way, have strayed from the faith and have entangled themselves in many sorrows.

11 But you, O man of God, flee from these things, and truly pursue justice, piety, faith, charity, patience, meekness.

12 Fight the good fight of faith. Take hold of the eternal life to which you have been called, and make a good profession of faith in the sight of many witnesses.

13 I charge you, in the sight of God, who enlivens all things, and in the sight of Christ Jesus, who gave the testimony of a good profession under Pontius Pilate,

14 to observe the commandment, immaculately, irreproachably, unto the return of our Lord Jesus Christ.

15 For at the proper time, he shall reveal the blessed and only Power, the King of kings and the Lord of lords,

16 who alone holds immortality, and who inhabits the inaccessible light, whom no man has seen, nor even is able to see, to whom is honor and everlasting dominion. Amen.

17 Instruct the wealthy of this age not to have a superior attitude, nor to hope in the uncertainty of riches, but in the living God, who offers us everything in abundance to enjoy,

18 and to do good, to become rich in good works, to donate readily, to share,

19 to gather for themselves the treasure of a good foundation for the future, so that they may obtain true life.

20 O Timothy, guard what has been deposited with you, avoiding the voice of profane novelties and of opposing ideas, which are falsely called knowledge.

21 Certain persons, promising these things, have perished from the faith. May grace be with you. Amen.

2 Timothy 1

1 Paul, an Apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God, in accord with the promise of the life which is in Christ Jesus,

2 to Timothy, most beloved son. Grace, mercy, peace, from God the Father and from Christ Jesus our Lord.

3 I give thanks to God, whom I serve, as my forefathers did, with a pure conscience. For without ceasing I hold the remembrance of you in my prayers, night and day,

4 desiring to see you, recalling your tears so as to be filled with joy,

5 calling to mind the same faith, which is in you unfeigned, which also first dwelt in your grandmother, Lois, and in your mother, Eunice, and also, I am certain, in you.

6 Because of this, I admonish you to revive the grace of God, which is in you by the imposition of my hands.

7 For God has not given us a spirit of fear, but of virtue, and of love, and of self-restraint.

8 And so, do not be ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me, his prisoner. Instead, collaborate with the Gospel in accord with the virtue of God,

9 who has freed us and has called us to his holy vocation, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace, which was given to us in Christ Jesus, before the ages of time.

10 And this has now been made manifest by the illumination of our Savior Jesus Christ, who certainly has destroyed death, and who has also illuminated life and incorruption through the Gospel.

11 Of this Gospel, I have been appointed a preacher, and an Apostle, and a teacher of the Gentiles.

12 For this reason, I also suffer these things. But I am not confounded. For I know in whom I have believed, and I am certain that he has the power to preserve what was entrusted to me, unto that day.

13 Hold to the kind of sound words that you have heard from me in the faith and love which is in Christ Jesus.

14 Guard the good entrusted to you through the Holy Spirit, who lives within us.

15 Know this: that all those who are in Asia have turned away from me, among whom are Phigellus and Hermogenes.

16 May the Lord have mercy on the house of Onesiphorus, because he has often refreshed me, and he has not been ashamed of my chains.

17 Instead, when he had arrived in Rome, he anxiously sought me and found me.

18 May the Lord grant to him to obtain mercy from the Lord in that day. And you know well in how many ways he has ministered to me at Ephesus.

2 Timothy 2

1 And as for you, my son, be strengthened by the grace which is in Christ Jesus,

2 and by the things which you have heard from me through many witnesses. These things encourage faithful men, who shall then be suitable to teach others also.

3 Labor like a good soldier of Christ Jesus.

4 No man, acting as a soldier for God, entangles himself in worldly matters, so that he may be pleasing to him for whom he has proven himself.

5 Then, too, whoever strives in a competition is not crowned, unless he has competed lawfully.

6 The farmer who labors ought to be the first to share in the produce.

7 Understand what I am saying. For the Lord will give you understanding in all things.

8 Be mindful that the Lord Jesus Christ, who is the offspring of David, has risen again from the dead, according to my Gospel.

9 I labor in this Gospel, even while chained like an evildoer. But the Word of God is not bound.

10 I endure all things for this reason: for the sake of the elect, so that they, too, may obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus, with heavenly glory.

11 It is a faithful saying: that if we have died with him, we will also live with him.

12 If we suffer, we will also reign with him. If we deny him, he will also deny us.

13 If we are unfaithful, he remains faithful: he is not able to deny himself.

14 Insist on these things, testifying before the Lord. Do not be contentious about words, for this is useful for nothing but the subversion of listeners.

15 Be solicitous in the task of presenting yourself before God as a proven and unashamed worker who has handled the Word of Truth correctly.

16 But avoid profane or empty talk. For these things advance one greatly in impiety.

17 And their word spreads like a cancer: among these are Hymenaeus and Philetus,

18 who have fallen away from the truth by saying that the resurrection is already complete. And so they have subverted the faith of certain persons.

19 But the firm foundation of God remains standing, having this seal: the Lord knows those who are his own, and all who know the name of the Lord depart from iniquity.

20 But, in a large house, there are not only vessels of gold and of silver, but also those of wood and of clay; and certainly some are held in honor, but others in dishonor.

21 If anyone, then, will have cleansed himself from these things, he shall be a vessel held in honor, sanctified and useful to the Lord, prepared for every good work.

22 So then, flee from the desires of your youth, yet truly, pursue justice, faith, hope, charity, and peace, along with those who call upon the Lord from a pure heart.

23 But avoid foolish and undisciplined questions, for you know that these produce strife.

24 For the servant of the Lord must not be contentious, but instead he must be meek toward everyone, teachable, patient,

25 correcting with self-restraint those who resist the truth. For at any time God may give them repentance, so as to recognize the truth,

26 and then they may recover from the snares of the devil, by whom they are held captive at his will.

2 Timothy 3

1 And know this: that in the last days perilous times will press near.

2 Men will be lovers of themselves, greedy, self-exalting, arrogant, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, ungrateful, wicked,

3 without affection, without peace, false accusers, unchaste, cruel, without kindness,

4 traitorous, reckless, self-important, loving pleasure more than God,

5 even having the appearance of piety while rejecting its virtue. And so, avoid them.

6 For among these are ones who penetrate houses and lead away, like captives, foolish women burdened with sins, who are led away by means of various desires,

7 always learning, yet never achieving knowledge of the truth.

8 And in the same manner that Jannes and Jambres resisted Moses, so also will these resist the truth, men corrupted in mind, reprobates from the faith.

9 But they will not advance beyond a certain point. For the folly of the latter shall be made manifest to all, just as that of the former.

10 But you have fully comprehended my doctrine, instruction, purpose, faith, longsuffering, love, patience,

11 persecutions, afflictions; such things as happened to me at Antioch, at Iconium, and at Lystra; how I endured persecutions, and how the Lord rescued me from everything.

12 And all those who willingly live the piety in Christ Jesus will suffer persecution.

13 But evil men and deceivers will advance in evil, erring and sending into error.

14 Yet truly, you should remain in those things which you have learned and which have been entrusted to you. For you know from whom you have learned them.

15 And, from your infancy, you have known the Sacred Scriptures, which are able to instruct you toward salvation, through the faith which is in Christ Jesus.

16 All Scripture, having been divinely inspired, is useful for teaching, for reproof, for correction, and for instruction in justice,

17 so that the man of God may be perfect, having been trained for every good work.

2 Timothy 4

1 I testify before God, and before Jesus Christ, who shall judge the living and the dead through his return and his kingdom:

2 that you should preach the word urgently, in season and out of season: reprove, entreat, rebuke, with all patience and doctrine.

3 For there shall be a time when they will not endure sound doctrine, but instead, according to their own desires, they will gather to themselves teachers, with itching ears,

4 and certainly, they will turn their hearing away from the truth, and they will be turned toward fables.

5 But as for you, truly, be vigilant, laboring in all things. Do the work of an Evangelist, fulfilling your ministry. Show self-restraint.

6 For I am already being worn away, and the time of my dissolution presses close.

7 I have fought the good fight. I have completed the course. I have preserved the faith.

8 As for the remainder, a crown of justice has been reserved for me, one which the Lord, the just judge, will render to me in that day, and not only to me, but also to those who look forward to his return. Hurry to return to me soon.

9 For Demas has abandoned me, out of love for this age, and he has departed for Thessalonica.

10 Crescens has gone to Galatia; Titus to Dalmatia.

11 Luke alone is with me. Take Mark and bring him with you; for he is useful to me in the ministry.

12 But Tychicus I have sent to Ephesus.

13 When you return, bring with you the supplies that I left with Carpus at Troas, and the books, but especially the parchments.

14 Alexander the coppersmith has shown me much evil; the Lord will repay him according to his works.

15 And you should also avoid him; for he has strongly resisted our words.

16 At my first defense, no one stood by me, but everyone abandoned me. May it not be counted against them!

17 But the Lord stood with me and strengthened me, so that through me the preaching would be accomplished, and so that all the Gentiles would hear. And I was freed from the mouth of the lion.

18 The Lord has freed me from every evil work, and he will accomplish salvation by his heavenly kingdom. To him be glory forever and ever. Amen.

19 Greet Prisca, and Aquila, and the household of Onesiphorus.

20 Erastus remained at Corinth. And Trophimus I left sick at Miletus.

21 Hurry to arrive before winter. Eubulus, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brothers greet you.

22 May the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. May grace be with you. Amen.

Titus 1

1 Paul, a servant of God and an Apostle of Jesus Christ, in accord with the faith of God's elect and in acknowledgment of the truth which is accompanied by piety,

2 in the hope of the eternal life that God, who does not lie, promised before the ages of time,

3 which, at the proper time, he has manifested by his Word, in the preaching that has been entrusted to me by the command of God our Savior;

4 to Titus, beloved son according to the common faith. Grace and peace, from God the Father and from Christ Jesus our Savior.

5 For this reason, I left you behind in Crete: so that those things which are lacking, you would correct, and so that you would ordain, throughout the communities, priests, (just as I also ordained you)

6 if such a man is without offense, the husband of one wife, having faithful children, not accused of self-indulgence, nor of insubordination.

7 And a bishop, as a steward of God, must be without offense: not arrogant, not short-tempered, not a drunkard, not violent, not desiring tainted profit,

8 but instead: hospitable, kind, sober, just, holy, chaste,

9 embracing faithful speech which is in agreement with doctrine, so that he may be able to exhort in sound doctrine and to argue against those who contradict.

10 For there are, indeed, many who are disobedient, who speak empty words, and who deceive, especially those who are of the circumcision.

11 These must be reproved, for they subvert entire houses, teaching things which should not be taught, for the favor of shameful gain.

12 A certain one of these, a prophet of their own kind, said: "The Cretans are ever liars, evil beasts, lazy gluttons."

13 This testimony is true. Because of this, rebuke them sharply, so that they may be sound in the faith,

14 not paying attention to Jewish fables, nor to the rules of men who have turned themselves away from the truth.

15 All things are clean to those who are clean. But to those who are defiled, and to unbelievers, nothing is clean; for both their mind and their conscience have been polluted.

16 They claim that they know God. But, by their own works, they deny him, since they are abominable, and unbelieving, and reprobate, toward every good work.

Titus 2

1 But you are to speak the things that befit sound doctrine.

2 Old men should be sober, chaste, prudent, sound in faith, in love, in patience.

3 Old women, similarly, should be in holy attire, not false accusers, not given to much wine, teaching well,

4 so that they may teach prudence to the young women, so that they may love their husbands, love their children,

5 be sensible, chaste, restrained, have concern for the household, be kind, be subordinate to their husbands: so that the Word of God may be not blasphemed.

6 Exhort young men similarly, so that they may show self-restraint.

7 In all things, present yourself as an example of good works: in doctrine, with integrity, with seriousness,

8 with sound words, irreproachably, so that he who is an opponent may dread that he has nothing evil to say about us.

9 Exhort servants to be submissive to their masters, in all things pleasing, not contradicting,

10 not cheating, but in all things showing good fidelity, so that they may adorn the doctrine of God our Savior in all things.

11 For the grace of God our Savior has appeared to all men,

12 instructing us to reject impiety and worldly desires, so that we may live soberly and justly and piously in this age,

13 looking forward to the blessed hope and the advent of the glory of the great God and of our Savior Jesus Christ.

14 He gave himself for our sake, so that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and might cleanse for himself an acceptable people, pursuers of good works.

15 Speak and exhort and argue these things with all authority. Let no one despise you.

Titus 3

1 Admonish them to be subordinate to the rulers and authorities, to obey their dictates, to be prepared for every good work,

2 to speak evil of no one, not to be litigious, but to be reserved, displaying all meekness toward all men.

3 For, in times past, we ourselves were also unwise, unbelieving, erring, servants of various desires and pleasures, acting with malice and envy, being hateful and hating one another.

4 But then the kindness and humanity of God our Savior appeared.

5 And he saved us, not by works of justice that we had done, but, in accord with his mercy, by the washing of regeneration and by the renovation of the Holy Spirit,

6 whom he has poured out upon us in abundance, through Jesus Christ our Savior,

7 so that, having been justified by his grace, we may become heirs according to the hope of eternal life.

8 This is a faithful saying. And I want you to confirm these things, so that those who believe in God may take care to excel in good works. These things are good and useful to men.

9 But avoid foolish questions, and genealogies, and contentions, as well as arguments against the law. For these are useless and empty.

10 Avoid a man who is a heretic, after the first and second correction,

11 knowing that one who is like this has been subverted, and that he offends; for he has been condemned by his own judgment.

12 When I send Artemas or Tychicus to you, hurry to return to me at Nicopolis. For I have decided to winter there.

13 Send Zenas the lawyer and Apollo ahead with care, and let nothing be lacking to them.

14 But let our men also learn to excel in good works pertaining to the necessities of life, so that they may not be unfruitful.

15 All those who are with me greet you. Greet those who love us in the faith. May the grace of God be with you all. Amen.

Philemon 1

1 Paul, a prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timothy, a brother, to Philemon, our beloved fellow laborer,

2 and to Apphia, most beloved sister, and to Archippus, our fellow soldier, and to the church which is in your house.

3 Grace and peace to you, from God our Father and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

4 I give thanks to my God, always keeping remembrance of you in my prayers,

5 (for I am hearing of your charity and faith, which you have in the Lord Jesus and with all the saints)

6 so that the participation of your faith may become evident by the recognition of every good work which is in you in Christ Jesus.

7 For I have found great joy and consolation in your charity, because the hearts of the saints have been refreshed by you, brother.

8 Because of this, I have enough confidence in Christ Jesus to command you concerning certain things,

9 but I beg you instead, for the sake of charity, since you are so much like Paul: an old man and now also a prisoner of Jesus Christ.

10 I beg you, on behalf of my son, whom I have begotten in my chains, Onesimus.

11 In times past, he was useless to you, but now he is useful both to me and to you.

12 So I have sent him back to you. And may you receive him like my own heart.

13 I myself wanted to retain him with me, so that he might minister to me, on your behalf, while I am in the chains of the Gospel.

14 But I was willing to do nothing without your counsel, so as not to make use of your good deed as if out of necessity, but only willingly.

15 So perhaps, then, he departed from you for a time, so that you might receive him again for eternity,

16 no longer as a servant, but, in place of a servant, a most beloved brother, especially to me: but how much so more to you, both in the flesh and in the Lord!

17 Therefore, if you hold me to be a companion, receive him as you would me.

18 But if he has harmed you in any way, or if he is in your debt, charge it to me.

19 I, Paul, have written this with my own hand: I will repay. And I need not tell you, that you are also in debt yourself, to me.

20 So it is, brother. May I delight with you in the Lord! Refresh my heart in Christ.

21 I have written to you, trusting in your obedience, knowing, too, that you will do even more than what I say.

22 But also, at once, prepare a lodging for me. For I am hoping, through your prayers, to present myself to you.

23 Greet Epaphras, my fellow captive in Christ Jesus,

24 and Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, and Luke, my helpers.

25 May the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.

Hebrews 1

1 In many places and in many ways, in past times, God spoke to the fathers through the Prophets;

2 lastly, in these days, he has spoken to us through the Son, whom he appointed as the heir of all things, and through whom he made the world.

3 And since the Son is the brightness of his glory, and the figure of his substance, and is carrying all things by the Word of his virtue, thereby accomplishing a purging of sins, he sits at the right hand of Majesty on high.

4 And having been made so much better than the Angels, he has inherited a name so much greater than theirs.

5 For to which of the Angels has he ever said: "You are my Son; today have I begotten you?" Or again: "I will be a Father to him, and he shall be a Son to me?"

6 And again, when he brings the only-begotten Son into the world, he says: "And let all the Angels of God adore him."

7 And about the Angels, certainly, he says: "He makes his Angels spirits, and his ministers a flame of fire."

8 But about the Son: "Your throne, O God, is forever and ever. The scepter of your kingdom is a scepter of equity.

9 You have loved justice, and you have hated iniquity. Because of this, God, your God, has anointed you with the oil of exultation, above your companions."

10 And: "In the beginning, O Lord, you founded the earth. And the heavens are the work of your hands.

11 These shall pass away, but you will remain. And all will grow old like a garment.

12 And you will change them like a cloak, and they shall be changed. Yet you are ever the same, and your years will not diminish."

13 But to which of the Angels has he ever said: "Sit at my right hand, until I make your enemies your footstool?"

14 Are they not all spirits of ministration, sent to minister for the sake of those who shall receive the inheritance of salvation?

Hebrews 2

1 For this reason, it is necessary for us to observe more thoroughly the things that we have heard, lest we let them slip away.

2 For if a word that was spoken through the Angels has been made firm, and every transgression and disobedience has received the recompense of a just retribution,

3 in what way might we escape, if we neglect such a great salvation? For though initially it had begun to be described by the Lord, it was confirmed among us by those who heard him,

4 with God testifying to it by signs and wonders, and by various miracles, and by the pouring out of the Holy Spirit, in accord with his own will.

5 For God did not subject the future world, about which we are speaking, to the Angels.

6 But someone, in a certain place, has testified, saying: "What is man, that you are mindful of him, or the Son of man, that you visit him?

7 You have reduced him to a little less than the Angels. You have crowned him with glory and honor, and you have set him over the works of your hands.

8 You have subjected all things under his feet." For in as much as he has subjected all things to him, he has left nothing not subject to him. But in the present time, we do not yet perceive that all things have been made subject to him.

9 Yet we understand that Jesus, who was reduced to a little less than the Angels, was crowned with glory and honor because of his Passion and death, in order that, by the grace of God, he might taste death for all.

10 For it was fitting for him, because of whom and through whom all things exist, who had led many children into glory, to complete the authorship of their salvation through his Passion.

11 For he who sanctifies, and those who are sanctified, are all from One. For this reason, he is not ashamed to call them brothers, saying:

12 "I will announce your name to my brothers. In the midst of the Church, I will praise you."

13 And again: "I will be faithful in him." And again: "Behold, I and my children, whom God has given to me."

14 Therefore, because children have a common flesh and blood, he himself also, in like manner, has shared in the same, so that through death, he might destroy him who held the dominion of death, that is, the devil,

15 and so that he might free those who, through the fear of death, had been condemned to servitude throughout their entire life.

16 For at no time did he take hold of the Angels, but instead he took hold of the offspring of Abraham.

17 Therefore, it is fitting for him to be made similar to his brothers in all things, so that he might become a merciful and faithful High Priest before God, in order that he might bring forgiveness to the offenses of the people.

18 For in as much as he himself has suffered and has been tempted, he also is able to assist those who are tempted.

Hebrews 3

1 Therefore, holy brothers, sharers in the heavenly calling, consider the Apostle and High Priest of our confession: Jesus.

2 He is faithful to the One who made him, just as Moses also was, with his entire house.

3 For this Jesus was considered worthy of greater glory than Moses, so much so that the house which he has built holds a greater honor than the former one.

4 For every house is built by someone, but God is the One who has created all things.

5 And certainly Moses was faithful, with his entire house, like any servant, as a testimony to those things that would soon be said.

6 Yet truly, Christ is like a Son in his own house. We are that house, if we firmly retain the faithfulness and the glory of hope, even unto the end.

7 Because of this, it is just as the Holy Spirit says: "If today you hear his voice,

8 harden not your hearts, as in the provocation, the very day of temptation, in the desert,

9 where your fathers tested me, even though they had seen and examined my works for forty years.

10 For this reason, I was enraged against this generation, and I said: They always wander astray in heart. For they have not known my ways.

11 So it is as I swore in my wrath: They shall not enter into my rest!"

12 Be cautious, brothers, lest perhaps there may be, in any of you, an evil heart of unbelief, turning aside from the living God.

13 Instead, exhort one another every day, while it is still called 'today,' so that none of you may become hardened through the falseness of sin.

14 For we have been made participants in Christ. This is only so, if we firmly retain the beginning of his substance, even unto the end.

15 For it has been said: "If today you hear his voice, harden not your hearts, in the same manner as in the former provocation."

16 For some of those listening did provoke him. But not all of these had set forth from Egypt through Moses.

17 So against whom was he angry for forty years? Was it not those who had sinned, whose dead bodies lay prostrate in the desert?

18 But to whom did he swear that they would not enter into his rest, except to those who were incredulous?

19 And so, we perceive that they were not able to enter because of unbelief.

Hebrews 4

1 Therefore, we should be afraid, lest the promise of entering into his rest may be relinquished, and some of you may be judged to be lacking.

2 For this was announced to us in a similar manner as to them. But the mere hearing of the word did not benefit them, since it was not joined together with a faith in those things that they heard.

3 For we who have believed shall enter into rest, in the same manner as he said: "So it is as I have sworn in my wrath: They shall not enter into my rest!" And certainly, this is when the works from the foundation of the world have been finished.

4 For, in a certain place, he spoke about the seventh day in this manner: "And God rested on the seventh day from all his works."

5 And in this place again: "They shall not enter into my rest!"

6 Therefore, this is because certain ones remain who are to enter into it, and those to whom it was announced first did not enter into it, because of unbelief.

7 Again, he defines a certain day, after so much time, saying in David, "Today," just as it was stated above, "If today you hear his voice, harden not your hearts."

8 For if Jesus had offered them rest, he would never have spoken, afterward, about another day.

9 And so, there remains a Sabbath of rest for the people of God.

10 For whoever has entered into his rest, the same has also rested from his works, just as God did from his.

11 Therefore, let us hasten to enter into that rest, so that no one may fall into the same example of unbelief.

12 For the Word of God is living and effective: more piercing than any two-edged sword, reaching to the division even between the soul and the spirit, even between the joints and the marrow, and so it discerns the thoughts and intentions of the heart.

13 And there is no created thing that is invisible to his sight. For all things are naked and open to the eyes of him, about whom we are speaking.

14 Therefore, since we have a great High Priest, who has pierced the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, we should hold to our confession.

15 For we do not have a high priest who is unable to have compassion on our infirmities, but rather one who was tempted in all things, just as we are, yet without sin.

16 Therefore, let us go forth with confidence toward the throne of grace, so that we may obtain mercy, and find grace, in a helpful time.

Hebrews 5

1 For every high priest, having been taken from among men, is appointed on behalf of men toward the things which pertain to God, so that he may offer gifts and sacrifices on behalf of sins;

2 he is able to commiserate with those who are ignorant and who wander astray, because he himself is also encompassed by infirmity.

3 And because of this, he also must make such offerings for sins even for himself, in the same manner as for the people.

4 Neither does anyone take up this honor himself, but rather he who is called by God, just as Aaron was.

5 Thus, even Christ did not glorify himself, so as to become High Priest, but instead, it was God who said to him: "You are my Son. Today I have begotten you."

6 And similarly, he says in another place: "You are a priest forever, according to the order of Melchizedek."

7 It is Christ who, in the days of his flesh, with a strong cry and tears, offered prayers and supplications to the One who was able to save him from death, and who was heard because of his reverence.

8 And although, certainly, he is the Son of God, he learned obedience by the things that he suffered.

9 And having reached his consummation, he was made, for all who are obedient to him, the cause of eternal salvation,

10 having been called by God to be the High Priest, according to the order of Melchizedek.

11 Our message about him is great, and difficult to explain when speaking, because you have been made feeble when listening.

12 For even though it is the time when you ought to be teachers, you are still lacking, so that you must be taught the things that are the basic elements of the Word of God, and so you have been made like those who are in need of milk, and not of solid food.

13 For anyone who is still feeding on milk is still unskillful in the Word of Justice; for he is like an infant.

14 But solid food is for those who are mature, for those who, by practice, have sharpened their mind, so as to discern good from evil.

Hebrews 6

1 Therefore, interrupting an explanation of the basics of Christ, let us consider what is more advanced, not presenting again the fundamentals of repentance from dead works, and of faith toward God,

2 of the doctrine of baptism, and also of the imposition of hands, and of the resurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment.

3 And we shall do this, if indeed God permits it.

4 For it is impossible for those who were once illuminated, and have even tasted of the heavenly gift, and have become sharers in the Holy Spirit,

5 who, despite having tasted the good Word of God and the virtues of the future age, have yet fallen away,

6 to be renewed again to penance, since they are crucifying again in themselves the Son of God and are still maintaining pretenses.

7 For the earth accepts a blessing from God, by drinking in the rain that often falls upon it, and by producing plants that are useful to those by whom it is cultivated.

8 But whatever brings forth thorns and briers is rejected, and is closest to what is accursed; their consummation is in combustion.

9 But from you, most beloved, we are confident that there will be things better and closer to salvation; even though we speak in this way.

10 For God is not unjust, such that he would forget your work and the love that you have shown in his name. For you have ministered, and you continue to minister, to the saints.

11 Yet we desire that each one of you display the same solicitude toward the fulfillment of hope, even unto the end,

12 so that you may not be slow to act, but instead may be imitators of those who, through faith and patience, shall inherit the promises.

13 For God, in making promises to Abraham, swore by himself, (because he had no one greater by whom he might swear),

14 saying: "Blessing, I shall bless you, and multiplying, I shall multiply you."

15 And in this way, by enduring patiently, he secured the promise.

16 For men swear by what is greater than themselves, and an oath as confirmation is the end of all their controversy.

17 In this matter, God, wanting to reveal more thoroughly the immutability of his counsel to the heirs of the promise, interposed an oath,

18 so that by two immutable things, in which it is impossible for God to lie, we may have the strongest solace: we who have fled together so as to hold fast to the hope set before us.

19 This we have as an anchor of the soul, safe and sound, which advances even to the interior of the veil,

20 to the place where the forerunner Jesus has entered on our behalf, so as to become the High Priest for eternity, according to the order of Melchizedek.

Hebrews 7

1 For this Melchizedek, king of Salem, priest of the Most High God, met Abraham, as he was returning from the slaughter of the kings, and blessed him.

2 And Abraham divided to him a tenth part of everything. And in translation his name is first, indeed, king of justice, and next also king of Salem, that is, king of peace.

3 Without father, without mother, without genealogy, having neither beginning of days, nor end of life, he is thereby likened to the Son of God, who remains a priest continuously.

4 Next, consider how great this man is, since the Patriarch Abraham even gave tithes to him from the principal things.

5 And indeed, those who are from the sons of Levi, having received the priesthood, hold a commandment to take tithes from the people in accord with the law, that is, from their brothers, even though they also went forth from the loins of Abraham.

6 But this man, whose lineage is not enumerated with them, received tithes from Abraham, and he blessed even the one who held the promises.

7 Yet this is without any contradiction, for what is less should be blessed by what is better.

8 And certainly, here, men who receive tithes still die; but there, he bears witness that he lives.

9 And so it may be said that even Levi, who received tithes, was himself a tithe through Abraham.

10 For he was still in the loins of his father, when Melchizedek met him.

11 Therefore, if consummation had occurred through the Levitical priesthood (for under it the people received the law), then what further need would there be for another Priest to rise up according to the order of Melchizedek, one who was not called according to the order of Aaron?

12 For since the priesthood has been transferred, it is necessary that the law also be transferred.

13 For he about whom these things have been spoken is from another tribe, in which no one attends before the altar.

14 For it is evident that our Lord arose out of Judah, a tribe about which Moses said nothing concerning priests.

15 And yet it is far more evident that, according to the likeness of Melchizedek, there rises up another priest,

16 who was made, not according to the law of a carnal commandment, but according to the virtue of an indissoluble life.

17 For he testifies: "You are a priest forever, according to the order of Melchizedek."

18 Certainly, there is a setting aside of the former commandment, because of its weakness and lack of usefulness.

19 For the law led no one to perfection, yet truly it introduced a better hope, through which we draw near to God.

20 Moreover, it is not without an oath. For certainly, the others were made priests without an oath.

21 But this man was made a priest with an oath, by the One who said to him: "The Lord has sworn and he will not repent. You are a priest forever."

22 By so much, Jesus has been made the sponsor of a better testament.

23 And certainly, so many of the others became priests because, due to death, they were prohibited from continuing.

24 But this man, because he continues forever, has an everlasting priesthood.

25 And for this reason, he is able, continuously, to save those who approach God through him, since he is ever alive to make intercession on our behalf.

26 For it was fitting that we should have such a High Priest: holy, innocent, undefiled, set apart from sinners, and exalted higher than the heavens.

27 And he has no need, daily, in the manner of other priests, to offer sacrifices, first for his own sins, and then for those of the people. For he has done this once, by offering himself.

28 For the law appoints men as priests, though they have infirmities. But, by the word of the oath that is after the law, the Son has been perfected for eternity.

Hebrews 8

1 Now the main point in the things that have been stated is this: that we have so great a High Priest, who is seated at the right hand of the throne of Majesty in the heavens,

2 who is the minister of holy things, and of the true tabernacle, which was established by the Lord, not by man.

3 For every high priest is appointed to offer gifts and sacrifices. Therefore, it is necessary for him also to have something to offer.

4 And so, if he were upon the earth, he would not be a priest, since there would be others to offer gifts according to the law,

5 gifts which serve as mere examples and shadows of the heavenly things. And so it was answered to Moses, when he was about to complete the tabernacle: "See to it," he said, "that you make everything according to the example which was revealed to you on the mountain."

6 But now he has been granted a better ministry, so much so that he is also the Mediator of a better testament, which has been confirmed by better promises.

7 For if the former one had been entirely without fault, then a place certainly would not have been sought for a subsequent one.

8 For, finding fault with them, he says: "Behold, the days shall arrive, says the Lord, when I will consummate a New Testament over the house of Israel and the house of Judah,

9 not according to the testament which I made with their fathers, on the day when I took them by the hand, so that I might lead them away from the land of Egypt. For they did not remain in my testament, and so I disregarded them, says the Lord.

10 For this is the testament which I will set before the house of Israel, after those days, says the Lord. I will instill my laws in their minds, and I will inscribe my laws on their hearts. And so, I will be their God, and they shall be my people.

11 And they will not teach, each one his neighbor, and each one his brother, saying: 'Know the Lord.' For all shall know me, from the least, even to the greatest of them.

12 For I will forgive their iniquities, and I will no longer remember their sins."

13 Now in saying something new, he has made the former old. But that which decays and grows old is close to passing away.

Hebrews 9

1 Certainly, the former also had the justifications of worship and a holy place for that age.

2 For a tabernacle was made at first, in which were the lampstand, and the table, and the bread of the Presence, which is called Holy.

3 Then, beyond the second veil, was the tabernacle, which is called the Holy of Holies,

4 having a golden censer, and the ark of the testament, covered all around and on every part with gold, in which was a golden urn containing manna, and the rod of Aaron which had blossomed, and the tablets of the testament.

5 And over the ark were the Cherubim of glory, overshadowing the propitiatory. There is not enough time to speak about each of these things.

6 Yet truly, once such things were placed together, in the first part of the tabernacle, the priests were, indeed, continually entering, so as to carry out the duties of the sacrifices.

7 But into the second part, once a year, the high priest alone entered, not without blood, which he offered on behalf of the neglectful offenses of himself and of the people.

8 In this way, the Holy Spirit is signifying that the way to what is most holy was not yet made manifest, not while the first tabernacle was still standing.

9 And this is a parable for the present time. Accordingly, those gifts and sacrifices that are offered are not able, as concerns the conscience, to make perfect those things that serve only as food and drink,

10 as well as the various washings and justices of the flesh, which were imposed upon them until the time of correction.

11 But Christ, standing as the High Priest of future good things, through a greater and more perfect tabernacle, one not made by hand, that is, not of this creation,

12 entered once into the Holy of Holies, having obtained eternal redemption, neither by the blood of goats, nor of calves, but by his own blood.

13 For if the blood of goats and oxen, and the ashes of a calf, when these are sprinkled, sanctify those who have been defiled, in order to cleanse the flesh,

14 how much more will the blood of Christ, who through the Holy Spirit has offered himself, immaculate, to God, cleanse our conscience from dead works, in order to serve the living God?

15 And thus he is the Mediator of the new testament, so that, by his death, he intercedes for the redemption of those transgressions which were under the former testament, so that those who have been called may receive the promise of an eternal inheritance.

16 For where there is a testament, it is necessary for the death of the one who testifies to intervene.

17 For a testament is confirmed by death. Otherwise, it as yet has no force, as long as the one who testifies lives.

18 Therefore, indeed, the first was not dedicated without blood.

19 For when every commandment of the law had been read by Moses to the entire people, he took up the blood of calves and goats, with water and with scarlet wool and hyssop, and he sprinkled both the book itself and the entire people,

20 saying: "This is the blood of the testament which God has commanded for you."

21 And even the tabernacle, and all the vessels for the ministry, he similarly sprinkled with blood.

22 And nearly everything, according to the law, is to be cleansed with blood. And without the shedding of blood, there is no remission.

23 Therefore, it is necessary for the examples of heavenly things to be cleansed, just as, indeed, these things were. Yet the heavenly things are themselves better sacrifices than these.

24 For Jesus did not enter by means of holy things made with hands, mere examples of the true things, but he entered into Heaven itself, so that he may appear now before the face of God for us.

25 And he did not enter so as to offer himself repeatedly, as the high priest enters into the Holy of Holies each year, with the blood of another.

26 Otherwise, he would need to have suffered repeatedly since the beginning of the world. But now, one time, at the consummation of the ages, he has appeared in order to destroy sin though his own sacrifice.

27 And in the same manner as it has been appointed for men to die one time, and after this, to be judged,

28 so also Christ was offered, one time, in order to empty the sins of so many. He shall appear a second time without sin, for those who await him, unto salvation.

Hebrews 10

1 For the law contains the shadow of future good things, not the very image of these things. So, by the very same sacrifices which they offer ceaselessly each year, they can never cause these to approach perfection.

2 Otherwise, they would have ceased to be offered, because the worshipers, once cleansed, would no longer be conscious of any sin.

3 Instead, in these things, a commemoration of sins is made every year.

4 For it is impossible for sins to be taken away by the blood of oxen and goats.

5 For this reason, as Christ enters into the world, he says: "Sacrifice and oblation, you did not want. But you have fashioned a body for me.

6 Holocausts for sin were not pleasing to you.

7 Then I said, 'Behold, I draw near.' At the head of the book, it has been written of me that I should do your will, O God."

8 In the above, by saying, "Sacrifices, and oblations, and holocausts for sin, you did not want, nor are those things pleasing to you, which are offered according to the law;

9 then I said, 'Behold, I have come to do your will, O God,' " he takes away the first, so that he may establish what follows.

10 For by this will, we have been sanctified, through the one time oblation of the body of Jesus Christ.

11 And certainly, every priest stands by, ministering daily, and frequently offering the same sacrifices, which are never able to take away sins.

12 But this man, offering one sacrifice for sins, sits at the right hand of God forever,

13 awaiting that time when his enemies will be made his footstool.

14 For, by one oblation, he has brought to fulfillment, for all time, those who are sanctified.

15 Now the Holy Spirit also testifies for us about this. For afterward, he said:

16 "And this is the testament which I will commit to them after those days, says the Lord. I will instill my laws in their hearts, and I will inscribe my laws on their minds.

17 And I will no longer remember their sins and iniquities."

18 Now, when there is a remission of these things, there is no longer an oblation for sin.

19 And so, brothers, have faith in the entrance into the Holy of Holies by the blood of Christ,

20 and in the new and living Way, which he has initiated for us by the veil, that is, by his flesh,

21 and in the Great Priest over the house of God.

22 So, let us draw near with a true heart, in the fullness of faith, having hearts cleansed from an evil conscience, and bodies absolved with clean water.

23 Let us hold fast to the confession of our hope, without wavering, for he who has promised is faithful.

24 And let us be considerate of one another, so as to prompt ourselves to charity and to good works,

25 not deserting our assembly, as some are accustomed to do, but consoling one another, and even more so as you see that the day is approaching.

26 For if we sin willingly, after receiving knowledge of the truth, there is no sacrifice remaining for sins,

27 but instead, a certain terrible expectation of judgment, and the rage of a fire that shall consume its adversaries.

28 If someone dies for acting against the law of Moses, and is shown no compassion because of two or three witnesses,

29 how much more, do you think, someone would deserve worse punishments, if he has tread upon the Son of God, and has treated the blood of the testament, by which he was sanctified, as unclean, and has acted with disgrace toward the Spirit of grace?

30 For we know that he has said: "Vengeance is mine, and I will repay," and again, "The Lord will judge his people."

31 It is dreadful to fall into the hands of the living God.

32 But call to mind the former days, in which, after being enlightened, you endured a great struggle of afflictions.

33 And certainly, in one way, by insults and tribulations, you were made a spectacle, but in another way, you became the companions of those who were the object of such behavior.

34 For you even had compassion on those who were imprisoned, and you accepted with gladness being deprived of your goods, knowing that you have a better and more lasting substance.

35 And so, do not lose your confidence, which has a great reward.

36 For it is necessary for you to be patient, so that, by doing the will of God, you may receive the promise.

37 "For, in a little while, and somewhat longer, he who is to come will return, and he will not delay.

38 For my just man lives by faith. But if he were to draw himself back, he would not please my soul."

39 So then, we are not sons who are drawn away to perdition, but we are sons of faith toward the securing of the soul.

Hebrews 11

1 Now, faith is the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not apparent.

2 For this reason, the ancients were given testimony.

3 By faith, we understand the world to be fashioned by the Word of God, so that the visible might be made by the invisible.

4 By faith, Abel offered to God a much better sacrifice than that of Cain, through which he obtained testimony that he was just, in that God offered testimony to his gifts. And through that sacrifice, he still speaks to us, though he is dead.

5 By faith, Enoch was transferred, so that he would not see death, and he was not found because God had transferred him. For before he was transferred, he had testimony that he pleased God.

6 But without faith, it is impossible to please God. For whoever approaches God must believe that he exists, and that he rewards those who seek him.

7 By faith, Noah, having accepted an answer about those things which were not yet seen, being afraid, fashioned an ark for the salvation of his house. Through the ark, he condemned the world, and was established as the heir of the justice that occurs through faith.

8 By faith, the one called Abraham obeyed, going out to the place that he was to receive as an inheritance. And he went out, not knowing where he was going.

9 By faith, he stayed in the Land of the Promise as if in a foreign land, dwelling in cottages, with Isaac and Jacob, co-heirs of the same promise.

10 For he was awaiting a city having firm foundations, whose designer and builder is God.

11 By faith also, Sarah herself, being barren, received the ability to conceive offspring, even though she was past that age in life. For she believed him to be faithful, who had promised.

12 Because of this, there were also born, from one who himself was as if dead, a mulititude like the stars of heaven, who are, like the sand of the seashore, innumerable.

13 All of these passed away, adhering to faith, not having received the promises, yet beholding them from afar and saluting them, and confessing themselves to be sojourners and guests upon the earth.

14 For those who speak in this way are themselves indicating that they seek a homeland.

15 And if, indeed, they had been mindful of the very place from which they departed, they certainly would have returned in time.

16 But now they hunger for a better place, that is, Heaven. For this reason, God is not ashamed to be called their God. For he has prepared a city for them.

17 By faith, Abraham, when he was tested, offered Isaac, so that he who had received the promises was offering up his only son.

18 To him, it was said, "Through Isaac, shall your offspring be summoned,"

19 indicating that God is even able to raise up from the dead. And thus, he also established him as a parable.

20 By faith, also, Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau, concerning future events.

21 By faith, Jacob, as he was dying, blessed each of the sons of Joseph; and he reverenced the summit of his rod.

22 By faith, Joseph, as he was dying, recalled the departure of the sons of Israel, and gave a commandment concerning his bones.

23 By faith, Moses, after being born, was hidden for three months by his parents, because they had seen that he was a graceful infant, and they did not fear the king's edict.

24 By faith, Moses, after growing up, denied himself a place as the son of Pharaoh's daughter,

25 choosing to be afflicted with the people of God, rather than to have the pleasantness of sin for a time,

26 valuing the reproach of Christ to be a greater wealth than the treasures of the Egyptians. For he looked forward to his reward.

27 By faith, he abandoned Egypt, not dreading the animosity of the king. For he pressed on, as if seeing him who is unseen.

28 By faith, he celebrated the Passover and the shedding of the blood, so that he who destroyed the firstborn might not touch them.

29 By faith, they crossed the Red Sea, as if on dry land, yet when the Egyptians attempted it, they were swallowed up.

30 By faith, the walls of Jericho collapsed, after being encircled for seven days.

31 By faith, Rahab, the harlot, did not perish with the unbelievers, after receiving the spies with peace.

32 And what should I say next? For time is not sufficient for me to give an account of Gideon, Barak, Samson, Jephthah, David, Samuel, and the Prophets:

33 those who, by faith, conquered kingdoms, accomplished justice, obtained promises, closed the mouths of lions,

34 extinguished the violence of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, recovered from infirmities, showed strength in battle, turned back the armies of foreigners.

35 Women received their dead by means of resurrection. But others suffered severe punishment, not yet receiving redemption, so that they would find a better resurrection.

36 Truly, others were tested by mocking and lashes, and moreover by chains and imprisonment.

37 They were stoned; they were cut; they were tempted. With the slaughter of the sword, they were killed. They wandered about in sheepskin and in goatskin, in dire need, in anguish afflicted.

38 Of them, the world was not worthy, wandering in solitude on mountains, in the caves and caverns of the earth.

39 And all these, having been proven by the testimony of faith, did not receive the Promise.

40 God's Providence holds something better for us, so that not without us would they be perfected.

Hebrews 12

1 Furthermore, since we also have so great a cloud of witnesses over us, let us set aside every burden and sin which may surround us, and advance, through patience, to the struggle offered to us.

2 Let us gaze upon Jesus, as the Author and the completion of our faith, who, having joy laid out before him, endured the cross, disregarding the shame, and who now sits at the right hand of the throne of God.

3 So then, meditate upon him who endured such adversity from sinners against himself, so that you may not become weary, failing in your souls.

4 For you have not yet resisted unto blood, while striving against sin.

5 And you have forgotten the consolation which speaks to you like sons, saying: "My son, do not be willing to neglect the discipline of the Lord. Neither should you become weary, while being rebuked by him."

6 For whomever the Lord loves, he chastises. And every son whom he accepts, he scourges.

7 Persevere in discipline. God presents you to himself as sons. But what son is there, whom his father does not correct?

8 But if you are without that discipline in which all have become sharers, then you are of adultery, and you are not sons.

9 Then, too, we have certainly had the fathers of our flesh as instructors, and we reverenced them. Should we not obey the Father of spirits all the more, and so live?

10 And indeed, for a few days and according to their own wishes, they instructed us. But he does so to our benefit, so that we may receive his sanctification.

11 Now every discipline, in the present time, does not seem a gladness, of course, but a grief. But afterwards, it will repay a most peaceful fruit of justice to those who become trained in it.

12 Because of this, lift up your lazy hands and your lax knees,

13 and straighten the path of your feet, so that no one, being lame, may wander astray, but instead may be healed.

14 Pursue peace with everyone. Pursue sanctity, without which no one shall see God.

15 Be contemplative, lest anyone lack the grace of God, lest any root of bitterness spring up and impede you, and by it, many might be defiled,

16 lest any fornicator or worldly person be like Esau, who, for the sake of one meal, sold his birthright.

17 For you know that afterwards, when he desired to inherit the benediction, he was rejected. For he found no place for repentance, even though he had sought it with tears.

18 But you have not drawn near to a tangible mountain, or a burning fire, or a whirlwind, or a mist, or a storm,

19 or the sound of a trumpet, or a voice of words. Those who had experienced these things excused themselves, lest the Word be spoken to them.

20 For they could not bear what was said, and so, if even a beast would have touched the mountain, it would have been stoned.

21 And what was seen was so terrible that even Moses said: "I am terrified, and so, I tremble."

22 But you have drawn near to mount Zion, and to the city of the living God, to the heavenly Jerusalem, and to the company of many thousands of Angels,

23 and to the Church of the first-born, those who have been inscribed in the heavens, and to God, the judge of all, and to the spirits of the just made perfect,

24 and to Jesus, the Mediator of the New Testament, and to a sprinkling of blood, which speaks better than the blood of Abel.

25 Be careful not to reject the One who is speaking. For if those who rejected him who was speaking upon the earth were not able to escape, so much more we who might turn away from the One who is speaking to us from heaven.

26 Then, his voice moved the earth. But now, he makes a promise, saying: "There is still one more time, and then I will move, not only the earth, but also heaven itself."

27 And so, in saying, "There is still one more time," he declares the transfer of the moveable things of creation, so that those things which are immoveable may remain.

28 Thus, in receiving an immoveable kingdom, we have grace. So, through grace, let us be of service, by pleasing God with fear and reverence.

29 For our God is a consuming fire.

Hebrews 13

1 May fraternal charity remain in you.

2 And do not be willing to forget hospitality. For by it, certain persons, without realizing it, have received Angels as guests.

3 Remember those who are prisoners, just as if you were imprisoned with them, and those who endure hardships, just as if you were in their place.

4 May marriage be honorable in every way, and may the marriage bed be immaculate. For God will judge fornicators and adulterers.

5 Let your behavior be without avarice; be content with what you are offered. For he himself has said, "I will not abandon you, and I will not neglect you."

6 So then, we may confidently say, "The Lord is my helper. I will not fear what man can do to me."

7 Remember your leaders, who have spoken the Word of God to you, whose faith you imitate, by observing the goal of their way of life:

8 Jesus Christ, yesterday and today; Jesus Christ forever.

9 Do not be led away by changing or strange doctrines. And it is best for the heart to be sustained by grace, not by foods. For the latter have not been as useful to those who walked by them.

10 We have an altar: those who serve in the tabernacle have no authority to eat from it.

11 For the bodies of those animals whose blood is carried into the Holy of holies by the high priest, on behalf of sin, are burned outside the camp.

12 Because of this, Jesus, too, in order to sanctify the people by his own blood, suffered outside the gate.

13 And so, let us go forth to him, outside the camp, bearing his reproach.

14 For in this place, we have no everlasting city; instead, we seek one in the future.

15 Therefore, through him, let us offer the sacrifice of continual praise to God, which is the fruit of lips confessing his name.

16 But do not be willing to forget good works and fellowship. For God is deserving of such sacrifices.

17 Obey your leaders and be subject to them. For they watch over you, as if to render an account of your souls. So then, may they do this with joy, and not with grief. Otherwise, it would not be as helpful to you.

18 Pray for us. For we trust that we have a good conscience, being willing to conduct ourselves well in all things.

19 And I beg you, all the more, to do this, so that I may be quickly returned to you.

20 Then may the God of peace, who led back from the dead that great Pastor of sheep, our Lord Jesus Christ, with the blood of the eternal testament,

21 equip you with all goodness, so that you may do his will. May he accomplish in you whatever is pleasing in his sight, through Jesus Christ, to whom is glory forever and ever. Amen.

22 And I beg you, brothers, that you may permit this word of consolation, especially since I have written to you with few words.

23 Know that our brother Timothy has been set free. If he arrives soon, then I will see you with him.

24 Greet all your leaders and all the saints. The brothers from Italy greet you.

25 Grace be with you all. Amen.

James 1

1 James, servant of God and of our Lord Jesus Christ, to the twelve tribes of the dispersion, greetings.

2 My brothers, when you have fallen into various trials, consider everything a joy,

3 knowing that the proving of your faith exercises patience,

4 and patience brings a work to perfection, so that you may be perfect and whole, deficient in nothing.

5 But if anyone among you is in need of wisdom, let him petition God, who gives abundantly to all without reproach, and it shall be given to him.

6 But he should ask with faith, doubting nothing. For he who doubts is like a wave on the ocean, which is moved about by the wind and carried away;

7 then a man should not consider that he would receive anything from the Lord.

8 For a man who is of two minds is inconstant in all his ways.

9 Now a humble brother should glory in his exaltation,

10 and a rich one, in his humiliation, for he will pass away like the flower of the grass.

11 For the sun has risen with a scorching heat, and has dried the grass, and its flower has fallen off, and the appearance of its beauty has perished. So also will the rich one wither away, according to his paths.

12 Blessed is the man who suffers temptation. For when he has been proven, he shall receive the crown of life which God has promised to those who love him.

13 No one should say, when he is tempted, that he was tempted by God. For God does not entice toward evils, and he himself tempts no one.

14 Yet truly, each one is tempted by his own desires, having been enticed and drawn away.

15 Thereafter, when desire has conceived, it gives birth to sin. Yet truly sin, when it has been consummated, produces death.

16 And so, do not choose to go astray, my most beloved brothers.

17 Every excellent gift and every perfect gift is from above, descending from the Father of lights, with whom there is no change, nor any shadow of alteration.

18 For by his own will he produced us through the Word of truth, so that we might be a kind of beginning among his creatures.

19 You know this, my most beloved brothers. So let every man be quick to listen, but slow to speak and slow to anger.

20 For the anger of man does not accomplish the justice of God.

21 Because of this, having cast away all uncleanness and an abundance of malice, receive with meekness the newly-grafted Word, which is able to save your souls.

22 So be doers of the Word, and not listeners only, deceiving yourselves.

23 For if anyone is a listener of the Word, but not also a doer, he is comparable to a man gazing into a mirror upon the face that he was born with;

24 and after considering himself, he went away and promptly forgot what he had seen.

25 But he who gazes upon the perfect law of liberty, and who remains in it, is not a forgetful hearer, but instead a doer of the work. He shall be blessed in what he does.

26 But if anyone considers himself to be religious, but he does not restrain his tongue, but instead seduces his own heart: such a one's religion is vanity.

27 This is religion, clean and undefiled before God the Father: to visit orphans and widows in their tribulations, and to keep yourself immaculate, apart from this age.

James 2

1 My brothers, within the glorious faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, do not choose to show favoritism toward persons.

2 For if a man has entered your assembly having a gold ring and splendid apparel, and if a poor man has also entered, in dirty clothing,

3 and if you are then attentive to the one who is clothed in excellent apparel, so that you say to him, "You may sit in this good place," but you say to the poor man, "You stand over there," or, "Sit below my footstool,"

4 are you not judging within yourselves, and have you not become judges with unjust thoughts?

5 My most beloved brothers, listen. Has not God chosen the poor in this world to be rich in faith and heirs of the kingdom that God has promised to those who love him?

6 But you have dishonored the poor. Are not the rich the ones who oppress you through power? And are not they the ones who drag you to judgment?

7 Are not they the ones who blaspheme the good name which has been invoked over you?

8 So if you perfect the regal law, according to the Scriptures, "You shall love your neighbor as yourself," then you do well.

9 But if you show favoritism to persons, then you commit a sin, having been convicted again by the law as transgressors.

10 Now whoever has observed the whole law, yet who offends in one matter, has become guilty of all.

11 For he who said, "You shall not commit adultery," also said, "You shall not kill." So if you do not commit adultery, but you kill, you have become a transgressor of the law.

12 So speak and act just as you are beginning to be judged, by the law of liberty.

13 For judgment is without mercy toward him who has not shown mercy. But mercy exalts itself above judgment.

14 My brothers, what benefit is there if someone claims to have faith, but he does not have works? How would faith be able to save him?

15 So if a brother or sister is naked and daily in need of food,

16 and if anyone of you were to say to them: "Go in peace, keep warm and nourished," and yet not give them the things that are necessary for the body, of what benefit is this?

17 Thus even faith, if it does not have works, is dead, in and of itself.

18 Now someone may say: "You have faith, and I have works." Show me your faith without works! But I will show you my faith by means of works.

19 You believe that there is one God. You do well. But the demons also believe, and they tremble greatly.

20 So then, are you willing to understand, O foolish man, that faith without works is dead?

21 Was not our father Abraham justified by means of works, by offering his son Isaac upon the altar?

22 Do you see that faith was cooperating with his works, and that by means of works faith was brought to fulfillment?

23 And so the Scripture was fulfilled which says: "Abraham believed God, and it was reputed to him unto justice." And so he was called the friend of God.

24 Do you see that a man is justified by means of works, and not by faith alone?

25 Similarly also, Rahab, the harlot, was she not justified by works, by receiving the messengers and sending them out through another way?

26 For just as the body without the spirit is dead, so also faith without works is dead.

James 3

1 My brothers, not many of you should choose to become teachers, knowing that you shall receive a stricter judgment.

2 For we all offend in many ways. If anyone does not offend in word, he is a perfect man. And he is then able, as if with a bridle, to lead the whole body around.

3 For so we put bridles into the mouths of horses, in order to submit them to our will, and so we turn their whole body around.

4 Consider also the ships, which, though they are great and may be driven by strong winds, yet they are turned around with a small rudder, to be directed to wherever the strength of the pilot might will.

5 So also the tongue certainly is a small part, but it moves great things. Consider that a small fire can set ablaze a great forest.

6 And so the tongue is like a fire, comprising all iniquity. The tongue, stationed in the midst of our body, can defile the entire body and inflame the wheel of our nativity, setting a fire from Hell.

7 For the nature of all beasts and birds and serpents and others is ruled over, and has been ruled over, by human nature.

8 But no man is able to rule over the tongue, a restless evil, full of deadly poison.

9 By it we bless God the Father, and by it we speak evil of men, who have been made in the likeness of God.

10 From the same mouth proceeds blessing and cursing. My brothers, these things ought not to be so!

11 Does a fountain emit, out of the same opening, both sweet and bitter water?

12 My brothers, can the fig tree yield grapes? Or the vine, figs? Then neither is salt water able to produce fresh water.

13 Who is wise and well-taught among you? Let him show, by means of good conversation, his work in the meekness of wisdom.

14 But if you hold a bitter zeal, and if there is contention in your hearts, then do not boast and do not be liars against the truth.

15 For this is not wisdom, descending from above, but rather it is earthly, beastly, and diabolical.

16 For wherever envy and contention is, there too is inconstancy and every depraved work.

17 But within the wisdom that is from above, certainly, chastity is first, and next peacefulness, meekness, openness, consenting to what is good, a plenitude of mercy and good fruits, not judging, without falseness.

18 And so the fruit of justice is sown in peace by those who make peace.

James 4

1 Where do wars and contentions among you come from? Is it not from this: from your own desires, which battle within your members?

2 You desire, and you do not have. You envy and you kill, and you are unable to obtain. You argue and you fight, and you do not have, because you do not ask.

3 You ask and you do not receive, because you ask badly, so that you may use it toward your own desires.

4 You adulterers! Do you not know that the friendship of this world is hostile to God? Therefore, whoever has chosen to be a friend of this world has been made into an enemy of God.

5 Or do you think that Scripture says in vain: "The spirit which lives within you desires unto envy?"

6 But he gives a greater grace. Therefore he says: "God resists the arrogant, but he gives grace to the humble."

7 Therefore, be subject to God. But resist the devil, and he will flee from you.

8 Draw near to God, and he will draw near to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners! And purify your hearts, you duplicitous souls!

9 Be afflicted: mourn and weep. Let your laughter be turned into mourning, and your gladness into sorrow.

10 Be humbled in the sight of the Lord, and he will exalt you.

11 Brothers, do not choose to slander one another. Whoever slanders his brother, or whoever judges his brother, slanders the law and judges the law. But if you judge the law, you are not a doer of the law, but a judge.

12 There is one lawgiver and one judge. He is able to destroy, and he is able to set free.

13 But who are you to judge your neighbor? Consider this, you who say, "Today or tomorrow we will go into that city, and certainly we will spend a year there, and we will do business, and we will make our profit,"

14 consider that you do not know what will be tomorrow.

15 For what is your life? It is a mist that appears for a brief time, and afterwards will vanish away. So what you ought to say is: "If the Lord wills," or, "If we live," we will do this or that.

16 But now you exult in your arrogance. All such exultation is wicked.

17 Therefore, he who knows that he ought to do a good thing, and does not do it, for him it is a sin.

James 5

1 Act now, you who are wealthy! Weep and wail in your miseries, which will soon come upon you!

2 Your riches have been corrupted, and your garments have been eaten by moths.

3 Your gold and silver have rusted, and their rust will be a testimony against you, and it will eat away at your flesh like fire. You have stored up wrath for yourselves unto the last days.

4 Consider the pay of the workers who reaped your fields: it has been misappropriated by you; it cries out. And their cry has entered into the ears of the Lord of hosts.

5 You have feasted upon the earth, and you have nourished your hearts with luxuries, unto the day of slaughter.

6 You led away and killed the Just One, and he did not resist you.

7 Therefore, be patient, brothers, until the advent of the Lord. Consider that the farmer anticipates the precious fruit of the earth, waiting patiently, until he receives the early and the late rains.

8 Therefore, you too should be patient and should strengthen your hearts. For the advent of the Lord draws near.

9 Brothers, do not complain against one another, so that you may not be judged. Behold, the judge stands before the door.

10 My brothers, consider the Prophets, who spoke in the name of the Lord, as an example of departing from evil, of labor, and of patience.

11 Consider that we beatify those who have endured. You have heard of the patient suffering of Job. And you have seen the end of the Lord, that the Lord is merciful and compassionate.

12 But before all things, my brothers, do not choose to swear, neither by heaven, nor by the earth, nor in any other oath. But let your word 'Yes' be yes, and your word 'No' be no, so that you may not fall under judgment.

13 Is any of you sad? Let him pray. Is he even-tempered? Let him sing psalms.

14 Is anyone ill among you? Let him bring in the priests of the Church, and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord.

15 And a prayer of faith will save the infirm, and the Lord will alleviate him. And if he has sins, these will be forgiven him.

16 Therefore, confess your sins to one another, and pray for one another, so that you may be saved. For the unremitting prayer of a just person prevails over many things.

17 Elijah was a mortal man like us, and in prayer he prayed that it would not rain upon the earth. And it did not rain for three years and six months.

18 And he prayed again. And the heavens gave rain, and the earth brought forth her fruit.

19 My brothers, if anyone of you strays from the truth, and if someone converts him,

20 he ought to know that whoever causes a sinner to be converted from the error of his ways will save his soul from death and will cover a multitude of sins.

1 Peter 1

1 Peter, Apostle of Jesus Christ, to the newly-arrived elect of the dispersion in Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia,

2 in accord with the foreknowledge of God the Father, in the sanctification of the Spirit, with the obedience and the sprinkling of the blood of Jesus Christ: May grace and peace be multiplied for you.

3 Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who according to his great mercy has regenerated us into a living hope, through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead:

4 unto an incorruptible and undefiled and unfading inheritance, which is reserved for you in heaven.

5 By the power of God, you are guarded through faith for a salvation which is ready to be revealed in the end time.

6 In this, you should exult, if now, for a brief time, it is necessary to be made sorrowful by various trials,

7 so that the testing of your faith, which is much more precious than gold tested by fire, may be found in praise and glory and honor at the revelation of Jesus Christ.

8 For though you have not seen him, you love him. In him also, though you do not see him, you now believe. And in believing, you shall exult with an inexpressible and glorious joy,

9 returning with the goal of your faith, the salvation of souls.

10 About this salvation, the prophets inquired and diligently searched, those who prophesied about the future grace in you,

11 inquiring as to what type of condition was signified to them by the Spirit of Christ, when foretelling those sufferings that are in Christ, as well as the subsequent glories.

12 To them, it was revealed that they were ministering, not for themselves, but for you those things which have now been announced to you through those who have preached the Gospel to you, through the Holy Spirit, who was sent down from heaven to the One upon whom the Angels desire to gaze.

13 For this reason, gird the waist of your mind, be sober, and hope perfectly in the grace that is offered to you in the revelation of Jesus Christ.

14 Be like sons of obedience, not conforming to the desires of your former ignorance,

15 but in accord with him who has called you: the Holy One. And in every behavior, you yourself must be holy,

16 for it is written: "You shall be holy, for I am Holy."

17 And if you invoke as Father him who, without showing favoritism to persons, judges according to each one's work, then act in fear during the time of your sojourning here.

18 For you know that it was not with corruptible gold or silver that you were redeemed away from your useless behavior in the traditions of your fathers,

19 but it was with the precious blood of Christ, an immaculate and undefiled lamb,

20 foreknown, certainly, before the foundation of the world, and made manifest in these latter times for your sake.

21 Through him, you have been faithful to God, who raised him up from the dead and gave him glory, so that your faith and hope would be in God.

22 So chastise your souls with the obedience of charity, in fraternal love, and love one another from a simple heart, attentively.

23 For you have been born again, not from corruptible seed, but from what is incorruptible, from the Word of God, living and remaining for all eternity.

24 For all flesh is like the grass and all its glory is like the flower of the grass. The grass withers and its flower falls away.

25 But the Word of the Lord endures for eternity. And this is the Word that has been evangelized to you.

1 Peter 2

1 Therefore, set aside all malice and all deceitfulness, as well as falseness and envy and every detraction.

2 Like newborn infants, desire the milk of reasonableness without guile, so that by this you may increase unto salvation,

3 if it is true that you have tasted that the Lord is sweet.

4 And approaching him as if he were a living stone, rejected by men, certainly, but elect and honored by God,

5 be also yourselves like living stones, built upon him, a spiritual house, a holy priesthood, so as to offer up spiritual sacrifices, acceptable to God through Jesus Christ.

6 Because of this, Scripture asserts: "Behold, I am setting in Zion a chief cornerstone, elect, precious. And whoever will have believed in him will not be confounded."

7 Therefore, to you who believe, he is honor. But to those who do not believe, the stone which the builders have rejected, the same has been made into the head of the corner,

8 and a stone of offense, and a rock of scandal, to those who are offended by the Word; neither do they believe, though they also have been built upon him.

9 But you are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, an acquired people, so that you may announce the virtues of him who has called you out of darkness into his marvelous light.

10 Though in past times you were not a people, yet now you are the people of God. Though you had not obtained mercy, yet now you have obtained mercy.

11 Most beloved, I beg you, as new arrivals and sojourners, to abstain from carnal desires, which battle against the soul.

12 Keep your behavior among the Gentiles to what is good, so that, when they slander you as if you were evildoers, they may, by the good works that are seen in you, glorify God on the day of visitation.

13 Therefore, be subject to every human creature because of God, whether it is to the king as preeminent,

14 or to leaders as having been sent from him for vindication over evildoers, it is truly for the praise of what is good.

15 For such is the will of God, that by doing good you may bring about the silence of imprudent and ignorant men,

16 in an open manner, and not as if cloaking malice with liberty, but like servants of God.

17 Honor everyone. Love brotherhood. Fear God. Honor the king.

18 Servants, be subject to your masters with all fear, not only to the good and meek, but also to the unruly.

19 For this is grace: when, because of God, a man willingly endures sorrows, suffering injustice.

20 For what glory is there, if you sin and then suffer a beating? But if you do well and suffer patiently, this is grace with God.

21 For you have been called to this because Christ also suffered for us, leaving you an example, so that you would follow in his footsteps.

22 He committed no sin, neither was deceit found in his mouth.

23 And when evil was spoken against him, he did not speak evil. When he suffered, he did not threaten. Then he handed himself over to him who judged him unjustly.

24 He himself bore our sins in his body upon the tree, so that we, having died to sin, would live for justice. By his wounds, you have been healed.

25 For you were like wandering sheep. But now you have been turned back toward the Pastor and the Bishop of your souls.

1 Peter 3

1 Similarly also, wives should be subject to their husbands, so that, even if some do not believe the Word, they may benefit without the Word, through the behavior of these wives,

2 as they consider with fear your chaste behavior.

3 For you, there should be no unnecessary adornment of the hair, or surrounding with gold, or the wearing of ornate clothing.

4 Instead, you should be a hidden person of the heart, with the incorruptibility of a quiet and a meek spirit, rich in the sight of God.

5 For in this way, in past times also, holy women adorned themselves, hoping in God, being subject to their own husbands.

6 For so Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him lord. You are her daughters, well-behaved and unafraid of any disturbance.

7 Similarly, you husbands should live with them in accord with knowledge, bestowing honor on the female as the weaker vessel and as co-heirs of the life of grace, so that your prayers may not be hindered.

8 And finally, may you all be of one mind: compassionate, loving brotherhood, merciful, meek, humble,

9 not repaying evil with evil, nor slander with slander, but, to the contrary, repaying with blessings. For to this you have been called, so that you may possess the inheritance of a blessing.

10 For whoever wants to love life and to see good days should restrain his tongue from evil, and his lips, so that they utter no deceit.

11 Let him turn away from evil, and do good. Let him seek peace, and pursue it.

12 For the eyes of the Lord are upon the just, and his ears are with their prayers, but the countenance of the Lord is upon those who do evil.

13 And who is it who can harm you, if you are zealous in what is good?

14 And yet, even when you suffer something for the sake of justice, you are blessed. So then, do not be afraid with their fear, and do not be disturbed.

15 But sanctify Christ the Lord in your hearts, being always ready to give an explanation to all who ask you the reason for that hope which is in you.

16 But do so with meekness and fear, having a good conscience, so that, in whatever matter they may slander you, they shall be confounded, since they falsely accuse your good behavior in Christ.

17 For it is better to suffer for doing good, if it is the will of God, than for doing evil.

18 For Christ also died once for our sins, the Just One on behalf of the unjust, so that he might offer us to God, having died, certainly, in the flesh, but having been enlivened by the Spirit.

19 And in the Spirit, he preached to those who were in prison, going to those souls

20 who had been unbelieving in past times, while they waited for the patience of God, as in the days of Noah, when the ark was being built. In that ark, a few, that is, eight souls, were saved by water.

21 And now you also are saved, in a similar manner, by baptism, not by the testimony of sordid flesh, but by the examination of a good conscience in God, through the resurrection of Jesus Christ.

22 He is at the right hand of God, devouring death, so that we may be made heirs to eternal life. And since he has journeyed to heaven, the Angels and powers and virtues are subject to him.

1 Peter 4

1 Since Christ has suffered in the flesh, you also should be armed with the same intention. For he who suffers in the flesh desists from sin,

2 so that now he may live, for the remainder of his time in the flesh, not by the desires of men, but by the will of God.

3 For the time that has passed is sufficient to have fulfilled the will of the Gentiles, those who have walked in luxuries, lusts, intoxication, feasting, drinking, and the illicit worship of idols.

4 About this, they wonder why you do not rush with them into the same confusion of indulgences, blaspheming.

5 But they must render an account to him who is prepared to judge the living and the dead.

6 For because of this, the Gospel was also preached to the dead, so that they might be judged, certainly, just like men in the flesh, yet also, so that they might live according to God, in the Spirit.

7 But the end of everything draws near. And so, be prudent, and be vigilant in your prayers.

8 But, before all things, have a constant mutual charity among yourselves. For love covers a multitude of sins.

9 Show hospitality to one another without complaining.

10 Just as each of you has received grace, minister in the same way to one another, as good stewards of the manifold grace of God.

11 When anyone speaks, it should be like words of God. When anyone ministers, it should be from the virtue that God provides, so that in all things God may be honored through Jesus Christ. To him is glory and dominion forever and ever. Amen.

12 Most beloved, do not choose to sojourn in the passion which is a temptation to you, as if something new might happen to you.

13 But instead, commune in the Passion of Christ, and be glad that, when his glory will be revealed, you too may rejoice with exultation.

14 If you are reproached for the name of Christ, you will be blessed, because that which is of the honor, glory, and power of God, and that which is of his Spirit, rests upon you.

15 But let none of you suffer for being a murderer, or a thief, or a slanderer, or one who covets what belongs to another.

16 But if one of you suffers for being a Christian, he should not be ashamed. Instead, he should glorify God in that name.

17 For it is time that judgment begin at the house of God. And if it is first from us, what shall be the end of those who do not believe the Gospel of God?

18 And if the just man will scarcely be saved, where will the impious and the sinner appear?

19 Therefore, too, let those who suffer according to the will of God commend their souls by good deeds to the faithful Creator.

1 Peter 5

1 Therefore, I beg the elders who are among you, as one who is also an elder and a witness of the Passion of Christ, who also shares in that glory which is to be revealed in the future:

2 pasture the flock of God that is among you, providing for it, not as a requirement, but willingly, in accord with God, and not for the sake of tainted profit, but freely,

3 not so as to dominate by means of the clerical state, but so as to be formed into a flock from the heart.

4 And when the Leader of pastors will have appeared, you shall secure an unfading crown of glory.

5 Similarly, young persons, be subject to the elders. And infuse all humility among one another, for God resists the arrogant, but to the humble he gives grace.

6 And so, be humbled under the powerful hand of God, so that he may exalt you in the time of visitation.

7 Cast all your cares upon him, for he takes care of you.

8 Be sober and vigilant. For your adversary, the devil, is like a roaring lion, traveling around and seeking those whom he might devour.

9 Resist him by being strong in faith, being aware that the same passions afflict those who are your brothers in the world.

10 But the God of all grace, who has called us to his eternal glory in Christ Jesus, will himself perfect, confirm, and establish us, after a brief time of suffering.

11 To him be glory and dominion forever and ever. Amen.

12 I have written briefly, through Sylvanus, whom I consider to be a faithful brother to you, begging and testifying that this is the true grace of God, in which you have been established.

13 The Church which is in Babylon, elect together with you, greets you, as does my son, Mark.

14 Greet one another with a holy kiss. Grace be to all of you who are in Christ Jesus. Amen.

2 Peter 1

1 Simon Peter, servant and Apostle of Jesus Christ, to those who have been allotted an equal faith with us in the justice of our God and in our Savior Jesus Christ.

2 Grace to you. And may peace be fulfilled according to the plan of God and of Christ Jesus our Lord,

3 in the same manner that all things which are for life and piety have been given to us by his Divine virtue, through the plan of him who has called us to our own glory and virtue.

4 Through Christ, he has given us the greatest and most precious promises, so that by these things you may become sharers in the Divine Nature, fleeing from the corruption of that desire which is in the world.

5 But as for you, taking up every concern, minister virtue in your faith; and in virtue, knowledge;

6 and in knowledge, moderation; and in moderation, patience; and in patience, piety;

7 and in piety, love of brotherhood; and in love of brotherhood, charity.

8 For if these things are with you, and if they abound, they will cause you to be neither empty, nor without fruit, within the plan of our Lord Jesus Christ.

9 For he who does not have these things at hand is blind and groping, being forgetful of his purification from his former offenses.

10 Because of this, brothers, be all the more diligent, so that by good works you may make certain your calling and election. For in doing these things, you do not sin at any time.

11 For in this way, you shall be provided abundantly with an entrance into the eternal kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.

12 For this reason, I will always begin to admonish you about these things, even though, certainly, you know them and are confirmed in the present truth.

13 But I consider it just, as long as I am in this tabernacle, to stir you up with admonishments.

14 For it is certain that the laying to rest of this, my tabernacle, is approaching swiftly, just as our Lord Jesus Christ has also indicated to me.

15 Therefore, I will present a work for you to have, so that, frequently after my passing, you may call to mind these things.

16 For it was not by following fanciful doctrines that we made known to you the power and presence of our Lord Jesus Christ, but we were made eyewitnesses of his greatness.

17 For he received honor and glory from God the Father, whose voice descended to him from the magnificent glory: "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased. Listen to him."

18 We also heard this voice conveyed from heaven, when we were with him on the holy mountain.

19 And so, we have an even firmer prophetic word, to which you would do well to listen, as to a light shining within a dark place, until the day dawns, and the daystar rises, in your hearts.

20 Understand this first: that every prophecy of Scripture does not result from one's own interpretation.

21 For prophecy was not conveyed by human will at any time. Instead, holy men were speaking about God while inspired by the Holy Spirit.

2 Peter 2

1 But there were also false prophets among the people, just as there will be among you lying teachers, who will introduce divisions of perdition, and they will deny him who bought them, the Lord, bringing upon themselves swift destruction.

2 And many persons will follow their indulgences; through such persons, the way of truth will be blasphemed.

3 And in avarice, they will negotiate about you with false words. Their judgment, in the near future, is not delayed, and their perdition does not sleep.

4 For God did not spare those Angels who sinned, but instead delivered them, as if dragged down by infernal ropes, into the torments of the underworld, to be reserved unto judgment.

5 And he did not spare the original world, but he preserved the eighth one, Noah, the herald of justice, bringing the flood upon the world of the impious.

6 And he reduced the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah to ashes, condemning them to be overthrown, setting them as an example to anyone who might act impiously.

7 And he rescued a just man, Lot, who was oppressed by the unjust and lewd behavior of the wicked.

8 For in seeing and in hearing, he was just, though he lived with those who, from day to day, crucified the just soul with works of iniquity.

9 Thus, the Lord knows how to rescue the pious from trials, and how to reserve the iniquitous for torments on the day of judgment;

10 even more so, those who walk after the flesh in unclean desires, and who despise proper authority. Boldly pleasing themselves, they do not dread to introduce divisions by blaspheming;

11 whereas the Angels, who are greater in strength and virtue, did not bring against themselves such a deplorable judgment.

12 Yet truly, these others, like irrational beasts, naturally fall into traps and into ruin by blaspheming whatever they do not understand, and so they shall perish in their corruption,

13 receiving the reward of injustice, the fruition of valuing the delights of the day: defilements and stains, overflowing with self-indulgences, taking pleasure in their feasts with you,

14 having eyes full of adultery and of incessant offenses, luring unstable souls, having a heart well-trained in avarice, sons of curses!

15 Abandoning the straight path, they wandered astray, having followed the way of Balaam, the son of Beor, who loved the wages of iniquity.

16 Yet truly, he had a correction of his madness: the mute animal under the yoke, which, by speaking with a human voice, forbid the folly of the prophet.

17 These ones are like fountains without water, and like clouds stirred up by whirlwinds. For them, the mist of darkness is reserved.

18 For, speaking with the arrogance of vanity, they lure, by the desires of fleshly pleasures, those who are fleeing to some extent, who are being turned from error,

19 promising them freedoms, while they themselves are the servants of corruption. For by whatever a man is overcome, of this also is he the servant.

20 For if, after taking refuge from the defilements of the world in the understanding of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, they again become entangled and overcome by these things, then the latter state becomes worse than the former.

21 For it would have been better for them not to have known the way of justice than, after acknowledging it, to turn away from that holy commandment which was handed on to them.

22 For the truth of the proverb has happened to them: The dog has returned to his own vomit, and the washed sow has returned to her wallowing in the mud.

2 Peter 3

1 Consider, most beloved, this second epistle which I am writing to you, in which I stir up, by admonition, your sincere mind,

2 so that you may be mindful of those words that I preached to you from the holy prophets, and of the precepts of the Apostles of your Lord and Savior.

3 Know this first: that in the last days there will arrive deceitful mockers, walking according to their own desires,

4 saying: "Where is his promise or his advent? For from the time that the fathers have slept, all things have continued just as they were from the beginning of creation."

5 But they willfully ignore this: that the heavens existed first, and that the earth, from water and through water, was established by the Word of God.

6 By water, the former world then, having been inundated with water, perished.

7 But the heavens and the earth that exist now were restored by the same Word, being reserved unto fire on the day of judgment, and unto the perdition of impious men.

8 Yet truly, let this one thing not escape notice, most beloved, that with the Lord one day is like a thousand years, and a thousand years is like one day.

9 The Lord is not delaying his promise, as some imagine, but he does act patiently for your sake, not wanting anyone to perish, but wanting all to be turned back to penance.

10 Then the day of the Lord shall arrive like a thief. On that day, the heavens shall pass away with great violence, and truly the elements shall be dissolved with heat; then the earth, and the works that are within it, shall be completely burned up.

11 Therefore, since all these things will be dissolved, what kind of people ought you to be? In behavior and in piety, be holy,

12 waiting for, and hurrying toward, the advent of the day of the Lord, by which the burning heavens shall be dissolved, and the elements shall melt from the heat of the fire.

13 Yet truly, in accord with his promises, we are looking forward to the new heavens and the new earth, in which justice lives.

14 Therefore, most beloved, while awaiting these things, be diligent, so that you may be found to be immaculate and unassailable before him, in peace.

15 And let the longsuffering of our Lord be considered salvation, as also our most beloved brother Paul, according to the wisdom given to him, has written to you,

16 just as he also spoke in all of his epistles about these things. In these, there are certain things which are difficult to understand, which the unlearned and the unsteady distort, as they also do the other Scriptures, to their own destruction.

17 But since you, brothers, know these things beforehand, be cautious, lest by being drawn into the error of the foolish, you may fall away from your own steadfastness.

18 Yet truly, increase in grace and in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. To him be glory, both now and in the day of eternity. Amen.

1 John 1

1 He who was from the beginning, whom we have heard, whom we have seen with our eyes, upon whom we have gazed, and whom our hands have certainly touched: He is the Word of Life.

2 And that Life has been made manifest. And we have seen, and we testify, and we announce to you: the Eternal Life, who was with the Father, and who appeared to us.

3 He whom we have seen and heard, we announce to you, so that you, too, may have fellowship with us, and so that our fellowship may be with the Father and with his Son Jesus Christ.

4 And this we write to you, so that you may rejoice, and so that your joy may be full.

5 And this is the announcement which we have heard from him, and which we announce to you: that God is light, and in him there is no darkness.

6 If we claim that we have fellowship with him, and yet we walk in darkness, then we are lying and not telling the truth.

7 But if we walk in the light, just as he also is in the light, then we have fellowship with one another, and the blood of Jesus Christ, his Son, cleanses us from all sin.

8 If we claim that we have no sin, then we are deceiving ourselves and the truth is not in us.

9 If we confess our sins, then he is faithful and just, so as to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all iniquity.

10 If we claim that we have not sinned, then we make him a liar, and his Word is not in us.

1 John 2

1 My little sons, this I write to you, so that you may not sin. But if anyone has sinned, we have an Advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ, the Just One.

2 And he is the propitiation for our sins. And not only for our sins, but also for those of the whole world.

3 And we can be sure that we have known him by this: if we observe his commandments.

4 Whoever claims that he knows him, and yet does not keep his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him.

5 But whoever keeps his word, truly in him the charity of God is perfected. And by this we know that we are in him.

6 Whoever declares himself to remain in him, ought to walk just as he himself walked.

7 Most beloved, I am not writing to you a new commandment, but the old commandment, which you had from the beginning. The old commandment is the Word, which you have heard.

8 Then too, I am writing to you a new commandment, which is the Truth in him and in you. For the darkness has passed away, and the true Light is now shining.

9 Whoever declares himself to be in the light, and yet hates his brother, is in the darkness even now.

10 Whoever loves his brother abides in the light, and there is no cause of offense in him.

11 But whoever hates his brother is in the darkness, and in darkness he walks, and he does not know where he is going. For the darkness has blinded his eyes.

12 I am writing to you, little sons, because your sins are forgiven for the sake of his name.

13 I am writing to you, fathers, because you have known him who is from the beginning. I am writing to you, adolescents, because you have overcome the evil one.

14 I am writing to you, little children, because you have known the Father. I am writing to you, young men, because you are strong, and the Word of God abides in you, and you have overcome the evil one.

15 Do not choose to love the world, nor the things that are in the world. If anyone loves the world, the charity of the Father is not in him.

16 For all that is in the world is the desire of the flesh, and the desire of the eyes, and the arrogance of a life which is not of the Father, but is of the world.

17 And the world is passing away, with its desire. But whoever does the will of God abides unto eternity.

18 Little sons, it is the last hour. And, as you have heard that the Antichrist is coming, so now many antichrists have arrived. By this, we know that it is the last hour.

19 They went out from among us, but they were not of us. For, if they had been of us, certainly they would have remained with us. But in this way, it is made manifest that none of them are of us.

20 Yet you have the anointing of the Holy One, and you know everything.

21 I have not written to you as to ones who are ignorant of the truth, but as to ones who know the truth. For no lie is of the truth.

22 Who is a liar, other than he who denies that Jesus is the Christ? This one is the Antichrist, who denies the Father and the Son.

23 No one who denies the Son also has the Father. Whoever confesses the Son, also has the Father.

24 As for you, let what you have heard from the beginning remain in you. If what you have heard from the beginning remains in you, then you, too, shall abide in the Son and in the Father.

25 And this is the Promise, which he himself has promised to us: Eternal Life.

26 I have written these things to you, because of those who would seduce you.

27 But as for you, let the Anointing that you have received from him abide in you. And so, you have no need of anyone to teach you. For his Anointing teaches you about everything, and it is the truth, and it is not a lie. And just as his Anointing has taught you, abide in him.

28 And now, little sons, abide in him, so that when he appears, we may have faith, and we may not be confounded by him at his advent.

29 If you know that he is just, then know, too, that all who do what is just are born of him.

1 John 3

1 See what kind of love the Father has given to us, that we would be called, and would become, the sons of God. Because of this, the world does not know us, for it did not know him.

2 Most beloved, we are now the sons of God. But what we shall be then has not yet appeared. We know that when he does appear, we shall be like him, for we shall see him as he is.

3 And everyone who holds this hope in him, keeps himself holy, just as he also is holy.

4 Everyone who commits a sin, also commits iniquity. For sin is iniquity.

5 And you know that he appeared in order that he might take away our sins. For in him there is no sin.

6 Everyone who abides in him does not sin. For whoever sins has not seen him, and has not known him.

7 Little sons, let no one deceive you. Whoever does justice is just, even as he also is just.

8 Whoever commits sin is of the devil. For the devil sins from the beginning. For this reason, the Son of God appeared, so that he might eradicate the works of the devil.

9 All those who have been born of God do not commit sin. For the offspring of God abides in them, and he is not able to sin, because he was born of God.

10 In this way, the sons of God are made manifest, and also the sons of the devil. Everyone who is not just, is not of God, as also anyone who does not love his brother.

11 For this is the announcement that you heard from the beginning: that you should love one another.

12 Do not be like Cain, who was of the evil one, and who killed his brother. And why did he kill him? Because his own works were wicked, but his brother's works were just.

13 If the world hates you, brothers, do not be surprised.

14 We know that we have passed from death to life. For we love as brothers. Whoever does not love, abides in death.

15 Everyone who hates his brother is a murderer. And you know that no murderer has eternal life abiding within him.

16 We know the love of God in this way: because he laid down his life for us. And so, we must lay down our lives for our brothers.

17 Whoever possesses the goods of this world, and sees his brother to be in need, and yet closes his heart to him: in what way does the love of God abide in him?

18 My little sons, let us not love in words only, but in works and in truth.

19 In this way, we will know that we are of the truth, and we will commend our hearts in his sight.

20 For even if our heart reproaches us, God is greater than our heart, and he knows all things.

21 Most beloved, if our heart does not reproach us, we can have confidence toward God;

22 and whatever we shall request of him, we shall receive from him. For we keep his commandments, and we do the things that are pleasing in his sight.

23 And this is his commandment: that we should believe in the name of his Son, Jesus Christ, and love one another, just as he has commanded us.

24 And those who keep his commandments abide in him, and he in them. And we know that he abides in us by this: by the Spirit, whom he has given to us.

1 John 4

1 Most beloved, do not be willing to believe every spirit, but test the spirits to see if they are of God. For many false prophets have gone out into the world.

2 The Spirit of God may be known in this way. Every spirit who confesses that Jesus Christ has arrived in the flesh is of God;

3 and every spirit who contradicts Jesus is not of God. And this one is the Antichrist, the one that you have heard is coming, and even now he is in the world.

4 Little sons, you are of God, and so you have overcome him. For he who is in you is greater than he who is in the world.

5 They are of the world. Therefore, they speak about the world, and the world listens to them.

6 We are of God. Whoever knows God, listens to us. Whoever is not of God, does not listen to us. In this way, we know the Spirit of truth from the spirit of error.

7 Most beloved, let us love one another. For love is of God. And everyone who loves is born of God and knows God.

8 Whoever does not love, does not know God. For God is love.

9 The love of God was made apparent to us in this way: that God sent his only-begotten Son into the world, so that we might live through him.

10 In this is love: not as if we had loved God, but that he first loved us, and so he sent his Son as a propitiation for our sins.

11 Most beloved, if God has so loved us, we also ought to love one another.

12 No one has ever seen God. But if we love one another, God abides in us, and his love is perfected in us.

13 In this way, we know that we abide in him, and he in us: because he has given to us from his Spirit.

14 And we have seen, and we testify, that the Father has sent his Son to be the Savior of the world.

15 Whoever has confessed that Jesus is the Son of God, God abides in him, and he in God.

16 And we have known and believed the love that God has for us. God is love. And he who abides in love, abides in God, and God in him.

17 In this way, the love of God is perfected with us, so that we may have confidence on the day of judgment. For as he is, so also are we, in this world.

18 Fear is not in love. Instead, perfect love casts out fear, for fear pertains to punishment. And whoever fears is not perfected in love.

19 Therefore, let us love God, for God first loved us.

20 If anyone says that he loves God, but hates his brother, then he is a liar. For he who does not love his brother, whom he does see, in what way can he love God, whom he does not see?

21 And this is the commandment that we have from God, that he who loves God must also love his brother.

1 John 5

1 Everyone who believes that Jesus is the Christ, is born of God. And everyone who loves God, who provides that birth, also loves him who has been born of God.

2 In this way, we know that we love those born of God: when we love God and do his commandments.

3 For this is the love of God: that we keep his commandments. And his commandments are not heavy.

4 For all that is born of God overcomes the world. And this is the victory that overcomes the world: our faith.

5 Who is it that overcomes the world? Only he who believes that Jesus is the Son of God!

6 This is the One who came by water and blood: Jesus Christ. Not by water only, but by water and blood. And the Spirit is the One who testifies that the Christ is the Truth.

7 For there are Three who give testimony in heaven: the Father, the Word, and the Holy Spirit. And these Three are One.

8 And there are three who give testimony on earth: the Spirit, and the water, and the blood. And these three are one.

9 If we accept the testimony of men, then the testimony of God is greater. For this is the testimony of God, which is greater: that he has testified about his Son.

10 Whoever believes in the Son of God, holds the testimony of God within himself. Whoever does not believe in the Son, makes him a liar, because he does not believe in the testimony which God has testified about his Son.

11 And this is the testimony which God has given to us: Eternal Life. And this Life is in his Son.

12 Whoever has the Son, has Life. Whoever does not have the Son, does not have Life.

13 I am writing this to you, so that you may know that you have Eternal Life: you who believe in the name of the Son of God.

14 And this is the confidence which we have toward God: that no matter what we shall request, in accord with his will, he hears us.

15 And we know that he hears us, no matter what we request; so we know that we can obtain the things that we request of him.

16 Anyone who realizes that his brother has sinned, with a sin that is not unto death, let him pray, and life shall be given to him who has sinned not unto death. There is a sin which is unto death. I am not saying that anyone should ask on behalf of that sin.

17 All that is iniquity is sin. But there is a sin unto death.

18 We know that everyone who is born of God does not sin. Instead, rebirth in God preserves him, and the evil one cannot touch him.

19 We know that we are of God, and that the entire world is established in wickedness.

20 And we know that the Son of God has arrived, and that he has given us understanding, so that we may know the true God, and so that we may remain in his true Son. This is the true God, and this is Eternal Life.

21 Little sons, keep yourselves from false worship. Amen.

2 John 1

1 The Elder to the Elect Lady, and those born of her, whom I love in the truth: and not I alone, but also all those who have known the truth,

2 because the truth which dwells in us shall be with us for eternity.

3 May grace, mercy, and peace be with you from God the Father, and from Christ Jesus, the Son of the Father, in truth and in love.

4 I was very glad because I discovered some of your sons walking in the truth, just as we received the commandment from the Father.

5 And now I petition you, Lady, not as if writing a new commandment to you, but instead that commandment which we have had from the beginning: that we love one another.

6 And this is love: that we walk according to his commandments. For this is the commandment that you have heard in the same way from the beginning, and in which you should walk.

7 For many deceivers have gone out into the world, those who do not confess that Jesus Christ has arrived in the flesh. Such a one as this is a deceiver and an antichrist.

8 Be cautious for yourselves, lest you lose what you have accomplished, and so that, instead, you may receive a full reward.

9 Everyone who withdraws and does not remain in the doctrine of Christ, does not have God. Whoever remains in the doctrine, such a one as this has both the Father and the Son.

10 If anyone comes to you, and does not bring this doctrine, do not be willing to receive him into the house, and do not speak a greeting to him.

11 For whoever speaks a greeting to him, is speaking with his evil works.

12 I have much more to write to you, but I am not willing to do so through paper and ink. For I hope that I may be with you in the future, and that I may speak face to face, so that your joy may be full.

13 The sons of your Elect Sister greet you.

3 John 1

1 The Elder, to Gaius, most beloved, whom I love in the truth.

2 Most beloved, concerning everything, I make it my prayer that you may benefit by advancing and succeeding in whatever may be to the benefit of your soul.

3 I was very glad when the brothers arrived, and when they offered testimony to the truth in you, that you are walking in the truth.

4 I have no greater grace than this, when I hear that my sons are walking in the truth.

5 Most beloved, you should act faithfully in whatever you do for the brothers, and those who are sojourners;

6 they have given testimony to your charity in the sight of the Church. You would to well to lead these ones worthily to God.

7 For they set out, on behalf of his name, accepting nothing from the unbelievers.

8 Therefore, we must accept such as these, in order that we may cooperate with the truth.

9 As it happens, I had written to the church. But Diotrephes, who loves to bear the highest rank among them, would not accept us.

10 Because of this, when I come, I will admonish his works which he does, babbling against us with malicious words. And as if this were not sufficient for him, he himself does not receive the brothers. And those who do receive them, he hinders, and he ejects them from the church.

11 Most beloved, do not be willing to imitate what is evil; instead imitate what is good. Whoever does good is of God. Whoever does evil has not seen God.

12 Testimony is being given for Demetrius by everyone, and by the truth itself. And we also offer testimony. And you know that our testimony is true.

13 I had many things to write to you, but I am not willing, through ink and pen, to write to you.

14 Yet I hope to see you soon, and then we will speak face to face. Peace to you. The friends greet you. Greet the friends by name.

Jude 1

1 Jude, a servant of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to those who are beloved in God the Father, and who are guarded and called in Jesus Christ:

2 May mercy, and peace, and love be fulfilled in you.

3 Most beloved, taking all care to write to you about your common salvation, I found it necessary to write to you in order to beg you to contend earnestly for the faith that was handed down once to the saints.

4 For certain men entered unnoticed, who were written of beforehand unto this judgment: impious persons who are transforming the grace of our God into self-indulgence, and who are denying both the sole Ruler and our Lord Jesus Christ.

5 So I want to caution you. Those who once knew everything that Jesus did, in saving the people from the land of Egypt, afterwards perished because they did not believe.

6 And truly, the Angels, who did not keep to their first place, but instead abandoned their own domiciles, he has reserved with perpetual chains under darkness, unto the great day of judgment.

7 And also Sodom and Gomorrah, and the adjoining cities, in similar ways, having given themselves over to fornication and to the pursuing of other flesh, were made an example, suffering the punishment of eternal fire.

8 Similarly also, these ones certainly defile the flesh, and they despise proper authority, and they blaspheme against majesty.

9 When Michael the Archangel, disputing with the devil, contended about the body of Moses, he did not dare to bring against him a judgment of blasphemy, so instead he said: "The Lord commands you."

10 But these men certainly blaspheme against whatever they do not understand. And yet, whatever they, like mute animals, know from nature, in these things they are corrupted.

11 Woe to them! For they have gone after the way of Cain, and they have poured out the error of Balaam for profit, and they have perished in the sedition of Korah.

12 These ones are defiled within their banquets, enjoying themselves and feeding themselves without fear; waterless clouds, which are tossed about by winds; autumn trees, unfruitful, twice dead, uprooted;

13 raging waves of the sea, foaming from their own confusion; wandering stars, for whom the whirlwind of darkness has been reserved forever!

14 And about these, Enoch, the seventh from Adam, also prophesied, saying: "Behold, the Lord is arriving with thousands of his saints,

15 to execute judgment against everyone, and to reprove all the impious concerning all the works of their impiety, by which they have acted impiously, and concerning all the harsh things that impious sinners have spoken against God."

16 These ones are complaining murmurers, walking according to their own desires. And their mouth is speaking arrogance, admiring persons for the sake of gain.

17 But as for you, most beloved, be mindful of the words which have been foretold by the Apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ,

18 who declared to you that, in the end time, there would arrive mockers, walking according to their own desires, in impieties.

19 These are the ones who segregate themselves; they are animals, not having the Spirit.

20 But you, most beloved, are building yourselves up by your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Spirit,

21 keeping yourselves in the love of God, and anticipating the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ unto eternal life.

22 So certainly, reprove them, after they have been judged.

23 Yet truly, save them, seizing them from the fire. And have mercy on others: in fear, hating even that which is of the flesh, the defiled garment.

24 Then, to him who has the power to keep you free from sin and to present you, immaculate, with exultation, before the presence of his glory at the advent of our Lord Jesus Christ,

25 to the only God, our Savior, through Jesus Christ our Lord: to him be glory and magnificence, dominion and power, before all ages, and now, and in every age, forever. Amen.

Revelation 1

1 The Revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave to him, in order to make known to his servants the things that must soon occur, and which he signified by sending his Angel to his servant John;

2 he has offered testimony to the Word of God, and whatever he saw is the testimony of Jesus Christ.

3 Blessed is he who reads or hears the words of this Prophecy, and who keeps the things that have been written in it. For the time is near.

4 John, to the seven Churches, which are in Asia. Grace and peace to you, from him who is, and who was, and who is to come, and from the seven spirits who are in the sight of his throne,

5 and from Jesus Christ, who is the faithful witness, the first-born of the dead, and the leader over the kings of the earth, who has loved us and has washed us from our sins with his blood,

6 and who has made us into a kingdom and into priests for God and for his Father. To him be glory and dominion forever and ever. Amen.

7 Behold, he arrives with the clouds, and every eye shall see him, even those who pierced him. And all the tribes of the earth shall lament for themselves over him. Even so. Amen.

8 "I am the Alpha and the Omega, the Beginning and the End," says the Lord God, who is, and who was, and who is to come, the Almighty.

9 I, John, your brother, and a sharer in the tribulation and in the kingdom and in patient endurance for Christ Jesus, was on the island which is called Patmos, because of the Word of God and the testimony to Jesus.

10 I was in the Spirit on the Lord's day, and I heard behind me a great voice, like that of a trumpet,

11 saying, "What you see, write in a book, and send it to the seven Churches, which are in Asia: to Ephesus, and to Smyrna, and to Pergamus, and to Thyatira, and to Sardis, and to Philadelphia, and to Laodicea."

12 And I turned around, so as to see the voice which was speaking with me. And having turned around, I saw seven golden lampstands.

13 And in the midst of the seven golden lampstands was one resembling the Son of man, clothed to the feet with a vestment, and wrapped to the breast with a wide belt of gold.

14 But his head and hair were bright, like white wool, or like snow; and his eyes were like a flame of fire;

15 and his feet resembled shining brass, just as in a burning furnace; and his voice was like the voice of many waters.

16 And in his right hand, he held the seven stars; and from his mouth went out a sharp two-edged sword; and his face was like the sun, shining with all its might.

17 And when I had seen him, I fell at his feet, like one who is dead. And he laid his right hand upon me, saying: "Do not be afraid. I am the First and the Last.

18 And I am alive, though I was dead. And, behold, I live forever and ever. And I hold the keys of death and of Hell.

19 Therefore, write the things which you have seen, and which are, and which must occur afterward:

20 the mystery of the seven stars, which you have seen in my right hand, and of the seven golden lampstands. The seven stars are the Angels of the seven Churches, and the seven lampstands are the seven Churches."

Revelation 2

1 "And to the Angel of the Church of Ephesus write: Thus says the One who holds the seven stars in his right hand, who walks in the midst of the seven golden lampstands:

2 I know your works, and your hardship and patient endurance, and that you cannot stand those who are evil. And so, you have tested those who declare themselves to be Apostles and are not, and you have found them to be liars.

3 And you have patient endurance for the sake of my name, and you have not fallen away.

4 But I have this against you: that you have relinquished your first charity.

5 And so, call to mind the place from which you have fallen, and do penance, and do the first works. Otherwise, I will come to you and remove your lampstand from its place, unless you repent.

6 But this you have, that you hate the deeds of the Nicolaitans, which I also hate.

7 Whoever has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the Churches. To him who prevails, I will give to eat from the Tree of Life, which is in the Paradise of my God.

8 And to the Angel of the Church of Smyrna write: Thus says the First and the Last, he who was dead and now lives:

9 I know your tribulation and your poverty, but you are rich, and that you are blasphemed by those who declare themselves to be Jews and are not, but who are a synagogue of Satan.

10 You should fear nothing amid those things which you will suffer. Behold, the devil will cast some of you into prison, so that you may be tested. And you will have tribulation for ten days. Be faithful even unto death, and I will give to you the crown of life.

11 Whoever has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the Churches. Whoever will prevail, he shall not be harmed by the second death.

12 And to the Angel of the Church of Pergamus write: Thus says he who holds the sharp two-edged spear:

13 I know where you dwell, where the seat of Satan is, and that you hold to my name and have not denied my faith, even in those days when Antipas was my faithful witness, who was slain among you, where Satan dwells.

14 But I have a few things against you. For you have, in that place, those who hold to the doctrine of Balaam, who instructed Balak to cast a stumbling block before the sons of Israel, to eat and to commit fornication.

15 And you also have those who hold to the doctrine of the Nicolaitans.

16 So do penance to the same extent. If you do less, I will come to you quickly and I will fight against these ones with the sword of my mouth.

17 Whoever has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the Churches. To him who prevails, I will give the hidden manna. And I will give to him a white emblem, and on the emblem, a new name has been written, which no one knows, except the one who receives it.

18 And to the Angel of the Church of Thyatira write: Thus says the Son of God, who has eyes like a flame of fire, and his feet are like shining brass.

19 I know your works, and your faith and charity, and your ministry and patient endurance, and that your more recent works are greater than the earlier ones.

20 But I have a few things against you. For you permit the woman Jezabel, who calls herself a prophetess, to teach and to seduce my servants, to commit fornication and to eat the food of idolatry.

21 And I gave her a time, so that she might do penance, but she is not willing to repent from her fornication.

22 Behold, I will cast her onto a bed, and those who commit adultery with her shall be in a very great tribulation, unless they repent from their works.

23 And I will put her sons to death, and all the Churches shall know that I am the one who examines temperaments and hearts. And I will give to each one of you according to your works. But I say to you,

24 and to the others who are at Thyatira: Whoever does not hold to this doctrine, and who has not 'known the depths of Satan,' as they say, I will not set any other weight upon you.

25 Even so, that which you have, hold on to it until I return.

26 And whoever will prevail and will observe my works even unto the end, I will give to him authority over the nations.

27 And he shall rule them with an iron rod, and they shall be broken like the earthenware of a potter.

28 The same I also have received from my Father. And I will give to him the morning star.

29 Whoever has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the Churches."

Revelation 3

1 "And to the Angel of the Church of Sardis write: Thus says he who has the seven spirits of God and the seven stars: I know your works, that you have a name which is alive, but you are dead.

2 Be vigilant, and confirm the things that remain, lest they soon die out. For I do not find your works to be full in the sight of my God.

3 Therefore, keep in mind the way that you have received and heard, and then observe it and repent. But if you will not be vigilant, I will come to you like a thief, and you will not know at what hour I will come to you.

4 But you have a few names in Sardis who have not defiled their garments. And these shall walk with me in white, because they are worthy.

5 Whoever prevails, so shall he be clothed in white vestments. And I will not delete his name from the Book of Life. And I will confess his name in the presence of my Father and in the presence of his Angels.

6 Whoever has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the Churches.

7 And to the Angel of the Church of Philadelphia write: Thus says the Holy One, the True One, he who holds the key of David. He opens and no one closes. He closes and no one opens.

8 I know your works. Behold, I have set an open door before you, which no one is able to close. For you have little power, and you have observed my word, and you have not denied my name.

9 Behold, I will take from the synagogue of Satan those who declare themselves to be Jews and are not, for they are lying. Behold, I will cause them to approach and to reverence before your feet. And they shall know that I have loved you.

10 Since you have kept the word of my patient endurance, I also will keep you from the hour of temptation, which shall overcome the whole world in order to test those living upon the earth.

11 Behold, I am approaching quickly. Hold on to what you have, so that no one may take your crown.

12 Whoever prevails, I will set him as a column in the temple of my God, and he shall not depart from it anymore. And I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the city of my God, the new Jerusalem that descends out of heaven from my God, and my new name.

13 Whoever has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the Churches.

14 And to the Angel of the Church of Laodicea write: Thus says the Amen, the faithful and true Witness, who is the Beginning of the creation of God:

15 I know your works: that you are neither cold, nor hot. I wish that you were either cold or hot.

16 But because you are lukewarm and are neither cold nor hot, I will begin to vomit you out of my mouth.

17 For you declare, 'I am wealthy, and I have been enriched further, and I have need of nothing.' And you do not know that you are wretched, and miserable, and poor, and blind, and naked.

18 I urge you to buy from me gold, tested by fire, so that you may be enriched and may be clothed in white vestments, and so that the shame of your nakedness may disappear. And anoint your eyes with an eye salve, so that you may see.

19 Those whom I love, I rebuke and chastise. Therefore, be zealous and do penance.

20 Behold, I stand at the door and knock. If anyone will hear my voice and will open the door to me, I will enter to him, and I will dine with him, and he with me.

21 Whoever prevails, I will grant to him to sit with me on my throne, just as I also have overcome and have sat down with my Father on his throne.

22 Whoever has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the Churches."

Revelation 4

1 After these things, I saw, and behold, a door was opened in heaven, and the voice that I heard speaking with me first was like a trumpet, saying: "Ascend to here, and I will reveal to you what must occur after these things."

2 And immediately I was in the Spirit. And behold, a throne had been placed in heaven, and there was One sitting upon the throne.

3 And the One who was sitting there was similar in appearance to a stone of jasper and sardius. And there was an iridescence surrounding the throne, in aspect similar to an emerald.

4 And surrounding the throne were twenty-four smaller thrones. And upon the thrones, twenty-four elders were sitting, clothed entirely in white vestments, and on their heads were gold crowns.

5 And from the throne, lightnings and voices and thunders went forth. And there were seven burning lamps before the throne, which are the seven spirits of God.

6 And in view of the throne, there was something that seemed like a sea of glass, similar to crystal. And in the middle of the throne, and all around the throne, there were four living creatures, full of eyes in front and in back.

7 And the first living creature resembled a lion, and the second living creature resembled a calf, and the third living creature had a face like a man, and the fourth living creature resembled a flying eagle.

8 And each of the four living creatures had upon them six wings, and all around and within they are full of eyes. And they took no rest, day or night, from saying: "Holy, Holy, Holy is the Lord God Almighty, who was, and who is, and who is to come."

9 And while those living creatures were giving glory and honor and blessings to the One sitting upon the throne, who lives forever and ever,

10 the twenty-four elders fell prostrate before the One sitting upon the throne, and they adored him who lives forever and ever, and they cast their crowns before the throne, saying:

11 "You are worthy, O Lord our God, to receive glory and honor and power. For you have created all things, and they became and were created because of your will."

Revelation 5

1 And in the right hand of the One sitting upon the throne, I saw a book, written inside and out, sealed with seven seals.

2 And I saw a strong Angel, proclaiming with a great voice, "Who is worthy to open the book and to break its seals?"

3 And no one was able, neither in heaven, nor on earth, nor under the earth, to open the book, nor to gaze upon it.

4 And I wept greatly because no one was found worthy to open the book, nor to see it.

5 And one of the elders said to me: "Weep not. Behold, the lion from the tribe of Judah, the root of David, has prevailed to open the book and to break its seven seals."

6 And I saw, and behold, in the midst of the throne and the four living creatures, and in the midst of the elders, a Lamb was standing, as if it were slain, having seven horns and seven eyes, which are the seven spirits of God, sent forth to all the earth.

7 And he approached and received the book from the right hand of the One sitting upon the throne.

8 And when he had opened the book, the four living creatures and the twenty-four elders fell down before the Lamb, each having stringed instruments, as well as golden bowls full of fragrances, which are the prayers of the saints.

9 And they were singing a new canticle, saying: "O Lord, you are worthy to receive the book and to open its seals, because you were slain and have redeemed us for God, by your blood, from every tribe and language and people and nation.

10 And you have made us into a kingdom and into priests for our God, and we shall reign over the earth."

11 And I saw, and I heard the voice of many Angels surrounding the throne and the living creatures and the elders, (and their number was thousands of thousands)

12 saying with a great voice: "The Lamb who was slain is worthy to receive power, and divinity, and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing."

13 And every creature that is in heaven, and on earth, and under the earth, and all that is within the sea: I heard them all saying: "To the One sitting upon the throne and to the Lamb be blessing, and honor, and glory, and authority, forever and ever."

14 And the four living creatures were saying, "Amen." And the twenty-four elders fell down on their faces, and they adored the One who lives forever and ever.

Revelation 6

1 And I saw that the Lamb had opened one of the seven seals. And I heard one of the four living creatures saying, in a voice like thunder: "Draw near and see."

2 And I saw, and behold, a white horse. And he who was sitting upon it was holding a bow, and a crown was given to him, and he went forth conquering, so that he might prevail.

3 And when he had opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature saying: "Draw near and see."

4 And another horse went forth, which was red. And it was granted to him who was sitting upon it that he would take peace from the earth, and that they would kill one another. And a great sword was given to him.

5 And when he had opened the third seal, I heard the third living creature saying: "Draw near and see." And behold, a black horse. And he who was sitting upon it was holding a balance in his hand.

6 And I heard something like a voice in the midst of the four living creatures saying, "A double measure of wheat for a denarius, and three double measures of barley for a denarius, but do no harm to wine and oil."

7 And when he had opened the fourth seal, I heard the voice of the fourth living creature saying: "Draw near and see."

8 And behold, a pale horse. And he who was sitting upon it, his name was Death, and Hell was following him. And authority was given to him over the four parts of the earth, to destroy by the sword, by famine, and by death, and by the creatures of the earth.

9 And when he had opened the fifth seal, I saw, under the altar, the souls of those who had been slain because of the Word of God and because of the testimony that they held.

10 And they were crying out with a loud voice, saying: "How long, O Holy and True Lord, will you not judge and not vindicate our blood against those who dwell upon the earth?"

11 And white robes were given to each of them. And they were told that they should rest for a brief time, until their fellow servants and their brothers, who were to be slain even as they were slain, would be completed.

12 And when he had opened the sixth seal, I saw, and behold, a great earthquake occurred. And the sun became black, like a haircloth sack, and the entire moon became like blood.

13 And the stars from heaven fell upon the earth, just as when a fig tree, shaken by a great wind, drops its immature figs.

14 And heaven receded, like a scroll being rolled up. And every mountain, and the islands, were moved from their places.

15 And the kings of the earth, and the rulers, and the military leaders, and the wealthy, and the strong, and everyone, servant and free, hid themselves in caves and among the rocks of the mountains.

16 And they said to the mountains and the rocks: "Fall over us and hide us from the face of the One sitting upon the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb.

17 For the great day of their wrath has arrived. And who will be able to stand?"

Revelation 7

1 After these things, I saw four Angels standing above the four corners of the earth, holding the four winds of the earth, so that they would not blow upon the earth, nor upon the sea, nor upon any tree.

2 And I saw another Angel ascending from the rising of the sun, having the Seal of the living God. And he cried out, in a great voice, to the four Angels to whom it was given to harm the earth and the sea,

3 saying: "Do no harm to the earth, nor to the sea, nor to the trees, until we seal the servants of our God on their foreheads."

4 And I heard the number of those who were sealed: one hundred and forty-four thousand sealed, out of every tribe of the sons of Israel.

5 From the tribe of Judah, twelve thousand were sealed. From the tribe of Ruben, twelve thousand were sealed. From the tribe of Gad, twelve thousand were sealed.

6 From the tribe of Asher, twelve thousand were sealed. From the tribe of Naphtali, twelve thousand were sealed. From the tribe of Manasseh, twelve thousand were sealed.

7 From the tribe of Simeon, twelve thousand were sealed. From the tribe of Levi, twelve thousand were sealed. From the tribe of Issachar, twelve thousand were sealed.

8 From the tribe of Zebulun, twelve thousand were sealed. From the tribe of Joseph, twelve thousand were sealed. From the tribe of Benjamin, twelve thousand were sealed.

9 After these things, I saw a great crowd, which no one could number, from all the nations and tribes and peoples and languages, standing before the throne and in sight of the Lamb, clothed in white robes, with palm branches in their hands.

10 And they cried out, with a great voice, saying: "Salvation is from our God, who sits upon the throne, and from the Lamb."

11 And all the Angels were standing around the throne, with the elders and the four living creatures. And they fell upon their faces in view of the throne, and they worshipped God,

12 saying: "Amen. Blessing and glory and wisdom and thanksgiving, honor and power and strength to our God, forever and ever. Amen."

13 And one of the elders responded and said to me: "These ones who are clothed in white robes, who are they? And where did they come from?"

14 And I said to him, "My lord, you know." And he said to me: "These are the ones who have come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and have made them white by the blood of the Lamb.

15 Therefore, they are before the throne of God, and they serve him, day and night, in his temple. And the One who sits upon the throne shall dwell over them.

16 They shall not hunger, nor shall they thirst, anymore. Neither shall the sun beat down upon them, nor any heat.

17 For the Lamb, who is in the midst of the throne, will rule over them, and he will lead them to the fountains of the waters of life. And God will wipe away every tear from their eyes."

Revelation 8

1 And when he had opened the seventh seal, there was silence in heaven for about half an hour.

2 And I saw seven Angels standing in the sight of God. And seven trumpets were given to them.

3 And another Angel approached, and he stood before the altar, holding a golden censer. And much incense was given to him, so that he might offer upon the golden altar, which is before the throne of God, the prayers of all the saints.

4 And the smoke of the incense of the prayers of the saints ascended, in the presence of God, from the hand of the Angel.

5 And the Angel received the golden censer, and he filled it from the fire of the altar, and he cast it down upon the earth, and there were thunders and voices and lightnings and a great earthquake.

6 And the seven Angels who hold the seven trumpets prepared themselves, in order to sound the trumpet.

7 And the first Angel sounded the trumpet. And there came hail and fire, mixed with blood; and it was cast down upon the earth. And a third part of the earth was burned, and a third part of the trees was entirely burned up, and all the green plants were burned.

8 And the second Angel sounded the trumpet. And something like a great mountain, burning with fire, was cast down into the sea. And a third part of the sea became like blood.

9 And a third part of the creatures that were living in the sea died. And a third part of the ships were destroyed.

10 And the third Angel sounded the trumpet. And a great star fell from heaven, burning like a torch. And it fell upon a third part of the rivers and upon the sources of water.

11 And the name of the star is called Wormwood. And a third part of the waters were turned into wormwood. And many men died from the waters, because they were made bitter.

12 And the fourth Angel sounded the trumpet. And a third part of the sun, and a third part of the moon, and a third part of the stars were struck, in such a way that a third part of them was obscured. And a third part of the day did not shine, and similarly the night.

13 And I saw, and I heard the voice of a lone eagle flying through the midst of heaven, calling with a great voice: "Woe, Woe, Woe, to the inhabitants of the earth, from the remaining voices of the three Angels, who will soon sound the trumpet!"

Revelation 9

1 And the fifth Angel sounded the trumpet. And I saw upon the earth, a star that had fallen from heaven, and the key to the well of the abyss was given to him.

2 And he opened the well of the abyss. And the smoke of the well ascended, like the smoke of a great furnace. And the sun and the air were obscured by the smoke of the well.

3 And locusts went forth from the smoke of the well into the earth. And power was given to them, like the power that the scorpions of the earth have.

4 And it was commanded of them that they must not harm the plants of the earth, nor anything green, nor any tree, but only those men who do not have the Seal of God upon their foreheads.

5 And it was given to them that they would not kill them, but that they would torture them for five months. And their torture was like the torture of a scorpion, when he strikes a man.

6 And in those days, men will seek death and they will not find it. And they will desire to die, and death will flee from them.

7 And the likenesses of the locusts resembled horses prepared for battle. And upon their heads were something like crowns similar to gold. And their faces were like the faces of men.

8 And they had hair like the hair of women. And their teeth were like the teeth of lions.

9 And they had breastplates like iron breastplates. And the noise of their wings was like the noise of many running horses, rushing to battle.

10 And they had tails similar to scorpions. And there were stingers in their tails, and these had the power to harm men for five months.

11 And they had over them a king, the Angel of the abyss, whose name in Hebrew is Doom; in Greek, Destroyer; in Latin, Exterminator.

12 One woe has gone out, but behold, there are still two woes approaching afterward.

13 And the sixth Angel sounded the trumpet. And I heard a lone voice from the four horns of the golden altar, which is before the eyes of God,

14 saying to the sixth Angel who had the trumpet: "Release the four Angels who were bound at the great river Euphrates."

15 And the four Angels were released, who had been prepared for that hour, and day, and month, and year, in order to kill one third part of men.

16 And the number of the army of horsemen was two hundred million. For I heard their number.

17 And I also saw the horses in the vision. And those who were sitting upon them had breastplates of fire and hyacinth and sulphur. And the heads of the horses were like the heads of lions. And from their mouths proceeded fire and smoke and sulphur.

18 And one third part of men were slain by these three afflictions: by the fire and by the smoke and by the sulphur, which proceeded from their mouths.

19 For the power of these horses is in their mouths and in their tails. For their tails resemble serpents, having heads; and it is with these that they cause harm.

20 And the rest of men, who were not slain by these afflictions, did not repent from the works of their hands, so that they would not worship demons, or idols of gold and silver and brass and stone and wood, which can neither see, nor hear, nor walk.

21 And they did not repent from their murders, nor from their drugs, nor from their fornication, nor from their thefts.

Revelation 10

1 And I saw another strong Angel, descending from heaven, clothed with a cloud. And a rainbow was upon his head, and his face was like the sun, and his feet were like columns of fire.

2 And he held in his hand a small open book. And he stationed his right foot upon the sea, and his left foot upon the land.

3 And he cried out with a great voice, in the manner of a lion roaring. And when he had cried out, seven thunders uttered their voices.

4 And when the seven thunders had uttered their voices, I was about to write. But I heard a voice from heaven, saying to me: "Seal the things that the seven thunders have spoken, and do not write them."

5 And the Angel, whom I saw standing upon the sea and upon the land, lifted up his hand toward heaven.

6 And he swore by the One who lives forever and ever, who created heaven, and the things that are in it; and the earth, and the things that are in it; and the sea, and the things that are in it: that the time will not be any longer,

7 but in the days of the voice of the seventh Angel, when he shall begin to sound the trumpet, the mystery of God will be completed, just as he has proclaimed in the Gospel, through his servants the Prophets.

8 And again, I heard a voice from heaven speaking with me and saying: "Go and receive the open book from the hand of the Angel who stands upon the sea and upon the land."

9 And I went to the Angel, saying to him that he should give the book to me. And he said to me: "Receive the book and consume it. And it shall cause bitterness in your stomach, but in your mouth it shall be sweet like honey."

10 And I received the book from the hand of the Angel, and I consumed it. And it was sweet like honey in my mouth. And when I had consumed it, my stomach was made bitter.

11 And he said to me, "It is necessary for you to prophesy again about many nations and peoples and languages and kings."

Revelation 11

1 And a reed, similar to a staff, was given to me. And it was said to me: "Rise up and measure the temple of God, and those who are worshiping in it, and the altar.

2 But the atrium, which is outside of the temple, set it aside and do not measure it, because it has been given over to the Gentiles. And they shall trample upon the Holy City for forty-two months.

3 And I will present my two witnesses, and they shall prophesy for one thousand two hundred and sixty days, clothed in sackcloth.

4 These are the two olive trees and the two lampstands, standing in the sight of the lord of the earth.

5 And if anyone will want to harm them, fire shall go forth from their mouths, and it shall devour their enemies. And if anyone will want to wound them, so must he be slain.

6 These have the power to close up the heavens, so that it may not rain during the days of their prophesying. And they have power over the waters, to convert them into blood, and to strike the earth with every kind of affliction as often as they will.

7 And when they will have finished their testimony, the beast that ascended from the abyss will make war against them, and will overcome them, and will kill them.

8 And their bodies shall lie in the streets of the Great City, which is figuratively called 'Sodom' and 'Egypt,' the place where their Lord also was crucified.

9 And those from the tribes and peoples and languages and nations shall be watching their bodies for three and one half days. And they shall not permit their bodies to be placed in tombs.

10 And the inhabitants of the earth will rejoice over them, and they will celebrate, and they will send gifts to one another, because these two prophets tortured those who were living upon the earth.

11 And after three and one half days, the spirit of life from God entered into them. And they stood upright on their feet. And a great fear fell over those who saw them.

12 And they heard a great voice from heaven, saying to them, "Ascend to here!" And they ascended into heaven on a cloud. And their enemies saw them.

13 And at that hour, a great earthquake occurred. And one tenth part of the City fell. And the names of the men slain in the earthquake were seven thousand. And the remainder were thrown into fear, and they gave glory to the God of heaven.

14 The second woe has gone out, but behold, the third woe approaches quickly.

15 And the seventh Angel sounded the trumpet. And there were great voices in heaven, saying: "The kingdom of this world has become our Lord's and his Christ's, and he shall reign forever and ever. Amen."

16 And the twenty-four elders, who sit on their thrones in the sight of God, fell upon their faces, and they adored God, saying:

17 "We give thanks to you, Lord God Almighty, who is, and who was, and who is to come. For you have taken your great power, and you have reigned.

18 And the nations became angry, but your wrath arrived, and the time for the dead to be judged, and to render a reward to your servants the prophets, and to the saints, and to those who fear your name, small and great, and to exterminate those who have corrupted the earth."

19 And the temple of God was opened in heaven. And the Ark of his Testament was seen in his temple. And there were lightnings and voices and thunders, and an earthquake, and great hail.

Revelation 12

1 And a great sign appeared in heaven: a woman clothed with the sun, and the moon was under her feet, and on her head was a crown of twelve stars.

2 And being with child, she cried out while giving birth, and she was suffering in order to give birth.

3 And another sign was seen in heaven. And behold, a great red dragon, having seven heads and ten horns, and on his heads were seven diadems.

4 And his tail drew down a third part of the stars of heaven and cast them to the earth. And the dragon stood before the woman, who was about to give birth, so that, when she had brought forth, he might devour her son.

5 And she brought forth a male child, who was soon to rule all the nations with an iron rod. And her son was taken up to God and to his throne.

6 And the woman fled into solitude, where a place was being held ready by God, so that they might pasture her in that place for one thousand two hundred and sixty days.

7 And there was a great battle in heaven. Michael and his Angels were battling with the dragon, and the dragon was fighting, and so were his angels.

8 But they did not prevail, and a place for them was no longer found in heaven.

9 And he was thrown out, that great dragon, that ancient serpent, who is called the devil and Satan, who seduces the whole world. And he was thrown down to the earth, and his angels were cast down with him.

10 And I heard a great voice in heaven, saying: "Now have arrived salvation and virtue and the kingdom of our God and the power of his Christ. For the accuser of our brothers has been cast down, he who accused them before our God day and night.

11 And they overcame him by the blood of the Lamb and by the word of his testimony. And they loved not their own lives, even unto death.

12 Because of this, rejoice, O heavens, and all who dwell within it. Woe to the earth and to the sea! For the devil has descended to you, holding great anger, knowing that he has little time."

13 And after the dragon saw that he had been thrown down to the earth, he pursued the woman who brought forth the male child.

14 And the two wings of a great eagle were given to the woman, so that she might fly away, into the desert, to her place, where she is being nourished for a time, and times, and half a time, from the face of the serpent.

15 And the serpent sent out from his mouth, after the woman, water like a river, so that he might cause her to be carried away by the river.

16 But the earth assisted the woman. And the earth opened her mouth and absorbed the river, which the dragon sent out from his mouth.

17 And the dragon was angry at the woman. And so he went away to do battle with the remainder of her offspring, those who keep the commandments of God and who hold to the testimony of Jesus Christ.

18 And he stood upon the sand of the sea.

Revelation 13

1 And I saw a beast ascending from the sea, having seven heads and ten horns, and upon its horns were ten diadems, and upon its heads were names of blasphemy.

2 And the beast that I saw was similar to a leopard, and its feet were like the feet of a bear, and its mouth was like the mouth of a lion. And the dragon gave his own power and great authority to it.

3 And I saw that one of its heads seemed to be slain unto death, but his deadly wound was healed. And the entire world was in wonder following the beast.

4 And they worshiped the dragon, who gave authority to the beast. And they worshiped the beast, saying: "Who is like the beast? And who would be able to fight with it?"

5 And there was given to it a mouth, speaking great things and blasphemies. And authority was given to him to act for forty-two months.

6 And he opened his mouth in blasphemies against God, to blaspheme his name and his tabernacle and those who dwell in heaven.

7 And it was given to him to make war with the saints and to overcome them. And authority was given to him over every tribe and people and language and nation.

8 And all who inhabit the earth worshiped the beast, those whose names have not been written, from the origin of the world, in the Book of Life of the Lamb who was slain.

9 If anyone has an ear, let him hear.

10 Whoever will be led into captivity, into captivity he goes. Whoever will kill with the sword, with the sword he must be killed. Here is the patient endurance and faith of the Saints.

11 And I saw another beast ascending from the land. And she had two horns like the Lamb, but she was speaking like the dragon.

12 And she acted with all the authority of the first beast in his sight. And she caused the earth, and those dwelling in it, to worship the first beast, whose deadly wound was healed.

13 And she accomplished great signs, even so that she would cause fire to descend from the sky to the earth in the sight of men.

14 And she seduced those living on the earth, by means of the signs that were given to her to perform in the sight of the beast, saying to those dwelling on the earth that they should make an image of the beast who had a wound of the sword and yet lived.

15 And it was given to her to give a spirit to the image of the beast, so that the image of the beast would speak. And she acted so that whoever would not worship the image of the beast would be slain.

16 And she will cause everyone, small and great, wealthy and poor, free and servant, to have a character on their right hand or on their foreheads,

17 so that no one may buy or sell, unless he has the character, or the name of the beast, or the number of his name.

18 Here is wisdom. Whoever has intelligence, let him determine the number of the beast. For it is the number of a man, and his number is six hundred and sixty-six.

Revelation 14

1 And I saw, and behold, the Lamb was standing above mount Zion, and with him were one hundred and forty-four thousand, having his name and the name of his Father written on their foreheads.

2 And I heard a voice from heaven, like the voice of many waters, and like the voice of a great thunder. And the voice that I heard was like that of singers, while playing on their stringed instruments.

3 And they were singing what seemed like a new canticle before the throne and before the four living creatures and the elders. And no one was able to recite the canticle, except those one hundred and forty-four thousand, who were redeemed from the earth.

4 These are the ones who were not defiled with women, for they are Virgins. These follow the Lamb wherever he will go. These were redeemed from men as the first-fruits for God and for the Lamb.

5 And in their mouth, no lie was found, for they are without flaw before the throne of God.

6 And I saw another Angel, flying through the midst of heaven, holding the eternal Gospel, so as to evangelize those sitting upon the earth and those of every nation and tribe and language and people,

7 saying with a loud voice: "Fear the Lord, and give honor to him, for the hour of his judgment has arrived. And worship him who made heaven and earth, the sea and the sources of water."

8 And another Angel followed, saying: "Fallen, fallen is Babylon the great, who inebriated all nations with the wine of her wrath and of fornication."

9 And the third Angel followed them, saying with a great voice: "If anyone has worshiped the beast, or his image, or has received his character on his forehead or on his hand,

10 he shall drink also from the wine of the wrath of God, which has been mixed with strong wine in the cup of his wrath, and he shall be tortured with fire and sulphur in the sight of the holy Angels and before the sight of the Lamb.

11 And the smoke of their torments shall ascend forever and ever. And they shall have no rest, day or night, those who have worshiped the beast or his image, or who have received the character of his name."

12 Here is the patient endurance of the Saints, those who keep the commandments of God and the faith of Jesus.

13 And I heard a voice from heaven, saying to me: "Write: Blessed are the dead, who die in the Lord, now and hereafter, says the Spirit, so that they may find rest from their labors. For their works follow them."

14 And I saw, and behold, a white cloud. And upon the cloud was one sitting, resembling a son of man, having a crown of gold on his head, and a sharp sickle in his hand.

15 And another Angel went forth from the temple, crying out in a great voice to the one sitting upon the cloud: "Send out your sickle and reap! For the hour of reaping has arrived, because the harvest of the earth has ripened."

16 And the one who was sitting upon the cloud sent out his sickle to the earth, and the earth was reaped.

17 And another Angel went forth from the temple that is in heaven; he also had a sharp sickle.

18 And another Angel went forth from the altar, who held power over fire. And he cried out in a great voice to him who held the sharp sickle, saying: "Send out your sharp sickle, and harvest the clusters of grapes from the vineyard of the earth, because its grapes have matured."

19 And the Angel sent out his sharp sickle to the earth, and he harvested the vineyard of the earth, and he cast it into the great basin of the wrath of God.

20 And the basin was trodden beyond the city, and blood went forth from the basin, even as high as the harnesses of horses, out to one thousand six hundred stadia.

Revelation 15

1 And I saw another sign in heaven, great and wondrous: seven Angels, holding the seven last afflictions. For with them, the wrath of God is completed.

2 And I saw something like a sea of glass mixed with fire. And those who had overcome the beast and his image and the number of his name, were standing upon the sea of glass, holding the harps of God,

3 and singing the canticle of Moses, the servant of God, and the canticle of the Lamb, saying: "Great and wondrous are your works, Lord God Almighty. Just and true are your ways, King of all ages.

4 Who shall not fear you, O Lord, and magnify your name? For you alone are blessed. For all nations shall approach and adore in your sight, because your judgments are manifest."

5 And after these things, I saw, and behold, the temple of the tabernacle of the testimony in heaven was opened.

6 And the seven Angels went forth from the temple, holding the seven afflictions, clothed with clean white linen, and girded around the chest with wide golden belts.

7 And one of the four living creatures gave to the seven Angels seven golden bowls, filled with the wrath of God, of the One who lives forever and ever.

8 And the temple was filled with smoke from the majesty of God and from his power. And no one was able to enter into the temple, until the seven afflictions of the seven Angels were completed.

Revelation 16

1 And I heard a great voice from the temple, saying to the seven Angels: "Go forth and pour out the seven bowls of the wrath of God upon the earth."

2 And the first Angel went forth and poured out his bowl upon the earth. And a severe and most grievous wound occurred upon the men who had the character of the beast, and upon those who adored the beast or its image.

3 And the second Angel poured out his bowl upon the sea. And it became like the blood of the dead, and every living creature in the sea died.

4 And the third Angel poured out his bowl upon the rivers and the sources of water, and these became blood.

5 And I heard the Angel of the waters saying: "You are just, O Lord, who is and who was: the Holy One who has judged these things.

6 For they have shed the blood of the Saints and the Prophets, and so you have given them blood to drink. For they deserve this."

7 And from the altar, I heard another one, saying, "Even now, O Lord God Almighty, your judgments are true and just."

8 And the fourth Angel poured out his bowl upon the sun. And it was given to him to afflict men with heat and fire.

9 And men were scorched by the great heat, and they blasphemed the name of God, who holds power over these afflictions, but they did not repent, so as to give him glory.

10 And the fifth Angel poured out his bowl upon the throne of the beast. And his kingdom became darkened, and they gnawed at their tongues out of anguish.

11 And they blasphemed the God of heaven, because of their anguish and wounds, but they did not repent from their works.

12 And the sixth Angel poured out his bowl upon that great river Euphrates. And its water dried up, so that a way might be prepared for the kings from the rising of the sun.

13 And I saw, from the mouth of the dragon, and from the mouth of the beast, and from the mouth of the false prophetess, three unclean spirits go out in the manner of frogs.

14 For these are the spirits of the demons that were causing the signs. And they advance to the kings of the entire earth, to gather them for battle on the great day of Almighty God.

15 "Behold, I arrive like a thief. Blessed is he who is vigilant and who preserves his vestment, lest he walk naked and they see his disgrace."

16 And he shall gather them together at a place which is called, in Hebrew, Armageddon.

17 And the seventh Angel poured out his bowl upon the air. And a great voice went out of the temple from the throne, saying: "It is done."

18 And there were lightnings and voices and thunders. And a great earthquake occurred, of a kind such as has never happened since men have been upon the earth, so great was this kind of earthquake.

19 And the Great City became divided into three parts. And the cities of the Gentiles fell. And Babylon the great came to mind before God, to give her the cup of the wine of the indignation of his wrath.

20 And every island fled away, and the mountains were not found.

21 And hail as heavy as a talent descended from the sky upon men. And men blasphemed God, because of the affliction of the hail, for it was exceedingly great.

Revelation 17

1 And one of the seven Angels, those who hold the seven bowls, approached and spoke with me, saying: "Come, I will show you the condemnation of the great harlot, who sits upon many waters.

2 With her, the kings of the earth have fornicated. And those who inhabit the earth have been inebriated by the wine of her prostitution."

3 And he carried me away in spirit to the desert. And I saw a woman sitting upon a scarlet beast, filled with names of blasphemy, having seven heads and ten horns.

4 And the woman was clothed all around with purple and scarlet, and adorned with gold and precious stones and pearls, holding a golden cup in her hand, filled with the abomination and with the filth of her fornication.

5 And a name was written upon her forehead: Mystery, Babylon the great, the mother of the fornications and the abominations of the earth.

6 And I saw that the woman was inebriated from the blood of the saints and from the blood of the martyrs of Jesus. And I was amazed, when I had seen her, with a great wonder.

7 And the Angel said to me: "Why do you wonder? I will tell you the mystery of the woman, and of the beast that carries her, which has seven heads and ten horns.

8 The beast that you saw, was, and is not, and is soon to ascend from the abyss. And he goes forth unto destruction. And the inhabitants upon the earth (those whose names have not been written in the Book of Life from the foundation of the world) shall be amazed upon seeing the beast who was and is not.

9 And this is for one who understands, who has wisdom: the seven heads are seven mountains, upon which the woman sits, and they are seven kings.

10 Five have fallen, one is, and the other has not yet arrived. And when he arrives, he must remain for a brief time.

11 And the beast who was, and is not, the same is also the eighth, and he is of the seven, and he goes forth unto destruction.

12 And the ten horns that you saw are ten kings; these have not yet received a kingdom, but they shall receive authority, as if they were kings, for one hour, after the beast.

13 These hold to one plan, and they shall hand over their power and authority to the beast.

14 These shall fight against the Lamb, and the Lamb shall conquer them. For he is the Lord of lords and the King of kings. And those who are with him are called, and chosen, and faithful."

15 And he said to me: "The waters that you saw, where the harlot sits, are peoples and nations and languages.

16 And the ten horns that you saw on the beast, these shall hate the woman who fornicates, and they shall make her desolate and naked, and they shall chew her flesh, and they shall burn her completely with fire.

17 For God has granted to their hearts that they may do to her whatever is pleasing, so that they may give their kingdom to the beast, until the words of God may be completed.

18 And the woman that you saw is the great City, which holds a kingdom above that of the kings of the earth."

Revelation 18

1 And after these things, I saw another Angel, descending from heaven, having great authority. And the earth was illuminated by his glory.

2 And he cried out with strength, saying: "Fallen, fallen is Babylon the great. And she has become the habitation of demons, and the keepsake of every unclean spirit, and the possession of every unclean and hateful flying thing.

3 For all the nations have imbibed the wine of the wrath of her fornication. And the kings of the earth have fornicated with her. And the merchants of the earth have become wealthy by the power of her pleasures."

4 And I heard another voice from heaven, saying: "Go away from her, my people, so that you may not be participants in her pleasures, and so that you may not be recipients of her afflictions.

5 For her sins have pierced through even to heaven, and the Lord has remembered her iniquities.

6 Render to her, as she has also rendered to you. And repay her doubly, according to her works. Mix for her a double portion, in the cup with which she mixed.

7 As much as she has glorified herself and lived in pleasure, so much so give to her torment and grief. For in her heart, she has said: 'I am enthroned as queen,' and, 'I am not a widow,' and, 'I shall not see sorrow.'

8 For this reason, her afflictions shall arrive in one day: death and grief and famine. And she shall be burned with fire. For God, who will judge her, is strong.

9 And the kings of the earth, who have fornicated with her and lived in luxury, shall weep and mourn for themselves over her, when they see the smoke of her conflagration,

10 standing far away, out of fear of her torments, saying: 'Woe! Woe! to Babylon, that great city, that strong city. For in one hour, your judgment has arrived.'

11 And the businessmen of the earth shall weep and mourn over her, because no one will buy their merchandise anymore:

12 merchandise of gold and silver and precious stones and pearls, and of fine linen and purple and silk and scarlet, and of every citrus tree wood, and of every tool of ivory, and of every tool from precious stone and brass and iron and marble,

13 and of cinnamon and black cardamom, and of fragrances and ointments and incense, and of wine and oil and fine flour and wheat, and of beasts of burden and sheep and horses and four-wheeled wagons, and of slaves and the souls of men.

14 And the fruits of the desires of your soul have gone away from you. And all things fat and splendid have perished from you. And they shall never find these things again.

15 The merchants of these things, who were made wealthy, shall stand far away from her, out of fear of her torments, weeping and mourning,

16 and saying: 'Woe! Woe! to that great city, which was clothed with fine linen and purple and scarlet, and which was adorned with gold and precious stones and pearls.'

17 For such great wealth was brought to destitution in one hour. And every shipmaster, and all who navigate on lakes, and mariners, and those who work at sea, stood far away.

18 And they cried out, seeing the place of her conflagration, saying: 'What city resembles this great city?'

19 And they cast dust upon their heads. And they cried out, weeping and mourning, saying: 'Woe! Woe! to that great city, by which all who had ships at sea were made rich from her treasures. For she has been made desolate in one hour.

20 Exult over her, O heaven, O holy Apostles and Prophets. For God has judged your judgment upon her.' "

21 And a certain strong Angel took up a stone, similar to a great millstone, and he cast it into the sea, saying: "With this force shall Babylon, that great city, be cast down. And she shall never be found again.

22 And the sound of singers, and musicians, and flute and trumpet players shall not be heard in you again. And every artisan of every art shall not be found in you again. And the sound of the mill shall not be heard in you again.

23 And the light of the lamp shall not shine in you again. And the voice of the groom and of the bride shall not be heard in you anymore. For your merchants were the leaders of the earth. For all the nations were led astray by your drugs.

24 And in her was found the blood of the Prophets and of the Saints, and of all who were slain upon the earth."

Revelation 19

1 After these things, I heard something like the voice of many multitudes in heaven, saying: "Alleluia! Praise and glory and power is for our God.

2 For true and just are his judgments, he who has judged the great harlot that corrupted the earth by her prostitution. And he has vindicated the blood of his servants from her hands."

3 And again, they said: "Alleluia! For her smoke ascends forever and ever."

4 And the twenty-four elders and the four living creatures fell down and worshiped God, sitting upon the throne, saying: "Amen! Alleluia!"

5 And a voice went out from the throne, saying: "Express praise to our God, all you his servants, and you who fear him, small and great."

6 And I heard something like the voice of a great multitude, and like the voice of many waters, and like the voice of great thunders, saying: "Alleluia! For the Lord our God, the Almighty, has reigned.

7 Let us be glad and exult. And let us give glory to him. For the marriage feast of the Lamb has arrived, and his wife has prepared herself."

8 And it was granted to her that she should cover herself with fine linen, splendid and white. For the fine linen is the justifications of the Saints.

9 And he said to me: "Write: Blessed are those who have been called to the wedding feast of the Lamb." And he said to me, "These words of God are true."

10 And I fell down before his feet, to adore him. And he said to me: "Be careful not to do so. I am your fellow servant, and I am among your brothers, who hold to the testimony of Jesus. Adore God. For the testimony of Jesus is a spirit of prophecy."

11 And I saw heaven opened, and behold, a white horse. And he who was sitting upon it was called Faithful and True. And with justice does he judge and fight.

12 And his eyes are like a flame of fire, and on his head are many diadems, having a name written, which no one knows except himself.

13 And he was clothed with a vestment sprinkled with blood. And his name is called: THE WORD OF GOD.

14 And the armies that are in heaven were following him on white horses, clothed in fine linen, white and clean.

15 And from his mouth proceeded a sharp two-edged sword, so that with it he may strike the nations. And he shall rule them with an iron rod. And he treads the winepress of the fury of the wrath of God Almighty.

16 And he has on his garment and on his thigh written: KING OF KINGS AND Lord OF LORDS.

17 And I saw a certain Angel, standing in the sun. And he cried out with a great voice, saying to all the birds that were flying through the midst of the sky, "Come and gather together for the great supper of God,

18 so that you may eat the flesh of kings, and the flesh of tribunes, and the flesh of the strong, and the flesh of horses and those sitting on them, and the flesh of all: free and servant, small and great."

19 And I saw the beast and the kings of the earth and their armies, having been gathered together to do battle against him who was sitting upon the horse, and against his army.

20 And the beast was apprehended, and with him the false prophetess, who in his presence caused the signs, by which she seduced those who accepted the character of the beast and who worshiped his image. These two were cast alive into the pool of fire burning with sulphur.

21 And the others were slain by the sword that proceeds from the mouth of him who was sitting upon the horse. And all the birds were sated with their flesh.

Revelation 20

1 And I saw an Angel, descending from heaven, holding in his hand the key of the abyss and a great chain.

2 And he apprehended the dragon, the ancient serpent, who is the devil and Satan, and he bound him for a thousand years.

3 And he cast him into the abyss, and he closed and sealed it, so that he would no longer seduce the nations, until the thousand years are completed. And after these things, he must be released for a brief time.

4 And I saw thrones. And they sat upon them. And judgment was given to them. And the souls of those beheaded because of the testimony of Jesus and because of the Word of God, and who did not adore the beast, nor his image, nor accept his character on their foreheads or on their hands: they lived and they reigned with Christ for a thousand years.

5 The rest of the dead did not live, until the thousand years are completed. This is the First Resurrection.

6 Blessed and holy is he who takes part in the First Resurrection. Over these the second death has no power. But they shall be priests of God and of Christ, and they shall reign with him for a thousand years.

7 And when the thousand years will have been completed, Satan shall be released from his prison, and he will go out and seduce the nations which are upon the four quarters of the earth, Gog and Magog. And he will gather them together for battle, those whose number is like the sand of the sea.

8 And they climbed across the breadth of the earth, and they encompassed the camp of the Saints and the Beloved City.

9 And fire from God descended from heaven and devoured them. And the devil, who seduced them, was cast into the pool of fire and sulphur,

10 where both the beast and the false prophetess shall be tortured, day and night, forever and ever.

11 And I saw a great white throne, and One sitting upon it, from whose sight earth and heaven fled, and no place was found for them.

12 And I saw the dead, great and small, standing in view of the throne. And books were opened. And another Book was opened, which is the Book of Life. And the dead were judged by those things that had been written in the books, according to their works.

13 And the sea gave up the dead who were in it. And death and Hell gave up their dead who were in them. And they were judged, each one according to his works.

14 And Hell and death were cast into the pool of fire. This is the second death.

15 And whoever was not found written in the Book of Life was cast into the pool of fire.

Revelation 21

1 I saw the new heaven and the new earth. For the first heaven and the first earth passed away, and the sea is no more.

2 And I, John, saw the Holy City, the New Jerusalem, descending out of heaven from God, prepared like a bride adorned for her husband.

3 And I heard a great voice from the throne, saying: "Behold the tabernacle of God with men. And he will dwell with them, and they will be his people. And God himself will be their God with them.

4 And God will wipe away every tear from their eyes. And death shall be no more. And neither mourning, nor crying out, nor grief shall be anymore. For the first things have passed away."

5 And the One who was sitting upon the throne, said, "Behold, I make all things new." And he said to me, "Write, for these words are entirely faithful and true."

6 And he said to me: "It is done. I am the Alpha and the Omega, the Beginning and the End. To those who thirst, I will give freely from the fountain of the water of life.

7 Whoever prevails shall possess these things. And I will be his God, and he shall be my son.

8 But the fearful, and the unbelieving, and the abominable, and murderers, and fornicators, and drug users, and idolaters, and all liars, these shall be a part of the pool burning with fire and sulphur, which is the second death."

9 And one of the seven Angels, those holding the bowls filled with the seven last afflictions, approached and spoke with me, saying: "Come, and I will show you the bride, the wife of the Lamb."

10 And he took me up in spirit to a great and high mountain. And he showed me the Holy City Jerusalem, descending out of heaven from God,

11 having the glory of God. And its light was like that of a precious stone, even like that of the jasper stone or like crystal.

12 And it had a wall, great and high, having twelve gates. And at the gates were twelve Angels. And names were written upon them, which are the names of the twelve tribes of the sons of Israel.

13 On the East were three gates, and on the North were three gates, and on the South were three gates, and on the West were three gates.

14 And the wall of the City had twelve foundations. And upon them were the twelve names of the twelve Apostles of the Lamb.

15 And he who was speaking with me was holding a golden measuring reed, in order to measure the City, and its gates and wall.

16 And the city is laid out as a square, and so its length is as great as the width. And he measured the city with the golden reed for twelve thousand stadia, and its length and height and breadth were equal.

17 And he measured its wall as one hundred and forty-four cubits, the measure of a man, which is of an Angel.

18 And the structure of its wall was of jasper stone. Yet truly, the city itself was of pure gold, similar to pure glass.

19 And the foundations of the wall of the city were adorned with every kind of precious stone. The first foundation was of jasper, the second was of sapphire, the third was of chalcedony, the fourth was of emerald,

20 the fifth was of sardonyx, the sixth was of sardius, the seventh was of chrysolite, the eighth was of beryl, the ninth was of topaz, the tenth was of chrysoprasus, the eleventh was of jacinth, the twelfth was of amethyst.

21 And the twelve gates are twelve pearls, one for each, so that each gate was made from a single pearl. And the main street of the city was of pure gold, similar to transparent glass.

22 And I saw no temple in it. For the Lord God Almighty is its temple, and the Lamb.

23 And the city has no need of sun or moon to shine in it. For the glory of God has illuminated it, and the Lamb is its lamp.

24 And the nations shall walk by its light. And the kings of the earth shall bring their glory and honor into it.

25 And its gates shall not be closed throughout the day, for there shall be no night in that place.

26 And they shall bring the glory and honor of the nations into it.

27 There shall not enter into it anything defiled, nor anything causing an abomination, nor anything false, but only those who have been written in the Book of Life of the Lamb.

Revelation 22

1 And he showed me the river of the water of life, shining like crystal, proceeding from the throne of God and of the Lamb.

2 In the midst of its main street, and on both sides of the river, was the Tree of Life, bearing twelve fruits, offering one fruit for each month, and the leaves of the tree are for the health of the nations.

3 And every curse shall be no more. But the throne of God and of the Lamb will be in it, and his servants shall serve him.

4 And they shall see his face. And his name shall be on their foreheads.

5 And night shall be no more. And they will not need the light of a lamp, nor the light of the sun, because the Lord God will illuminate them. And they shall reign forever and ever.

6 And he said to me: "These words are entirely faithful and true." And the Lord, the God of the spirits of the prophets, sent his Angel to reveal to his servant what must occur soon:

7 "For behold, I am approaching quickly! Blessed is he who keeps the words of the prophecy of this book."

8 And I, John, heard and saw these things. And, after I had heard and seen, I fell down, so as to adore before the feet of the Angel, who was revealing these things to me.

9 And he said to me: "Be careful not to do so. For I am your fellow servant, and I am among your brothers the prophets, and among those who keep the words of the prophecy of this book. Adore God."

10 And he said to me: "Do not seal the words of the prophecy of this book. For the time is near.

11 Whoever does harm, he might still do harm. And whoever is filthy, he might still be filthy. And whoever is just, he may still be just. And one who is holy, he may still be holy."

12 "Behold, I am approaching quickly! And my repayment is with me, to render to each one according to his works.

13 I am the Alpha and the Omega, the First and the Last, the Beginning and the End."

14 Blessed are those who wash their robes in the blood of the Lamb. So may they have a right to the tree of life; so may they enter through the gates into the City.

15 Outside are dogs, and drug users, and homosexuals, and murderers, and those who serve idols, and all who love and do what is false.

16 "I, Jesus, have sent my Angel, to testify to these things for you among the Churches. I am the Root and the Origin of David, the bright morning Star."

17 And the Spirit and the Bride say: "Draw near." And whoever hears, let him say: "Draw near." And whoever thirsts, let him draw near. And whoever is willing, let him accept the water of life, freely.

18 For I call as witnesses all listeners of the words of the prophecy of this book. If anyone will have added to these, God will add upon him the afflictions written in this book.

19 And if anyone will have taken away from the words of the book of this prophecy, God will take away his portion from the Book of Life, and from the Holy City, and from these things which have been written in this book.

20 He who offers testimony to these things, says: "Even now, I am approaching quickly." Amen. Come, Lord Jesus.

21 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.